<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<d:book xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <d:info>
        <d:title>Paul's Book Log</d:title>
        <d:subtitle>2010 - 2019</d:subtitle>
        <d:abstract>
            <d:para>These are the criteria by which I grade a book. A grade of <d:emphasis
                role="bold">1</d:emphasis> usually means that I have made a definite decision
                not to finish a book. Of course, there are some books that I start and set aside.
                But I only enter the book if I have finished it or determined it is not worth
                finishing.</d:para>
            <d:formalpara>
                <d:title>Grading Scale</d:title>
                <d:para>
                    <d:simplelist>
                        <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">1</d:emphasis> - Don't bother</d:member>
                        <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">2</d:emphasis> - Generally a waste of
                            time</d:member>
                        <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">3</d:emphasis> - OK</d:member>
                        <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">4</d:emphasis> - Can recommend the book
                            to others</d:member>
                        <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">5</d:emphasis> - Intend to read the book
                            again</d:member>
                    </d:simplelist>
                </d:para>
            </d:formalpara>
        </d:abstract>
    </d:info>
    <d:chapter>
        <d:title>2010</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Quiet Warrior</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Thomas Buell</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/9/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Stacy gave this book to me for Christmas, and just like in 2009, I started the
                year off with a book about the Navy. One of my favorite books about the Civil War
                was <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">The Warrior
                    Generals</emphasis> by Commander Thomas Buell (ret.) It was a thought provoking
                examination of four generals, two Union and two Confederate. And it was a delight to
                read. Perhaps more to be expected by a retired Naval officer turned historian, this
                is the biography of Admiral Raymond Spruance, a man of towering accomplishment who
                is generally overshadowed by the more flamboyant figures of WWII. But CDR Buell's
                writing is just as clear and compelling in this book as it was in <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">The Warrior
                    Generals</emphasis>. It is difficult to pinpoint just what it is about his style
                that I find so compelling. As a career Naval Officer, he has an insider's view into
                Admiral Spruance's career, yet I believe this book would be as accessible to a
                civilian as it is to a former Naval Officer. He evaluates Adm Spruance's actions
                with a professional eye, and provides judgement on any controversial actions or
                decisions in just a few well crafted sentences. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Apologia Pro Vita Sua</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>John Henry Cardinal
                    Newman</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/11/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>John Henry Cardinal Newman's account of his conversion to the Catholic Church.
                The style is very dry and cerebral; and Cardinal Newman seems sensitive to charges
                that he had been less than forthright in his days as an Anglican priest. In
                contemporary America, with its celebration of the supremacy of the individual and
                emphasis on the individual's relationship with God, this tone seems defensive. But
                in early Victorian Britain, with its ingrained prejudice against Catholicism and
                belief in English superiority, the tone is perhaps more understandable. Indeed,
                Cardinal Newman retains his British sense of upright behavior, refusing to
                proselytize for the Catholic faith. Rather he gives an honest account of how,
                through his research into the teachings of the Church fathers, he came to view the
                Anglican Church as heretical. This account really may only appeal to a serious
                theologian. Where his account is of interest to a broader audience is in his
                criticism of the "Liberal" party in the Anglican Church and the danger of the
                liberal promotion of personal behavior and rejection of dogma. Given the current
                state of the Anglican Church, Cardinal Newman's warnings seem to be
                confirmed.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Into the Fire</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>LCDR John Owen</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/12/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Lieutenant Commander John Owen was the team Chaplain for the Navy Football team
                for the 2007 season. The book is really a collection of his pre-game talks to the
                team combined with his reflections on his role as a religious teacher in a secular
                institution. Personally, the talks aren't interesting. What is interesting are the
                inside observations of the players and coaches who participated in one of the best
                season's in Navy football history.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">In the Aftermath: Provocations and
                    Lamentations</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>David Bentley
                    Hart</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/12/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">An engaging and stimulating collection of
                essays by a contemporary Orthodox theologian. I found his essay regarding Pope John
                Paul II's outreach to the Orthodox church to be particularly insightful. Mr. Hart is
                a formidable opponent of secular materialists and militant Darwinists. This can make
                for delightfully entertaining passages. In this season of Lent, I wonder whether to
                admire his spirited defense of Christianity or blush at his refusal to turn the
                other cheek to his enemies. While this observation is made somewhat light-heartedly,
                it is a point to ponder. Christian humility certainly does not preclude a spirited
                defense or promotion of Christianity. But when the tone descends to the level of
                squabbling academics, has a line between humility and pride been traversed? But the
                reading was entertaining enough that I won't take him to task too severely. Reading
                these essays is also a great way to improve your vocabulary. Mr. Hart most assuredly
                does not believe in writing at a layman's level. Turning, at random to a single page
                (which happened to fall in the essay "The Laughter of the Philosophers") consisting
                of 38 lines, the following words provide an example of his formidable vocabulary:
                obtundently, perspicuous, caliginous, turgidity, splenetic </para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">What Hath God Wrought: The Transformation of
                    America, 1815-1848</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Daniel Walker
                    Howe</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/19/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An edition of the Oxford History of the United States; the same series that
                includes James McPherson's Battle Cry of Freedom. Stephen Brumbaugh lent this book
                to me. A comprehensive examination of the military, political, religious, artistic
                and social history of the United States from the end of the War of 1812 to the end
                of the Mexican War. In some respects, a very balanced account with no revisionist
                economic or social theory to explain the events. He details both the great
                accomplishments and the glaring iniquities of the period. Perhaps the greatest
                strength of this book is coverage of the role that religion played in America during
                this period. Perhaps because my interest has always been more for military history,
                religion tends to be overlooked unless it is plainly unavoidable (such as in dealing
                with the Mormon migration to Utah). For example, in all the books by Bruce Catton, I
                don't remember any discussion on the religious influences or practices of either the
                Union or the Confederacy. Mr. Howe does a nice job in showing how religious beliefs
                and practices led to concrete social and political results.</d:para>
            <d:para>However, there are some glaring weaknesses as well. While purporting to provide
                a narrative of the period, he never the less is not shy about passing judgement upon
                people and their actions. For example, during the Battle of New Orleans, the British
                commander assigned one of his Irish units the task of carrying bundles of brush to
                fill in the ditch in front of the American lines. For whatever reason, the commander
                of the Irish unit failed to make the arrangements and the subsequent British attack
                was badly hampered. The dereliction of this commander is self evident even to
                someone not versed in military history, and simply describing the situation allows
                anyone with any intelligence to draw the appropriate conclusion. But Mr. Howe still
                provides his personal judgement on the Irish commander's culpability. And the
                yardstick Mr. Howe uses to make his judgements is to compare are modern conventions
                of right and wrong. This shows him to fall in the "progressive" school of historians
                who view all history as a long development to the present "enlightened" time. In Mr.
                Howe's defense, this is probably the most typical outlook of modern historians. The
                problem with this approach is that many times the historian is quick to see the
                faults of his subject without evaluating how the virtues of the subject compare with
                the faults of the author and his society.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Forged Coupon</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Leo Tolstoy</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/20/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This is a very short work detailing how a single act of selfishness causes a
                chain of consequences. This serves as a useful vehicle for Tolstoy to examine some
                of the ignoble facets of the Russian society of his day. The chain of misfortunes,
                however, also spurs some positive actions, mostly by characters who share Tolstoy's
                personal view of Christianity and its place for social reform. The problem with
                Tolstoy's view of Christianity is that it is essentially a Protestant view in which
                the individual is capable of working out his relationship with Christ and that the
                Church is generally a hindrance to this process. But G.K. Chesterton offers a strong
                critique of this view: "My point is that the world did not tire of the Church's
                ideal, but of its reality. Monasteries were impugned not for the chastity of monks,
                but for the unchastity of monks. Christianity was unpopular not because of the
                humility, but the arrogance of Christians. Certainly if the church failed it was
                largely through the churchmen." In each and every age, the Church and society in
                general are composed of the saints, the ordinary and the wicked. In each age, the
                saints carry forward the holiness of the Church despite the wickedness of the bad
                and the indifference of the ordinary. When an individual, or a group decides to
                leave the Church on account of the bad and the indifference, they also leave behind
                the saints. When they start their own church (as the Lutherans, Anglicans, etc.)
                they wind up in the same boat, only with a smaller crew. And when eventually one or
                more individuals in the protesting church leaves on account of the bad and
                indifferent, then a cascading chain of splintering churches is the result. So while
                Tolstoy is certainly right to point out the shortcomings of the Orthodox Church in
                the last years of the Romanov dynasty, his complete rejection of the Church winds up
                illustrating the point that the road to hell is paved with good intentions. Surely
                Satan is aware of the military maxim "Divide and Conquer."</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Edward Dominic Fenwick Papers 1803 -
                    1832</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Father Luke Tancrell,
                    O.P.</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This book probably should not receive a grade as it is a reference work (and I
                know the editor.) Bishop Fenwick grew up on what is now Samson's Harbor Farm, and
                Father Tancrell visited my father in researching this book. I had the pleasure of
                meeting Father Tancrell when he was assigned to the Dominican House in Washington
                DC. Any collection of letters does not provide narrative flow, but this a
                fascinating look at life in the early days of America.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Abolition of Man</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>C.S. Lewis</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/11/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>0</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I've not yet decided on how to grade this book. It is a short series of lectures
                by C.S. Lewis dealing with the effects of moral relativism in education and as such
                is certainly prescient. I think that I will read this again before deciding on a
                grade.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">What's Wrong with the World</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>G.K. Chesterton</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/3/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I picked this up as reading material for Lent, but it is really social
                commentary rather than spiritual. Chesterton had a gift of penetrating insight,
                whether the subject is religion or society - not for nothing is he known as the
                "Apostle of Common Sense."</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">John Paul Jones</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Samuel Eliot
                    Morison</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/23/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This book belonged to my grandfather (Thaddeus Krush) and I inherited it from
                Nanny. It was very interesting reading this book after having read Evan Thomas'
                Jones bio just two years ago. I went back to my review of Mr. Thomas' biography to
                ensure that it was rated lower than the grade I assigned to this one (and indeed, I
                had rated it lower). In a way, an entire essay could be devoted to the differences
                between these two books. But to be brief, ADM Morison's credentials as an historian,
                his passion for sailing and his experience as historian for the US Navy during World
                War II provide greater credibility than Mr. Thomas' background as a reporter
                (all-be-it a very successful reporter). Given that the material covered was almost
                identical, Adm. Morison's book was more interesting, more balanced and more
                insightful.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Modern Times: The World from the Twenties to the
                    Eighties</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Paul Johnson</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/19/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Inherited this book from Stacy's father. A tremendous work, perhaps best
                summarized by the quote from the back of the dust jacket: "Throughout these years,
                the power of the State to do evil expanded with awesome speed. Its power to do good
                grew slowly and ambiguously." I will certainly return to this book later as Mr.
                Johnson revised this book to carry it up to the Nineties.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Two-Ocean War</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Samuel Eliot
                    Morison</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/2/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Given to me by Stephen Brumbaugh as a "going away" present from Fannie Mae. A
                thorough and very readable summary of the operations of the U.S. Navy in World War
                II.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Jesus Shock</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Peter Kreeft</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/6/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Bought this from Amazon.com with a gift certificate I received as a gift when I
                left Fannie Mae.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Forty Ways to Look at Winston
                    Churchill</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Gretchen Rubin</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/14/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Given to me by Uncle Steve a while ago. 40 very short chapters examining the
                life of Winston Churchill. Not terrible, but particularly enlightening either. This
                book does serve as sort of a "Wikipedia" entry that gives a brief overview of his
                life, accomplishments and failures and trying to give expression to as many possible
                views on Churchill as possible.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">How Robert E. Lee Lost the Civil
                War</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Edward
                    Bonekemper</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/22/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>It is not uncommon now days to argue that General Lee has been over-rated by
                historians, and Mr. Bonekemper has made a bid to be the coup-de-grace to Lee's
                reputation. While not quite descending to the level of jeremiad, Mr. Bonekemper
                misses no chance to point out Gen. Lee's faults. This is somewhat a shame, because
                he does have some good points to make. In fact, there are a number of very telling
                arguments. First, that Lee was too aggressive - and he presents some interesting
                figures to back this up. The statistics that he cites demonstrate that Lee lost more
                soldiers than any General in the war, both in raw numbers and in percentage of his
                forces lost. His poor staff work and overly complex plans helped contribute to the
                heavy losses. Mr. Bonekemper also suggests that Lee learned to be very aggressive in
                the Mexican War, when muskets and cannon had much less range and accuracy - which is
                an argument that I have not heard before but is worth consideration. He suggests
                that Lee should have used his influence to end the war in 1864 to prevent
                unnecessary bloodshed. Lee's invasions of the North were fatally flawed because
                given the scope of his plans, he was going to have to march his army back south at
                the end of the campaign, regardless of what happened along the way, and leave the
                impression that he had been forced to retire. He completely neglected the rest of
                the confederacy to focus on Virginia - which is perhaps the argument that most
                closely supports the assertion in the title of the book. There are a number of flaws
                in Mr. Bonekemper's presentation. He argues with the gift of hindsight, as if his
                conclusions were as glaringly obvious then as they are now. He makes no effort to
                identify what Lee did right. Indeed, his book reads as the summation by the
                prosecution rather than a intellectual evaluation. His chronological narrative does
                not support his arguments particularly well - he would have been better off
                organizing the book around his chief arguments.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Out of the Silent Planet</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>C.S. Lewis</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/26/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Philosophy 101 by Socrates</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Peter Kreeft</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/4/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">"They Have Killed Papa Dead: The Road to Ford's
                    Theatre, Abraham Lincoln's Murder, and the Rage for
                Vengeance"</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Anthony Pitch</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/7/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Warrior Generals</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Thomas Buell</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/22/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This is the second time that I have read this book; this time prompted by having
                read Bonekemper's "How Lee Lost the Civil War" and Buell's bio of Admiral Spruance.
                I can't quite put my finger on what makes his style so distinctive, but I find his
                books hard to put down. In addition to style, he brings a tremendous amount of
                common sense to military subjects based upon his own career in the Navy. Mr. Buell
                focuses his attention on three Generals from the Union (Grant, Thomas and Barlow)
                and three Confederate generals (Lee, Hood and Gordon). He is pretty hard on both
                Grant and Lee, both of whom fought with tenacity but not always with skill. Both
                were weak in staff work and logistics and their short comings prevented them from
                achieving better results. Mr. Buell is perhaps a little hard on Grant, going so far
                as to label his 1864 campaign in Virginia as a failure. But no matter the tactical
                setbacks he experienced, he never lost the initiative and by refusing to disengage
                from Lee, he was sure to win in the end. Like Mr. Bonekemper, Buell criticizes Lee's
                lavish expenditure of his soldiers lives, but he is a bit more understanding of
                Lee's grand design to win the war for the Confederacy. Lee's intention was to
                influence northern opinion by sapping the will of the Army of the Potomac to fight
                and the will of the northern public to endure the losses and humiliation - all while
                preventing the Union army from over running his native state. In the end, he was
                unsuccessful - not for lack of will but for opportunities lost due to poor
                intelligence, missing maps, poor staff work and the loss of his best generals and
                soldiers due to aggressive tactics. The next pair of generals are Thomas and Hood.
                Buell argues that Thomas was the outstanding general of the war because he lacked
                none of the shortcomings of Lee and Grant. In fact, his staff work, logistical
                planning and intelligence operations clearly foreshadowed modern American combined
                operations. He defends Thomas from the denigrating comments by Grant and Sherman
                that he was superb on defense but slow to attack. One short coming of Thomas, and
                Buell does admit this, was his inability to communicate effectively with Grant and
                Sherman, which ultimately reduced his effectiveness. Another criticism that Buell
                missed is that Thomas' approach to war ignored politics. While he recognized that
                the only way to defeat the Confederacy was to destroy the southern armies, he wasn't
                as sensitive to northern politics as were Grant and Sherman. Perhaps his disdain for
                politics led him to feel a certain amount of disdain for Grant and Sherman, who were
                both political operators as well as generals. Hood gets perhaps the shortest shrift
                in the book and only seems to serve as a foil to illustrate the ultimately
                superiority of the northern methods of waging war. Hood was superb as a brigade and
                even division commander, largely average in a short stint as a corps commander and
                an absolute disaster as an army commander. The final pair of generals are Barlow and
                Gordon. Gordon had a sterling career, steadily moving up the ranks due to
                aggressiveness in battle. Barlow too gradually rose up through the ranks, although
                not quite as high as Gordon. The big contrast between the two warriors was that
                Gordon never really adapted his tactics as the war progressed, whereas Barlow
                learned to transition from tightly massed formations to flexible skirmish lines
                which could take advantage of the terrain.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Notes from the Underground</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Fyodor
                    Dostoevsky</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/23/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A short novel written from the point of view of a young radical. Perhaps not up
                to his best standards, but Dostoevsky has a skill for taking an individual aliened
                from society and treating them sympathetically. The end result is that he more
                clearly illustrates the negative consequences of how they choose to respond to their
                alienation than if he had written a polemical essay against the folly of the
                "modern" reaction against all aspects of "traditional" society. He very clearly
                illustrates how the moderns "throw the baby out with the bath water" in their
                reaction against the negative features of their society and their fellow man. The
                short story "The Dream of the Ridiculous Man" was interesting - it seems to be
                another aliened young man who has turned to nihilism, but instead has a vision that
                transforms his life. Instead of a nihilist raging against society, he is transformed
                into a prophet in the mold of St. Paul. Interestingly enough, his vision could very
                well have been the idea for C.S. Lewis' story Out of the Silent Planet and also
                seems to be reflected in the book I am currently reading - Walker Percy's <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Lost in the
                    Cosmos</emphasis>. I wonder if this influence is direct (i.e. they are
                reflecting upon Dostoevsky's story) or indirect.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Sacraments We Celebrate</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Msgr Peter Vahgi</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Chancellorsville</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Stephen Sears</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/6/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Well written and thought provoking. General Hooker had many things going for him
                - excellent logistics, planning, staff work and infantry organization. Lee had very
                little going for him, terrible logistics, a third of his army absent from the battle
                and the loss of his best General about half way through the battle. Yet Lee managed
                to win a spectacular but ultimately costly and inclusive victory. Hooker had bad
                luck, (getting wounded at a critical juncture of the battle, etc.), he badly
                mishandled his cavalry and artillery and perhaps no general in the Civil War
                received worse performance from his subordinates. He also divided his forces,
                allowing Lee to shift back and forth between both wings of his army. In the end, he
                was unable to overcome the mistakes. The irony is that 6 weeks later, George Meade
                fought exactly the type of battle that Hooker wanted to fight - allowing Lee to
                repeatedly attack his prepared positions at Gettysburg. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Lost in the Cosmos - The Last Self-Help
                    Book</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Walker Percy</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/6/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This book was quite a find - I had never heard of it until I listened to a
                recorded lecture by Peter Kreeft in which he compared this book with C.S. Lewis'
                    <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">The Abolition
                    of Man</emphasis>. It is funny to think of someone, perhaps a science fiction
                fan or amateur astronomer, stumbling upon this book seeing the title and thinking,
                "hey, this might be for me." But the "Last Self-Help Book" is sub-title is quite
                ironic, and if this book is a self-help book for anyone, it would be for
                philosophers, artists and scientist. Actually, Mr. Percy's approach in this book is
                probably as close to the Socratic method as anything I have read. He defines some
                terms relating to semiotics (the study of symbols) and spends the rest of the book
                asking questions and suggesting "thought experiments." Perhaps the single,
                overarching question in the book is from the dust jacket - "Why is it possible to
                learn more in ten minutes about the Crab Nebula in Taurus, which is 6,000
                light-years away, than you presently know about yourself, even though you've been
                stuck with yourself all your life?" </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Last Battle</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>C.S. Lewis</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/11/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Perelandra</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>C.S. Lewis</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/26/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>The second book in Lewis' Space Trilogy, this book has much less action than the
                first installment; indeed, much less action than one typically expects from the
                science fiction genre. Instead, this book is an extended reflection upon the fall of
                man in the Garden of Eden and a look forward to the end times foretold in the Book
                of Revelation. The scenes where Westin (or rather the demon possessing Weston) is
                trying to tempt the Queen of Perelandra is a very subtle, persistent and disturbing
                - one wishes for the action to proceed to escape the oppressive atmosphere. Yet
                Westin's blandishments are so familiar - one can think of many examples in the
                media, in academia, in advertising and pop-culture - in which we are constantly
                bombarded with these empty promises. This book definitely calls for a second reading
                to fully explore Mr. Lewis' arguments and symbols.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">That Hideous Strength</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>C.S. Lewis</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/11/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>It is interesting how different is each of the books that comprise Lewis' Space
                Trilogy. The first, <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline"
                    >Out of the Silent Planet</emphasis>, is probably closest to contemporary
                science fiction. <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline"
                    >Perelandra</emphasis> is an extended theological exploration and <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">That Hideous
                    Strength</emphasis> is almost closer to an action-adventure story. It is a
                fast-paced and gripping account of what happens when science loses connection to
                morality. As I read this book, I felt it would be a nice companion piece to
                Solzhenitsyn's The First Circle.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Manalive</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>G.K. Chesterton</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Stacy gave me an electronic book reader for my birthday, and this is the first
                book that I have finished. It was an open-source edition, and the problem with this
                is that the OCR technology isn't perfect. But the imperfections aren't much of a
                problem and are a small price to pay in order to be able to read a book like this,
                which would be difficult to find in print.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Winters Tale</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Mark Helprin</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/4/10</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Recorded book. I first read this book 15 years ago after reading A Soldier of
                the Great War. The story was gripping, but so fantastic that it was hard to know
                what to make of it. I was delighted to find this on CD at the library. Although Mr.
                Helprin is Jewish, when I first read this book I thought that it had a very "Roman
                Catholic" outlook. This book resembles nothing so much as an artistic interpretation
                of the coming of the Messiah and the Apocalypse. The writing is beautiful, the
                characters are noble.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="bookOfTheYear">
            <d:title>Book of the Year</d:title>
            <d:para><emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Lost in the
                    Cosmos</emphasis>. Honorable mention to <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Modern
                Times</emphasis>.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:chapter>
    <d:chapter>
        <d:title>2011</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Arians of the Fourth
                Century</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>John Henry Cardinal
                    Newman</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/11/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Read from an open source e-book. The quality of the scan wasn't great - in
                particular, it had great difficulty with the footnote on the bottom of the page,
                especially if they extended to the next page. The history of heresies suffer in
                comparison to military histories in that theological battles are waged by scholars
                and theologians over fine shades of meaning, yet this book shows the very great
                consequences caused by even fine shades of meaning. For in all human affairs, there
                seems to be a never ending struggle between those who seek the truth and thus seek
                maximum precision in their language and those who seek some earthly reward - usually
                power, sometimes money - who are willing to shade meanings to hide their true
                intentions. When Constantine became emperor of Rome and became interested in
                Christianity as a means of unifying his empire, the stakes in theological disputes
                were raised immensely. This is an excellent defense of the Catholic position against
                the Arians and an excellent example of why the pursuit of truth and the accurate use
                of language are so important. Also, a good treatment of the career of St. Athanasius
                is woven throughout the narrative - this will be of interest to Thomas some
                day..</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Descent into Hell</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Charles Williams</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/29/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">This novel was recommended in a lecture I
                listened to by Peter Kreeft. A much more polished open source e-book that
                illustrates the great benefit of the open source movement in e-books. It is hard to
                describe this book - the story is set in a suburb of London - a new development
                surrounding an old hill-top estate with an ancient history. The plot revolves around
                a local stage production of a play by the poet who inhabits the old estate. The
                story tracks some residents on the path to heaven in contrast with others who are on
                the descent mentioned in the title. The language is often dense, time becomes
                non-linear and the boundary between the living and the dead becomes blurred - indeed
                the writing at times seems more free verse than prose, yet the book is still oddly
                compelling for all that. Here is an example of a particularly dense sentence:</para>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">"Much difficulty in finding what? in finding
                it? the it that could be found if he thought of himself more; that was what he had
                said or she had said, whichever had said that the thing was to be found, as if Adela
                had said it, Adela in her real self, by no means the self that went with Hugh; no,
                but the true, the true Adela who was apart and his; for that was the difficulty all
                the while, that she was truly his, and wouldn't be, but if he thought more of her
                truly being, and not of her being untruly away, on whatever way, for the way that
                went away was not the way she truly went, but if they did away with the way she went
                away, then Hugh could be untrue and she true, then he would know themselves, two,
                true and two, on the way he was going, and the peace in himself, and the scent of
                her in him, and the her, meant for him, in him; that was the she he knew, and he
                must think the more of himself." But this sentence occurs at the great turning point
                when one of the protagonists, Mr. Wentworth, begins his descent in earnest. As nice
                as this was in e-book form, I would like to read this one again in text.</para>
            <d:para>.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Admiral Farragut</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Alfred Thayer
                    Mahan</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/11/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I stumbled across this book on an on-line collection of open source books, and
                this is an example of a hidden treasure made easily accessible by the e-book. Any
                midshipman at the Naval Academy is familiar with Capt Mahan's name thanks to Mahan
                Hall, and those who did not sleep through their Naval History course would recognize
                him as the author of a book that influenced nearly all navies from 1900 until about
                1940. This biography was written two years after Capt. Mahan wrote <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">The Influence of Sea
                    Power Upon History</emphasis>. In style, very similar to Samuel Elliot Morrison
                (I don't know if this was a conscious imitation of Mahan's style by Morrison, or
                just a reflection of the pre-modern academic style.) It is easily accessible to the
                layman yet very stimulating to those familiar with the Navy. This would be excellent
                reading for midshipman, because Capt. Mahan's central concern is not so much to
                celebrate Farragut's accomplishments as to understand how his development as a naval
                officer allowed him to achieve greatness when called to duty in the Civil
                War.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The River War</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Winston
                    Churchill</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/26/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An account of the "Dervish" Rebellion in the Sudan against Egyptian rule, and
                the joint British / Egyptian operations to re-conquer the Sudan. Of some passing
                interest as the Sudan has just recently voted to split into two separate countries
                (north and south).</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Silence</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Shusaku Endo</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Gripping, yet haunting. A novel about Christian missionaries and martyrs in
                Japan - grapples with the issue of why some give heroic witness to their faith and
                why simply try to survive. The book offers no answers but hints that Christ remains
                with both the heroic and the abject..</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Man Who Was Thursday</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>G.K. Chesterton</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Influence of Sea Power Upon
                    History</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Alfred Thayer
                    Mahan</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/23/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Nearly rates a 5 for interest and style, but realistically, I will not re-read
                this book except for the first chapter. In fact, the first chapter should be
                required reading for every Midshipman at Annapolis..</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Crecy</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Hilaire Belloc</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/26/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Between the Water and the
                Woods</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Patrick Leigh
                    Fermor</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/26/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Mr. Fermor passed away this year. The day after I read his obituary in the Wall
                Street Journal, Tom Kalaris (Stacy's brother) sent an e-mail stating that Mr. Fermor
                was one of his personal heroes. So I found this book at Barnes and Noble and picked
                it up as a Father's Day present. Mr. Fermor provides a vivid portrait of the lands
                and people in Austria and Romania in the years immediately before World War II. This
                book is actually the second in a series of three books describing his trip on foot
                from Holland to Constantinople following his expulsion from college. (The third
                volume was not published at the time of his death.) Stylistically, this book is very
                well crafted, sometimes even spectacular. But the problem with a travelog is that
                there are plenty of small obstacles overcome, but no resolution of weighty matters
                that would provide depth..</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Jesus Christ</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Pope Benedict
                    XVI</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/15/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Stylistically, this borders on dry academic prose, but that may be partly a
                translation issue. What this book does, and does very well, is to provide an
                overview of the events in the life of Jesus from Palm Sunday through the
                Crucifixion, balancing the Church's understanding and interpretation of these events
                with an examination of scholarly interpretation. If the end result were just a
                rehash of scholarly opinion, this book would rate a lower score. But Pope Benedict
                raises our view above the debates of the scholars to remind us of the miracle that
                has become the very reason for faith and the center point of all of the history of
                mankind..</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Robinson Crusoe</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Daniel Defoe</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/16/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This is one of those classics about which everyone knows a little, but which few
                have taken the time to actually read. The details of the adventure story are well
                known; a man shipwrecked on a deserted island who manages to survive for many years
                alone, the psychological impact of the discovery of a single footprint upon the
                sand, and the relationship with Friday, whom he rescues from an enemy tribe. Yet
                just as interesting are Crusoe's musings on man's relationship with God - indeed
                Crusoe's developing faith can be taken as the key theme of the entire work. This is
                perhaps, a very Protestant take on theology - a man drawing closer to God through
                his reading of the Bible and his own prayers and reflections. But aside from some
                comments about Papists and priest craft, his treatment of Catholics is much better
                than one would expect from a post-Reformation Englishman. The book is actually quite
                gripping up to the point of the rescue of Friday. From there on out, it returns to
                being simply a run-of-the-mill adventure story.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">A Country of Vast Designs</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Robert W. Merry</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A balanced and readable history of the presidency of James K. Polk. A good
                introduction, but not a great deal of depth.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Rite</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Matt Baglio</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/28/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A balanced view of the Catholic Church's rite of exorcism. Reads like a really
                long magazine article.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Innocence of Father
                Brown</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>G.K. Chesterton</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/20/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A collection of "mysteries"; short stories featuring the priest / detective
                Father Brown. Similar in tone, although both more and less serious that the Sherlock
                Holmes stories. More serious in that they are more illustrative of the danger of
                modern life to the soul; yet the stories Chesterton's whimsy and emphasis on Father
                Brown's humility provides the stores with a much lighter touch than Arthur Conan
                Doyle achieves with Holmes. (This is not a criticism of Doyle as I love nearly all
                of the Holmes collection.) Nearly all of these stories were a joy to read..</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Randolph of Roanoke: A Study in
                    Conservatism</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Russell Kirk</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/21/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>If you read enough history of the US in the period between 1800 and 1830, you
                will inevitably encounter the figure of John Randolph of Roanoke, usually presented
                as an acid tongued curmudgeon with a rapier wit and an irredeemably bad temper. In
                these accounts, his prime accomplishment was his duel with Henry Clay. Mr. Kirk
                provides a much more balanced view, presenting Randolph as a champion of individual
                rights and a Cassandra warning of the dangers of unchecked Federal power. His views
                can best be summarized, perhaps, by a phrase used by Randolph: "Change is not
                reform."</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Exploring Reality: The Intertwining of Science and
                    Religion</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>John
                    Polkinghorne</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/29/11</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>John Polkinghorne is a quantum physicist turned Anglican priest, and this book
                is a collection of essays on the ways science and religion complement each other.
                Stylistically, it is rather dry, as one would expect of a physicist, but his
                knowledge of both the language and methodologies of science and theology give him a
                very balance point of view that stands against the atheism of some scientists and
                the anti-scientism of some fundamentalists. Earlier this year, the famous physicist
                Steven Hawkings wrote an article that asserts that the universe does not need a
                creator as the law of gravity was sufficient cause in and of itself. He attempted to
                argue his point in the language of philosophy and addressed some of the proofs for
                Gods existence addressed by St. Thomas Aquinas. But his arguments were ill-organized
                and slip-shod. Mr. (Dr. ? Father? I'm not sure of the Anglican honorific)
                Polkinghorne is able to argue intelligently in both realms and is thus provides a
                more informed opinion.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Heritage</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Abba Eban</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2011</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>1</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Did not finish this book. A history of the Jewish people. An interesting
                subject, but an imperfect execution. Mr. Eban seems to combine pride in Jewish
                culture with the Enlightenment's (and modern academia's) mistrust of religion. So
                the result is a pride in Jewish culture without reflection on the status of the Jews
                as God's chosen people.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="bookOfTheYear">
            <d:title>Book of the Year</d:title>
            <d:para>Fiction <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline"
                    >Silence</emphasis> / <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">Robinson Crusoe</emphasis></d:para>
            <d:para>Non-fiction: <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline"
                    >The Influence of Sea Power Upon History</emphasis></d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:chapter>
    <d:chapter>
        <d:title>2012</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Imitation of Christ</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Thomas a' Kempis</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/6/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An e-book downloaded from the Project Gutenberg website. I started reading this
                last Lent, and finally finished it this year. This is a very difficult book for a
                modern reader, both in content and in style. To imitate Christ, the author
                continually emphasizes the rejection of worldly interests, the acceptance of trials
                and tribulations and the humility to ignore the opinions of others. In the modern
                world, we are immersed in mass communication enabled by technology, which provides
                an instant and ever changing propagation of public opinion and which contributes to
                the idea that all problems can be resolved with the application of time and money.
                Furthermore, on a personal level, there is a tremendous emphasis on the individual -
                in terms of health and intellect. So if the author is correct in the path of
                following Christ, then this book makes for a very tough pill to swallow.
                Stylistically, the devotional style of the late Middle Ages does not naturally
                appeal the direct, secular modern style. But, just because the book is hard to read
                does not mean it is not true.. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Pensees </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Blaise Pascal</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/28/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Another e-book from Project Gutenberg, and another book that I started in last
                year's lent and finished this year. The OCR on this book was pretty poor. This is a
                collection of reflections on religion by Blaise Pascal, and stylistically is much
                more intellectual than the Imitation of Christ - after all Pascal was a noted
                mathematician. This book is not really intended to read from front to back, and
                would really be better read as a real book rather than an e-book.. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Phaedo </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Plato</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Plato's account of the last hours of Socrates, in which Socrates lays out the
                rational argument for the afterlife. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Myth of the Great War </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>John Mosier</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/17/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para> </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Lord of the Rings </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>J.R.R. Tolkien</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/30/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I read the first volume of this trilogy when I was in England with Nanny as a
                boy. Thomas and I have just now finished the whole set - some of it read together
                and some by ourselves. This was voted the greatest British novel of the 20th century
                some years ago, prompting much wailing and gnashing of teeth by the literati. For
                those who equate art with "the shock of the new" (to borrow a book title from Robert
                Hughes), Tolkien has little to offer. His writing does not offer "realism" in the
                sense of cynicism, despair, transgression of morals and manners, pseudo
                Freudian-ism, etc. But, of course, no art is "real", but instead abstract
                representations that can be good, beautiful and/or true (or that can willfully
                ignore the good, beautiful and/or true). More than anything else, The Lord of the
                Rings is beautiful; Tolkien seems to have been a man who deeply loved words. He
                loves good, old fashioned words and delights in their use. He loves words so much
                that he even invented languages for the elves and the dwarves, and writes songs and
                poems in these new languages. What makes this work so enduring and so popular, I
                think, is that it appeals to our in-born desire for beauty and goodness and shows
                the world not as it now is, but as it should be. The heroes are not like those we
                know, but reflect a nobility that we wish we could obtain. The dialog is not like
                any conversation we would have with our friends or co-workers, but is fluent and
                true. The plot really could have been taken from any Norse saga, or Greek myth, or
                German fairy tale. This has allowed the books to be made into a series of very good
                action movies. As I mentioned, I read the first volume as a young boy, and while the
                plot did not grip me enough to continue on to the next two volumes, the images of
                the Shire and of the encroaching darkness of evil and the flight of the hobbits from
                the Ring Wraiths have long stuck with me. Indeed, the Shire reminds me of nothing so
                much of Samson's Harbor Farm. What will always draw me back to these books is the
                beauty of the writing. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Lancelot </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Walker Percy</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/24/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para> </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Possessed </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Fyodor
                    Dostoevsky</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/30/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para> </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The First Team </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>John Lundstrom</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An outstanding academic study of naval fighter combat in the South Pacific
                during the first 6 months following Pearl Harbor.. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Hamlet </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>William
                    Shakespeare</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/1/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I enjoyed this more than I thought I would; for all of Hamlet's reputation as
                depressed or paralyzed by indecision, the play is not at all morose. I think,
                perhaps some of the reputation of the lead part is more a reflection on the critics
                than on the play. In any event, as far as tragedies go, I still prefer Macbeth.
            </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Warrior Elite </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Dick Couch</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/20/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para> </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The First Team: The Guadalcanal Campaign
                </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>John Lundstrom</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/30/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>As the sub-title indicates, Mr. Lundstrom focuses his analysis of fighter
                tactics as they played out during the Guadalcanal Campaign. Of particular interest
                to me as my mother's father was a Marine and an aircraft mechanic on Guadalcanal.
            </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Commentaries on the Gallic War
                </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Julius Caesar</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/5/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para> </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Gulliver's Travels </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Jonathan Swift</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/20/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>The images are timeless - Gulliver tied down by the Lilliputians, Gulliver in
                the land of giants, etc. Swift's satire is biting, and sometimes telling even in the
                modern world - i.e. the ultra-rationalistic residents of the floating island of
                Laputa. To my taste, however, his satire comes off less humorous and more preachy -
                more like the crank shouting on the street corner than the wit at a highbrow
                cocktail party. In this sense, I believe that Robinson Crusoe has aged better than
                Gulliver's Travels. But the Jonathan Swift's incredible imagination will likely
                always attract new readers, and really, human nature has not changed so much that
                his satire won't strike home in any age.. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Good Soldier </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Ford Maddox Ford</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/5/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Recommended by John Mosier in the Myth of the Good War, but I can't remember
                why. Perhaps it was to illustrate the obtuseness of the British upper class before
                World War I. Didn't much care for the book. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Battle of Blenheim </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Hilaire Belloc</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/7/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A monograph on Marlborough's great victory over the French. Actually there
                wasn't much to the battle. The French line was divided in two with separate
                commanders. Each of the two French commanders anchored their flanks with nearly all
                their infantry leaving the center undermanned with their generally inferior cavalry.
                After futile assaults on the flanks, the cavalry of Marlborough and Eugene smashed
                through the center and captured the French right wing whose infantry was holed up in
                the village of Blenheim. The brilliance of Marlborough and Eugene was in the
                campaign leading up to the battle, moving from the Rhine to the Danube to isolate
                and destroy a combined French and Bavarian force.. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline"> The Wisdom of Father Brown
                </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>G. K. Chesterton</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/27/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Very entertaining But not, perhaps, as enjoyable as the <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Innocence of Father
                    Brown</emphasis>. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Story of the Malakand Field Force
                </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Winston
                    Churchill</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/28/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Churchill's description of the fighting on the frontier between India and
                Afghanistan seems equally relevant today The description of the tribes and manner of
                fighting are immediately recognizable. Perhaps the only misplaced judgement is
                Churchill's belief that western commerce and "progress" would ultimately civilize
                this frontier. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Macbeth</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>William
                    Shakespeare</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Phantastes, A Faerie
                Romance</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>George MacDonald</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/15/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Heretics</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>G. K. Chesterton</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/16/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Tolkien Reader </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>J.R.R. Tolkien</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/17/12</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Cross of Iron: The Rise and Fall of the German War
                    Machine, 1918-1945</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>John Mosier</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2012</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Not sure if I read this in 2012, but I read it after the Myth of the Great War,
                and I don't find it listed elsewhere. Mr. Mosier challenges some of the conventional
                wisdom on the course of the war on the eastern front. For instance, he argues that
                even before the invasion of Normandy, the Dieppe raid and the invasion of Italy drew
                off enough German troops to tilt the results of the battles of Stalingrad and Kursk
                to the Soviets. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="bookOfTheYear">
            <d:title>Book of the Year</d:title>
            <d:para>Non-fiction: tough choice, but I will go with the two editions of <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">The First
                Team</emphasis>.</d:para>
            <d:para>Fiction: <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Lord
                    of the Rings</emphasis></d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:chapter>
    <d:chapter>
        <d:title>2013</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Persian Fire: The First World Empire and the
                    Battle for the West</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Tom Holland</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">A very readable history of the Greek -
                Persian wars. Stacy gave this to me as a gift for Christmas; she had read an
                interview with her brother Tom and he had recommended the book. Probably the best
                treatment of the Persians that I have read. Does a pretty good job with the whos
                and hows and whys of the war between the Greeks and Persians. A couple of nit-picks.
                Like many contemporary historians, he wants to rectify a traditional viewpoints with
                regards to the non-Western actors. Like many such attempts, he slips into the trap
                at times of denigrating the Greeks. But he does not carry this to an obnoxious
                extreme. Second, he comes across as a cynic in all matters of religion. As a student
                of politics and military action, he seems to view it as just another tool by which a
                state maintains order. Third, he can be occasionally crass in terms of treating
                sexuality. This might be fine in the locker room among adults, but it will
                definitely prevent me from recommending this to Thomas until he is older. But,
                all-in-all, an enjoyable and profitable read.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Letters of St. Ignatius of
                    Antioch</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>St. Ignatius of
                    Antioch</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>No point in assigning a grade. It is very interesting how much he writes in the
                manner of St. Paul - both in content and in style.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">An Essay on the Development of Christian
                    Doctrine</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>John Henry Cardinal
                    Newman</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/30/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>His style is very dry and academic, but there are times when Cardinal Newman is
                very insightful. What struck me most was his descriptions, using source material, of
                the pagan establishments view of the early Christian. This is entirely foreign to
                the modern reader as our perspective comes about 1600 years following Christianitys
                eclipse of paganism. But Christianity was such a radical departure for the Roman
                establishment that they truly believed that Christians were atheists.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Clear the Bridge</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Richard O'Kane</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/5/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Account of his service as a submarine skipper in WWII.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Place of the Lion</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Charles Williams</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/9/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>1</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Poitiers</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Hilaire Belloc</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/22/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A short book describing the English defeat of the French during the 100 Years
                War. Like all the great English victories of this war the result was largely decided
                by the long bow.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Masters and Commanders</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Andrew Roberts</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/19/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Focuses on the interactions between Roosevelt, General Marshall, Churchill and
                General Brooke. A very good overview of the subject referencing plenty of source
                material  some of which he claims is presented for the first time. His judgments on
                the character and accomplishments of those involved are solid. His judgments on the
                course of the war are trite and reflect the consensus view of the war with little
                original thought  particularly when it comes to the Soviets.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Atheist Delusions</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>David Bentley
                    Hart</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/12/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I had put off reading this as one reviewer had mentioned that it was somewhat
                lacking in charity to the current popular writers who espouse atheism. But I find
                this judgment itself to be inaccurate. Mr. Hart certainly does not suffer fools
                gladly, but in this case, his sharp words are not aimed at the character of his
                opponents but rather the shallowness of their arguments. Most of the book, rather
                than consisting of attacks upon atheists is rather a presentation of Christian
                history and its contributions to the development of the modern world shorn of the
                current politically correct history of Christianity based upon the distortions of
                the Enlightenment. Also, more fully develops the theme of the utter foreignness of
                Christianity to the Roman world as discussed above in the "Essay on the Development
                of Christian Doctrine."</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Three Men in a Boat</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Jerome K. Jerome</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/10/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Thomas Dangerous Book for Boys listed this as a must read for all boys based
                upon its humor. While it was entertaining and occasionally funny in the dry British
                fashion, this book definitely falls in the category of "good but not
                great."</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Victory of Reason</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Rodney Stark</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Types of Naval Officers Drawn from the History of
                    the British Navy</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Alfred Thayer
                    Mahan</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/18/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">From Sail to Steam, Recollections of Naval
                    Life</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Alfred Thayer
                    Mahan</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Sea Power and Its Relation to the War of
                    1812</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Alfred Thayer
                    Mahan</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/13</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Far and away the best history of the War of 1812 that I have read. The naval
                actions of the war take up only a small portion of the book. Capt. Mahan describes
                in great detail the economy and system of trade that existed between Europe and the
                US in the years after the Revolution, how the French Revolution and Napoleonic wars
                impacted these systems and how the United States responded. He is a hard critic of
                how Jefferson and Madison responded to these circumstances.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="bookOfTheYear">
            <d:title>Book of the Year</d:title>
            <d:para>
                <d:emphasis role="underline">Sea Power and Its Relation to the War of
                    1812</d:emphasis>. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:chapter>
    <d:chapter>
        <d:title>2014</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Incidents and Anecdotes of the Civil
                    War</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Admiral David Dixon
                    Porter</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">This is not so much a history of the Civil
                War but a collection of sea stories. A very enjoyable read.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Sand Pebbles</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Richard McKenna</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">I didnt read McKennas biography until
                after I finished this book, but it was obvious that he was a Navy veteran. In fact,
                whenever the plot of the book gets "underway" with the U.S.S. San Pueblo, his
                writing is exceptional. It is less so when the plot takes the protagonists ashore,
                but he does present a very balanced account of all the different parties in conflict
                in China in the years in between WWI and WWII.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">With The Old Breed</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> E.B. Sledge</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">The memoirs of a Marine who fought on
                Pelileu and Okinawa. His description of the horrors of combat on Okinawa is very
                much on par with those of William Manchester in "Goodbye, Darkness". My impression,
                however, is that E.B. Sledge offered a broader view that included those with whom he
                served while Manchester was more self-focused. While Sledge says that he wrote the
                book for his family, it seems that in a way, he was trying to honor the memory of
                those who died. While he was not a professional writer (rather a professor of
                ornithology), his book is in every way as readable as Manchesters. Sledge really
                had a gift for observation.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Complete Father Brown
                Mysteries</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> G.K. Chesterton</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">I ordered this e-book from Amazon; it
                contains the Father Brown mysteries that I had not yet read. Almost all of these
                stories are a delight to read; at the end of a busy day I would often pour a beer to
                accompany one of these stories.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Gettysburg: The Last
                Invasion</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Allen C. Guelzo</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/1/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">I picked this up for Thomas after he took a
                field trip to Gettysburg. I had not heard of this book, so I started reading it to
                see if it would be worthwhile. Given how much I've already read about Gettysburg, I
                probably would not have looked at it otherwise. But this was such a well written and
                thought-provoking book that I finished the whole thing. Professor Guelzo offers a
                compelling narrative of events, he challenges some of the accepted wisdom about the
                Civil War being the first "modern" conflict, he offers balanced judgements on the
                actions of key figures and he highlights many of the political aspects of the
                "Civil" War. Sometimes his supporting evidence does not support his conclusions -
                for instance he maintains that statistically there was little danger from being hit
                by the inaccurate fire of inexperienced troops, yet elsewhere he describes an
                instance of a row of casualties from a North Carolina regiment on the opening day of
                the battle. But his premise still is worth considering - he contends the mass
                casualties were a result of inexperience troops standing toe to toe to fire for
                extended periods, yet not charging with bayonet. This is born out by evidence of
                units succeeding in seemingly suicidal charges at key points in the battle (the 20th
                Maine at Little Round Top, the 1st Minnesota at the end of day 2, etc.). This book
                is a borderline 5, although as much as I enjoyed reading it, I doubt I shall read it
                again. But I definitely recommend it as first rate military history.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">This Republic of Suffering</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Drew Gilpin
                    Faust</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/10/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Written in drab academic style, Ms. Faust
                never-the-less has produced an interesting book on how Americans, both soldier and
                civilian, both northern and southern, dealt with the enormous loss of life in the
                Civil War. I can't help but think of William Nevin, who served for 40 days before
                dying of "camp fever." We posses two letters written by Will to his aunt during his
                short service that describe the novelty of army life without any reference to the
                pain and suffering of the war other than a passing mention of a sick tent-mate. When
                I look at the portrait of his father, Theodore Hugh Nevin, that hangs above my
                mantle, I wonder about pain he endured at the loss of his oldest son. </para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Wars of the Roses</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Allison Weir</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">We visited Nantucket this summer, and this
                book was on the shelf of the house that we rented. I managed to get most of the way
                through the book while on vacation, then checked it out from the library to finish.
                Ms. Weir covers the back-and-forth struggle between the York and Lancaster branches
                of the Plantagenet dynasty, beginning with the overthrow of Richard II and
                concluding with the victory of Edward IV over Henry VI. This era illustrates the
                weakness of the feudal system - strong kings dying young and young kings unable to
                keep the nobility in check. In the political vacuum, the struggles between factions
                in the nobility temporarily weakened the monarchy, but ultimately weakened the lords
                even more. This set the stage for the strong monarchs of the House of Tudor and the
                transition to a more absolute monarchy. </para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Life of Nelson</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Alfred Thayer
                    Mahan</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/1/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">What If?</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Randall Munroe</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis> 10/8/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Beauty of the Infinite: The Aesthetics of
                    Christian Truth</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> David Bentley
                    Hart</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/19/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">This book is not addressed to the general
                reading population; rather it is the work of a serious philosopher addressing other
                serious philosophers. Thus, it uses a vocabulary that is not familiar to the
                non-academic (not to mention Harts unusually broad vocabulary even when he is
                writing to the general public). I read this on the Kindle app  the ability to look
                up words with a touch was helpful, but no replacement for already having command of
                the terminology. </para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Divine Comedy</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Dante Alighieri</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/29/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">On Something</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Hillaire Belloc</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/31/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Utopia</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> St. Thomas More</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Alices Adventures in
                Wonderland</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Lewis Carroll</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Princess and the Goblin</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> George
                    MacDonald</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">A Shorter Summa</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Peter Kreeft</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/30/14</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:chapter>
    <d:chapter>
        <d:title>2015</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Master of Sea Power: A Biography of Fleet Admiral
                    Ernest J. King</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Thomas B. Buell</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/15</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Mr. Buell is one of my favorite biographers, and this was an excellent treatment
                of the life and the influence of Admiral King. Admiral King's role in the Navy in WW
                II can best be compared to that of General George Marshall for the Army.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Chico the Jester</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Alexandre Dumas</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis> 4/15</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">This appeared in a list of books compiled by
                the Wall Street Journal that would interest watchers of the Game of Thrones series
                (of which I am not a viewer). But I do have an interest in the Middle Ages, so I
                downloaded this book from Amazon. Technically not set in the Medieval France, but at
                the period in which the Reformation is just about to break upon Europe. It is a work
                of historical fiction about a court Jester who manages to guide the King of France
                through plots and revolts. Actually a very interesting story to which I am not doing
                justice owing to the passage of time and the corresponding loss of details.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The White Company</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Sir Arthur Conan
                    Doyle</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2015</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>1</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">From same book list as Chico the Jester.
                Very similar to Walking Drum; the authors only interest in the Middle Ages seems to
                be as a backdrop of ignorance, prejudice and violence in which his very modern and
                very English and very Protestant (in outlook, anyway) hero can advance from one
                adventure to the next. The relatively little I know about the English "companies"
                that fought in France during the 100 years war lead me to believe that they were a
                blood thirsty lot little better than the Vikings. There is a second volume that
                accompanies this, but I could not finish the first volume.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Venice: Pure City</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Peter Ackroyd</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/15</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Read this in preparation for our trip to
                Italy. A basic background on the history, art, architecture, and people of
                Venice.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Virtues of War</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Steven
                    Pressfield</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/15</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Found this at the used book bin at the
                library; I thought Thomas would enjoy the portrayal of Alexander the Great. A work
                of historical fiction, written as if Alexander was dictating his lessons on
                leadership. Mr. Pressfield is a very engaging story teller, and does an excellent
                job of dissecting the tactics of the Macedonian army at the peak of its power.
            </para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Yanks are Coming </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> H.W. Crocker
                    III</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/15</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Bought this for Thomas, and read it while he
                was away at summer camp. A very cursory introduction to the US involvement in WWI,
                including profiles of the most famous Americans involved in the war.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Fighting the Flying Circus</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Eddie
                    Rickenbacker</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/15</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">I am sorry I lost my comments on this book.
                The gist was that Eddie Rickenbacker was a truly remarkable man and a terrific
                writer.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Memoirs of General Baron De
                    Marbot</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> General
                    Jean-Baptiste-Antoine-Marcelin Marbot</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/15</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">A cavalryman in the French army under
                Napoleon. An engaging account of the Napoleonic wars from a very brave officer who
                fought in many of the biggest battles of the wars. This book was recommended by
                Steven Pressfield in his notes on the sources he used in writing "The Virtues of
                War."</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Mass in Slow Motion</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Father Ronald
                    Knox</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/15</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">A series of homilies given by Father Knox to
                the school girls at a parochial school that he served. Explains the structure and
                meaning of the Roman Catholic mass.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Teaching Particulars</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Helaine L.
                    Smith</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/15</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Ms. Smith is a private school English
                teacher, and she presents a series of discussions on poems, short stories and novels
                tailored for classes from 6th thru 12th grade. I bought this as a resource for
                Thomas and Anna; but enjoyed reading the book myself.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="bookOfTheYear">
            <d:title>Book of the Year</d:title>
            <d:para>I lost the original document and made my best effort to re-create the list. So
                I'm pretty sure this list is not complete. Based on the list as is, "Master of Sea
                Power" is the winner.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:chapter>
    <d:chapter>
        <d:title>2016</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">City of God</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>St. Augustine</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I bought this from Barnes and Noble several years ago. The book was written as a
                response to those who blamed the influence of Christianity for the sack of Rome. A
                good portion of the book contains arguments against paganism; overall its purpose is
                a justification for the truth of Christianity..</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Game of Thrones</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>George R. R.
                    Martin</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Thomas loves the Game of Throne series and suggested that I read it. Mr. Martin
                is a great story teller - on par with Tom Clancy and Stephen King.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Galileo Heretic</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Pietro Redondi</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>What I love about this book was that it sought to understand Galileo and his
                conflict with the Church in the context of the times in which it occurred, rather
                than trying to project modern ideals and assumptions onto the issue. If you have no
                interest in theology, this will be a very dry read. If you love thought provoking
                research, the details are fascinating.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">In the First Circle</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Aleksandr
                    Solzhenitsyn</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/30/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A new translation of the unabridged version of the novel. It was originally
                publishes as The First Circle, and heavily edited to appease Soviet censors. Covers
                one weekend in the life of a prison dedicated to scientific and engineering
                projects. A truly magnificent novel, both heart-breaking and uplifting as ordinary
                people (both inside and outside the prison) try to survive in Stalinist
                Russia.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Reckoning: The Murder of Christopher
                    Marlowe</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Charles Nicholl</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Mr. Redondi in Galileo Heretic attempts to put himself in 17th century Italy to
                illustrate to the reader what he feels lead to Galileos trial. In contrast, Mr.
                Nicholl attempts to look back from the 20th century to provide his guess at what
                exactly led to the death of poet Christopher Marlowe. Extremely well researched, Mr.
                Nicholl is forced into a great deal of speculation based on a very thin amount of
                material. In his defense, he does an outstanding job of informing the reader on what
                he can prove and on what he leaves to speculation. In the end, there is not enough
                evidence to make a convincing argument, but the book is an excellent introduction to
                the paranoid spy vs. spy atmosphere created by the secret police in Elizabeth Is
                reign.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">City of Saints</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>George Weigel</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/4/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A travel guide of sorts, highlighting Pope St. John Paul IIs ties to the city
                of Krakow, Poland.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Diplomacy</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Henry Kissinger</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/2/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I started this several years ago, ploughing through the sections from the age of
                enlightenment through WWII. I was lost interest when the book reached the Cold War
                as I was generally more familiar with the events of this period. Nonetheless, once I
                started again, I found Mr. Kissinger a very insightful guide to the events that he
                either observed or participated in first hand. Mr. Kissinger was famous when I was a
                child; today he seems only to be discussed when someone levels a charge that he is a
                war criminal for some incident or the other in the course of his service. Truth be
                told, Mr. Kissinger pretty accurately describes the species of frustrated idealist
                (peculiar to America, and perhaps to the Communist Party) who views foreign policy
                as a means of advancing their ideals and who treat any rational discussion of
                national interests as a dastardly betrayal of their ideals. The fact that
                Kissingers critics can only paint him as some kind of devil while he is able to
                accurately describe this class of critic with an analytic, critical and even
                somewhat sympathetic eye is evidence that he is much closer to the truth than his
                opponents. Other critics lay the charge that he is a cynical practitioner of
                realpolitik, but it is clear from this book that he tries to balance the notion of
                rational national interests with the ideals on which the American republic was
                founded.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Russian Revolution</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>William Henry
                    Chamberlin</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/11/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Utterly forgettable.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Forgotten Man: A New History of the Great
                    Depression </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Amity Shlaes</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/30/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A well written review of the causes of the Great Depression and the attempts to
                revive the American economy in the 1930s. The subject of the Depression in general
                and the New Deal in particular tends to generate polemics based upon an authors
                political leanings. While Ms. Shlaes reaches the conclusion that the New Deal did
                not end the depression and may have prolonged it, she presents both sides of the
                argument in a balanced fashion. In particular, she focuses on the lives of a number
                of figures, both famous and obscure, to help illustrate the impact and reactions to
                the economic and political conditions. I will likely buy this book for Thomas for
                Christmas.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">A Storm of Swords</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> George R. R.
                    Martin</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis> 9/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Third in a series of 5 books in the Game Of Thrones series, although I believe
                the author is currently working on one additional book to conclude the series. As
                Ive mentioned before, he is a first rate story teller - to that I would add that he
                is a first-rate entertainer. His stories read as if they were movies, which is
                probably why the Game of Thrones TV series is so popular. So I do not begrudge him
                his success; indeed I rank his work with that of Tom Clancy who I think was an
                equally gifted story-teller and entertainer, and perhaps Steven King. But I do have
                a number of nits to pick. 1. The pace of military operations rivals that of the
                armies in World War II more so than the medieval era. The speed with which King
                Baratheon delivered his army from his island base to the far side of the great wall
                would have exceeded the capabilities of most armies in WWII. 2. While he does a
                remarkable job of describing a battle, his tendency to resolve them with an
                unexpected stroke belies the nature of medieval war fare where most battles were
                resolved by the brute weight (literally, given the armor and horses) of the
                contending forces. 3. He has obviously embraced the axiom show, dont tell, but he
                has used the phrase the juices ran down his chin far too many times to illustrate
                the fact that one of his characters was ravenously hungry. 4. The explicit sex
                scenes are too much - Mr. Martin, to judge by the publicity photos, is a rather
                over-weight, middle-aged man, and would rather he kept his fantasies entirely to
                himself. As the kids say these days - TMI (too much information.) 5. While he
                kills of characters in droves, once he narrates a chapter from someones first
                person point of view, it seems like they are in the series for the long haul. In
                this book, Catlyn (sp?) Stark is murdered, yet she is back from the dead in the
                books coda. 6. There is too much of the Perils of Pauline in his handling of
                Arrya Stark. In fact, at one point I was so annoyed by yet another unexpected turn
                in her fortunes that I skipped ahead to the end of the book to see how everything
                turned out. So, over all I can recommend this series, but I dont foresee the desire
                to ever read them again.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">A Journey In the Seaboard Slave States, vols. 1
                    and 2</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Frederick Law
                    Olmsted</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/27/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>In the 1850s, Frederick Law Olmsted (future architect of Central Park)
                travelled across the south writing articles for the New York Daily Times. This was
                in the time period shortly after the publication of Uncle Toms Cabin, and the paper
                sent him to get a first hand view of the conditions of slaves. He is clearly
                anti-slavery, but no polemicist. More than anything, he is interested in what makes
                a farm successful, and his over-riding impression is that slavery was so grossly
                wasteful that he wondered why anyone would voluntarily continue the practice. He
                also described the unhealthy social effects of slavery on both the servants and the
                masters. These two volumes cover his travels from Washington, DC, to Richmond and
                Norfolk, VA, across North Carolina to coastal South Carolina and Savannah, GA, then
                to Mobile AL, New Orleans and the Red River district of Louisiana. His detailed
                descriptions of his travels are an excellent view of life in the antebellum south.
                The second volume is one of the worst printing jobs Ive ever seen in a book, at
                least three different pages are duplicated.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">A Journey in the Back
                Country</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Frederick Law
                    Olmsted</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Found this on Google Play. The first half is Mr. Olmsteds return journey from
                Louisiana to Virginia via the upland country (what we would call the Piedmont
                region in Virginia and Maryland) of Mississippi, Alabama and Tennessee. The second
                half isnt as interesting as he attempts to draw generalizations on Southern society
                and on the impact of slavery on both the Southern and National economy.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Fifth Gospel</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Ian Caldwell</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/31/2016</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Stacy gave this to me for Christmas at the recommendation of her boss at Capital
                One.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="bookOfTheYear">
            <d:title>Book of the Year</d:title>
            <d:para>I lost the original document halfway thru 2016 and made my best effort to
                re-create the list. So it may not be complete. But based on the list as is, "In The
                First Circle" is the winner. Galileo Heretic gets honorable mention.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:chapter>
    <d:chapter>
        <d:title>2017</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Armada</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Garrett
                    Mattingly</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Stacy gave this to me for Christmas, 2016. An excellent history of the Spanish
                Armada, with particular emphasis on the events that precipitated the campaign. Well
                written and presents the Spanish point of view with equal attention and sympathy as
                to the English.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Snow and Steel</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Peter
                    Caddick-Adams</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Another Christmas gift from Stacy. This is an outstanding work of military
                history. The author is a former British Army officer who frequented the Ardennes
                during his Army career. He turned his interest in his surroundings to excellent use;
                intermixing many first hand accounts of the battle with his own observations of the
                ground and his sound professional judgement. I passed this book on to Uncle
                Steve.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Last Stand of the Tin Can
                Sailors</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>James
                    Hornfischer</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/21/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Yet another Christmas gift from Stacy. A gripping account of the Battle of Leyte
                Gulf in World War II, focusing on the escort carriers, destroyers and destroyer
                escorts that confronted the main Japanese force during the second day of the battle.
                .</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Company</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Robert Little</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/5/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Reminds me very much of James Webbs A Country Such as This, which chronicled
                the careers of three or four (I forget some of the details) classmates from their
                graduation from Annapolis though the course of the Cold War. In this case, Mr.
                Little narrates the careers of two classmates from Yale who join the CIA in the
                early 50s through the fall of the Soviet Union. In any case, I dont necessarily
                love this plot device; it stretches the imagination too much when characters
                conveniently find themselves involved in all the key points of a given period of
                history. But the book was well written and the story kept my interest. One footnote,
                the book pays careful attention to the career of James Jesus Angleton; although when
                he exits the stage, Stacys father does not get a cameo appearance in the story! (In
                fact and not fiction, he assumed the role as Deputy Director for Counterintelligence
                when Angleton was relieved of his duties.)</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">A Kingdom Far and Clear</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Mark Helprin</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/13/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A childrens book illustrated by Chris van Allsberg of Polar Express fame. While
                written for children, Mr. Helprin does not dumb-down his writing. Like most of his
                novels, he contrasts the beautiful with the ugly, the good with the evil and the
                true with the false; but he is always more interested in the virtues than the vices.
                So rather than a castigating the wicked in an excessively moralizing tone, his prose
                attempts to rise to the perfections of the virtues. I originally bought this for
                Anna, but she was not interested in the book.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Stalin: Paradoxes of Power,
                1878-1928</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Stephen Kotkin</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Stacy gave this to me for Christmas. An outstanding biography of a loathsome
                subject. There aren't many details of Stalin's early life, but Mr. Kotkin provides
                an in depth presentation of the Russian empire in which Stalin was raised. He gives
                the best presentation of the system of "autocracy" by which the last Tsars ruled. In
                the West, we make the mistake of thinking of the Tsars as just another tyrannical
                king along the lines of Henry VIII of England or Louis XIV of France. But the theory
                of power to which Nicholas II subscribed was much closer to that of the Byzantine
                blend of religious and secular authority. (Please note that I do not use the term
                "Byzantine" in the pejorative sense, but in the actual historical sense.) Nicholas
                II opposed the radical parties that sought to remake Russia, but he also opposed
                conservative parties that sought to defend the throne. Any political party at all
                was a diminution of his power. Kotkin's description of Russia's entanglement in WWI
                is also top notch. I believe that there will be two more volumes in this biography.
                I am drawn to Kotkin's scholarship but not anxious to spend more time in Stalin's
                presence.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Inspector</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Nikolai Gogol</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Was highly commended in Stephen Kotkin's Stalin, but I did not enjoy much. It
                is a play concerning bumbling provincial officials in a village in Tsarist Russia.
                They mistake a neer-do-well clerk passing through town for a government inspector.
                Plays are generally not my thing, and you always wonder what gets lost in a
                translation.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Seven Story Mountain</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Thomas Merton</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/16/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Selected this for reading during Lent.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Bunker Hill: A City, a Siege, A
                    Revolution</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Nathaniel
                    Philbrick</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Hard Sayings: A Catholic Approach to Answering
                    Bible Difficulties</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Trent Horn</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Fleet at Flood Tide: America at Total War in
                    the Pacific, 1944-1945</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>James D.
                    Hornfischer</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/18/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Again, a Christmas gift from Stacy.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Natural Navigator: The Rediscovered Art of
                    Letting Nature Be Your Guide</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Tristan Gooley</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/20/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This was a gift from Stacy and I to Thomas, I read it before him because the
                stack of books he is trying to catch up on has grown pretty large!</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Last Testament</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Benedict XVI and Peter
                    Seewald</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/31/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para/>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Speechwriter</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Barton Swaim</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/6/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This book was a Christmas gift to Thomas. In grading this book, Ive gone back
                and forth between a 4 and a 5. Mr. Swaim is a gifted writer and he has an
                interesting story to tell about his stint as a speech writer for South Carolina
                Governor Mark Sanford. Gov. Sanford's personal shortcomings provide plenty of
                material to work with, but what makes this book so interesting is Mr. Swaims
                attempt to understand why things happened the way the did. One of his most
                insightful observations is that in todays world of 24 hour news coverage, the media
                expects that politicians will have some opinion on any possible subject at any
                moment in time. Of course, no one can possibly have something intelligent to say on
                everything, so politicians learn to provide expansive but meaningless answers in
                order to buy time. (Which is basically the exact opposite approach provided to
                plebes at the Naval Academy; I was taught that there were only 5 appropriate
                responses from a plebe: Aye, Aye, sir to respond to directions, Yes, sir, No,
                sir to answer simple queries, or the correct answer or Ill find out, sir to
                requests for information.)</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Stories and Prose Poems</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Aleksandr
                    Solzhenitsyn</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/10/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Bought this at Barnes and Noble, it turns out to be a re-packaging of a number
                of short pieces by Mr. Solzhenitsyn that have appeared in other books (with the
                exception of a single new short story.) The writing is great; the grade reflects the
                lack of new material.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">A Dance With Dragons</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>George R. R.
                    Martin</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Meh. Mr. Martin either needs to listen to his editor. If he does, then he needs
                a better editor. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Art of Invisibility</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Kevin Mitnick</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Stacy gave this to me for Fathers Day. Poorly written and poorly organized
                although I can sympathize since he is a technology geek. The book does have some
                useful information about staying somewhat safe in the on-line environment.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Histories</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Herodotus</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/18/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>The Landmark edition of the Histories of Herodotus is marvelous - tons of foot
                notes to explain unfamiliar people and places plus maps on every third
                page.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Outliers</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Malcolm Gladwell</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/23/17</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Mr. Gladwell brings a statisticians eye into the debate between nature vs.
                nurture in the development of genius. While he does provide original insight into
                some nurture factors that are immediately apparent, in the end he offers little
                more than the recognition that genius is a combination of innate capability, hard
                work and external support (whether that comes from your family, school,
                neighborhood, etc.) Mr. Gladwell is an enthusiastic and entertaining writer; he
                doesnt overwhelm the reader with too many numbers. And I did find his conclusions
                to be thought provoking. However, keeping in mind the mantra that correlation does
                not mean causation, I dont think many of his examples conclusively prove the
                causation implied by his thesis.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="bookOfTheYear">
            <d:title>Book of the Year</d:title>
            <d:para>No 5s this year, but based on the number of recommendations Ive given to
                others, I will go with The Speechwriter</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:chapter>
    <d:chapter>
        <d:title>2018</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Grant</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Ron Chernow</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/7/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">I dont think anyone would argue that Grant
                is the greatest American; indeed many deride him as a butcher, a simpleton,
                incompetent and / or corrupt. But I have always been fascinated by Grant and admired
                his rise from modest circumstances. After reading this biography, I can say that if
                he is not the greatest American, he is perhaps the most fascinating. When I was
                younger, I read most of the books of Bruce Catton and he was a big admirer of
                Grants rise from humble origins and failure to the pinnacle of success. But his
                work largely ignored Grants post war career as general and president and largely
                ignored his struggles with alcohol. Thomas Buell is one of my favorite biographers,
                but he characterized Grant as a yeoman who achieved success by dogged
                determination despite a glaring lack of intellect and imagination. And B.H. Liddell
                Hart proclaims Sherman as the sole military genius of the Civil War with Grant
                mostly providing support and encouragement. But I think that Mr. Chernow is correct
                in his assessment of Grant as the true genius behind the successful conclusion of
                the Civil War. He was consistently aggressive throughout the war; seemingly
                untroubled by anxiety over what could possibly go wrong yet having an uncanny
                ability to sense how his opponents anxieties could be exploited. His Vicksburg
                campaign provided the blue print for Shermans campaigns in Georgia and the
                Carolinas. And while the Overland campaign against Lee was a bloody slog, he never
                lost sight of his strategic goal of destroying the Confederate army and Southern
                morale. Lee matched Grants tactical skill, but Grant dictated the pace of action in
                Virginia while at the same time coordinating action by all Union armies across the
                entire theater of conflict. While most commentators note the higher number of
                casualties suffered by the Union during this campaign, in terms of percentages,
                Grant's Army of the Potomac suffered casualties of 45% while Lee's Army of Northern
                Virginia (already much smaller to start with) suffered losses of over 50%. And in
                the end, he had the wisdom to understand how to manage Lee to achieve the surrender
                of his army rather than its dispersal into guerrilla bands. The coverage of his
                career as President is also excellent. Grant's presidency is mostly regarded as a
                failure due to a number of financial scandals by members of his administration. Yet
                Mr. Chernow highlights the many successes he achieved that have been largely
                ignored. As much as Ive read about the Civil War, Mr. Chernows biography has
                demonstrated that I have a glaring lack of knowledge about the Reconstruction
                era.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">His Fathers Son: The Life of General Ted
                    Roosevelt, Jr. </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Tim Brady </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A Christmas gift from Thomas. An interesting subject for a biography even though
                Ted Roosevelt, Jr. will always stand in his fathers shadow. Writing style is merely
                so-so.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Translator </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Daoud Hari </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I gave this to Thomas for Christmas and read it after he was finished. Mr.
                Haris account of his experiences during the genocide in Darfur in the 2000s is
                fairly brief, but as powerful as anything to be found in Solzhenitsyn. Yet for all
                of the heartbreaking details , he tells his story with a grace, charm and even humor
                that is spellbinding. Some of the language in this book is as beautiful as any prose
                Ive read in English. I dont know how much of the writing is his own (English is
                not his native language) or how much is from his co-authors (the title page states
                As told to Dennis Michael Burke and Megan M. McKenna ), but my impression on
                reading it is that Burke and McKenna may have transcribed and organized his words by
                the style is his own (just a guess.) The end result is both tragic and
                beautiful.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Paris in the Present Tense </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Mark Helprin </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/2/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I dont read Mr. Helprins work with the expectation of finding the plot or
                characters drawn from real life. Rather, I will read anything he writes simply for
                his magnificent style. This book seems to owe its genesis to the real life issue of
                the recent rise of anti-Semitism in western Europe. It has enough style to worthy a
                5, but the plot has some holes that seem to indicate that this book was thrown
                together in a bit of a hurry. I have no idea if that is the case, but if you
                approach the book with the expectation of being dazzled by his rumination on art,
                beauty, modern society, you will not be disappointed. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Light of Christ: An Introduction to
                    Catholicism </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Father Thomas Joseph White,
                    OP </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>In spite of the title, I dont consider this is book to be an introduction for
                the average layperson. In style and content it is more on par with an upper-level
                undergraduate course. Father Whites style is clear, precise and thorough, which
                requires close attention from the reader. I picked this up to read during
                Lent.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Last of the Tsars</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Robert Service </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/22/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A serviceable account (ha! ha!) of the abdication, imprisonment and execution
                of Tsar Nicholas II and his family. Well written, but really sheds no new light on
                the events covered. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Landmark Julius Caesar </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Julius Caesar</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>"All Gaul is divided into three parts;" this book is divided into five works by
                or about Julius Caesar. First is the Commentaries on the Gallic Wars by Caesar
                himself, as are the Commentaries on the Civil War. Then come the On the Alexandrian
                War, On the African War and On the Spanish War. These were written by others, but
                cover his campaigns that finished the civil war against Pompey and his allies.
                Caesar's writing is much closer to modern style than Herodotus. The Landmark version
                of this book is top notch.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">How to Think </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Alan Jacobs </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Mainly a discussion on how to recognize bias in your own thinking and that of
                others.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Political Tribes </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Amy Chua</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/29/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Ms. Chua argues that current political divisions are due more to people's need
                to belong to a group than to a rational understanding and promotion of policies and
                values. I have not been registered to a party since 2008, and the longer I am away
                from my former alignment, the more I can recognize how often someone can rationalize
                support for a person or a policy simply because it comes from someone who shares the
                same party. Nothing particularly new or insightful, but a good common sense reminder
                to at least try to thing for yourself.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Fall of Berlin 1945 </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Antony Beevor</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/14/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A chronicle of the last months of WW II on the eastern front in Europe. Mr.
                Beevor offers a wealth of detail illustrating the horrific conditions involved in
                combat between the Soviets and the Germans. I am particularly struck by the
                similarities between the Nazi and Soviet regimes - in their devotion to their
                respective ideologies and in their stunning disregard for human life. Before WWII
                had even started, both regimes had already demonstrated callous disregard for the
                lives of their ideological opponents. Their conduct of the war ultimately showed an
                equal disregard for the lives of their own citizens.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Two Hundred Years Together: A Russo-Jewish History
                    to 1972 </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/27/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>0</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>To my knowledge, this book has not yet been fully translated into English.
                Amazon did have a partial translation, so I left the grade incomplete. Perhaps the
                best summary is the final quote offered by Solzhenitsyn before his post script: I
                believe that the contact of the Jewish and Slavic souls in Russia was not a
                coincidence; there was some purpose to it. Thus this book is Mr. Solzhenitsyns
                reflections upon that purpose.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Plantagenets </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Dan Jones </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/30/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>The Plantagenets, both the kings and their wives and relatives, are much more
                interesting than the characters in The Game of Thrones. But Mr. Jones is not in the
                same league as Mr. Martin as a story-teller. This book covers the high-lights, and
                touch on some interesting ideas - the development of English law, the evolution of
                kingship and the nobility, the increasing role of trade and banking. Mr. Jones, to
                his credit notes these issues, but the format of this book, touching on the
                highlights and lowlights of each king, leaves little room to explore them in
                depth.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Battle for Spain </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Antony Beevor </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/6/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A good overview of the Spanish Civil War marred by Mr. Beevors prejudice for
                the Republicans. I doubt that anyone in todays age could be pro-Nationalist
                (restricting the use of the term Nationalist to describe Francos forces). But in
                failing to treat the Republican abuses of power with the same jaundice eye as the
                Nationalists damages his credibility as an impartial reporter of the course of the
                Civil War. To his credit, he is very critical of the lack of political and military
                capability of the Republicans and he is nearly as hard on the Communists as he is on
                the Nationalists. He would have been best served to have stuck with presenting the
                facts and raising questions on alternative courses of action both sides could have
                taken (which he does quite effectively) and left the moral judgements to the reader.
                He did this much more effectively in The Fall of Berlin 1945.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Fur Hat </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Vladimir
                    Voinovich</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A dark comedy of the Soviet era. Mr. Voinovich tells the story of a writer who
                wins an award of a Fur Hat. But to the writer's chagrin (and ultimate self
                destruction), his hat isn't one made of the fur of a rabbit, fox or martin. His hat
                is merely that of the fur of a tabby cat. Vanity of vanities in the workers'
                paradise of the Soviet Union!</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Glass House </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Brian Alexander </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/2/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This is one of those books that summarizes itself in a long sub-title: The 1%
                Economy and the Shattering of the All-American Town. An examination of the authors
                home town - Lancaster, OH - and the downturn of the local economy due to the loss of
                manufacturing jobs. The organization of the book is a mess, but the author does have
                a vivid eye for the people of Lancaster and their struggles.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Counting Coup </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Larry Colton </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/12/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Tom Kalaris, Stacys cousin from Montana, sent us this book. The author, a
                sports writer, spent a year in Montana following the season of the girls high
                school basketball team in Hardin, Montana. He was drawn to this team because half of
                the squad were Crow Indians. Having spent a fair amount of time in the west as a
                child, and having relatives who have lived in Montana, Wyoming and Utah, I was
                somewhat familiar in an abstract sense of what life was like on the reservations.
                This book provides a much more detailed examination of life on the Crow reservation
                and of the complexity of the relationships between the Crow and their neighbors in
                Hardin. The author was able to learn a great deal about the girls on the team, and
                in particular of the star player - a Crow girl named Sharon. He learned so much,
                that as I read the book I wondered whether he was engaging in speculation on what
                the girls were thinking or feeling or whether he was betraying a great deal of trust
                of those with whom he lived for that year. In reading articles online, it appears
                that the second is the case. Before leaving, he had been named an honorary member of
                the tribe, but after the publication of the book, he is persona non grata among both
                the Crows and the non-native residents. But while those whose lives are examined in
                this book may feel betrayed, Mr. Colton has presented the rest of us with an
                unvarnished look at the struggles the Crows face in adapting to the modern
                world</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">A Canticle for Leibowitz </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Walter M. Miller </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/20/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Simply outstanding. In a way, a combination of science fiction and historical
                fiction. Set far in the future following a nuclear war at the end of the 20th
                century. Set in a Catholic monastery of a new religious order created to preserve as
                much learning as possible from the pre-apocalypse civilization, there are sections
                covering three different periods of history. The first period resembles the Dark
                Ages, the second with the Renaissance and the final a futuristic modern
                society.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Gun </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>C.J Chivers </d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/21/18</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An examination of the development of the AK-47 assault rifle and its impact in
                the post Cold War world, expanded with a general examination of the development of
                automatic weapons and a detailed look at how the US military responded to this
                development. Not great, but worthwhile read for both those who are interested in
                guns and for those who does not really understand firearms. In the current debate on
                gun control and gun violence, the press tends to label any gun that resembles the
                AK-47 or the M-16 as an assault rifle without understanding the capabilities of the
                gun in question. Mr. Chivers may not explicitly state it, but this book makes clear
                that an assault rifle is one that fires a rifle round (as opposed to a pistol round)
                and that can operate in either a semi-automatic (pull the trigger, fire one bullet)
                mode or a fully automatic (pull the trigger and bullets fire until you release the
                trigger) mode. A gun firing a pistol round with the same capability to switch
                between semi and fully automatic firing is known as a sub-machine gun. Aside from
                the technical development of assault rifles, he also recognizes the tremendous
                symbolic impact of the assault rifle. So while the press may be wrong to call an
                AR-15 or AK-47 that can only fire in semi-automatic mode (the only type of which can
                legally be purchased) from a technical perspective, they have a better argument from
                perspective of the public fascination with such fire arms. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="bookOfTheYear">
            <d:title>Book of the Year</d:title>
            <d:para>Fiction : <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline"
                    >Canticle for Leibowitz</emphasis> Non-fiction: <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Grant</emphasis></d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:chapter>
    <d:chapter>
        <d:title>2019</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Lady of Guadalupe: And the Conquest of
                    Darkness</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Warren H.
                    Carroll</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/1/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I guess I classify this book as a work of Catholic history. It is not strictly a
                work of objective history nor a work of theology. It is instead an account of the
                conquest of Mexico from the viewpoint of a believing Catholic for other Catholics.
                After reading this book, I would like to learn more about Hernan Cortez.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">A Literary Education and Other
                Essays</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Joseph Epstein</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/5/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Over the past year to year and a half, Mr. Epstein has been a frequent
                contributor of editorials to the Wall Street Journal and an occasional contributor
                to First Things. After an essay in First Things in which he discussed the joys of
                reading, I decide to see what I could find at public library. I found this volume at
                Little Falls Library. Whether I agree with his arguments (or not) or am interested
                in his topics (or not), I find that I always enjoy his style and wit. The downside
                to checking out a collection of essays from the library is that they are better read
                a bit at a time, but the pressure of the due date forces one to plow through the
                entire collection all at once. I will attempt to find other collections at second
                hand so that I may enjoy them at leisure.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Landmark Thucydides: A Comprehensive Guide to
                    the Peloponnesian War</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Thucydides</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/7/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>When Thomas returned from the Ionian Village summer camp in Greece, his uncle
                Tom had recommend that he read this book. Tom had recently read a book called The
                Thucydides Trap; it is my understanding that this book links the events of the
                Peloponnesian War with the contemporary competition between the US and China. Not
                having read the Thucydides Trap and now having read the History of the Peloponnesian
                War, I can say that I dont see the connection. I see a much better connection
                between this book and the events leading up to the American Civil War, or leading up
                to WWI, or even the current rise of populist movements in Europe and the US. The
                conflict in this war was an internecine affair - Greek on Greek. They spoke the same
                language, worshipped the same gods, participated in the same athletic competitions.
                A sobering illustration of how even in a common culture, selfish interests can
                override common sense and lead to terrible outcomes. Herodotus, in my opinion,
                probably offers a better comparison for US / China relations. Herodotus attempted to
                explore why two different cultures came into conflict, and why the Greeks were able
                to prevail. Like all of the Landmark versions of classic histories, this book is
                loaded with maps, footnotes and explanatory appendixes. The Landmark classics almost
                deserve a grade of 5 based solely on the quality of the production.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Silver Eagle</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Clancy Lyall, Ronald
                    Ooms</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/2/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An oral autobiography of Clancy Lyall, a d:paratrooper who served in WWII and
                the Korean War. Ronald Ooms conducted a series of interviews with Mr. Lyall and
                simply arranged the responses to create a chronological account of his life.
                Interesting, but would have been much more interesting if someone with a military
                background would have asked more probing questions about his experiences. Mr. Lyall
                settled in St. Mary's County, Maryland and my mother gave me this book for
                Christmas.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">A History of Byzantium</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Timothy Gregory</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>One of Thomas textbooks from his college course on the history of Byzantium.
                Since it is a textbook, it is not surprising that it comes up short in style;
                especially in comparison to Norwichs 3 volume history. But it is a very balanced
                presentation and delves more deeply into economic and social concerns than I
                red:member from Norwich.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Sophia Petrovna</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Lydia
                    Chukovskaya</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/20/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A novella from the point of view of a mother whose son is arrested and
                imprisoned by the Soviets in the height of the Stalinist purges. While the plot is
                utterly predictable to anyone familiar with the history of the Soviets, the
                reactions of the characters to the events is very believable. We have the benefit of
                looking back with detailed knowledge of what was going on in the Soviet Union. These
                characters were discovering for themselves the true nature of the Soviet
                regime.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Byzantines</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Guglielmo Cavallo,
                    editor</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/27/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Another one of Thomas text books; a collection of essays on various aspect of
                life in the Byzantine Empire. Stylistically tending to the dry and scholarly, but
                each of the essayists seemed more concerned with understanding life from the
                Byzantine perspective than trying to pigeon hole their subject into modern
                terms.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">New Seeds of Contemplation</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Thomas Merton</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/5/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Reading for Lent, didnt finish by Easter. Better to take this book in small
                chunks than to simply power through. We have the choice of two identities: the
                external mask which seems to be real and which lives by a shadowy autonomy for the
                brief moment of earthly existence, and the hidden, inner person who seems to us to
                be nothing, but who can give himself eternally to the truth in whom he subsists. It
                is this inner self that is taken up into the mystery of Christ, by His love, by the
                Holy Spirit, so that in secret we live 'In Christ.'</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Zen and the Birds of
                Appetite</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Thomas Merton</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/11/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A collection of essays on Thomas Mertons engagement with Buddhism. Gave this to
                Thomas for Christmas since he was somewhat curious about Buddhism. I am not so
                curious myself, but still found this worthwhile. "Zen enriches no one. There is no
                body to be found. The birds may come and circle for a while... but they soon go
                elsewhere. When they are gone, the 'nothing,' the 'no-body' that was there, suddenly
                appears. That is Zen. It was there all the time but the scavengers missed it,
                because it was not their kind of prey."</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Frankenstein</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Mary Shelley</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/13/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>As I get older, I am less and less a fan of the overwrought style of the
                Romantic period writing. While nominally about a science experiment gone awry, the
                book is as much about natural philosophy and the moral impact of the quest for
                scientific knowledge. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Cuckoos Egg</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Cliff Stoll</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/17/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para> </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The War of the Copper Kings</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> C.B. Glasscock</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/23/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A gift from Stacys cousin Tom Kalaris, who live is Montana. The story of the
                development of the mining industry in Butte, Montana. Stylistically, a fine specimen
                of florid muck-racking journalism. Took a long time to really get going with the
                book, and this almost merited a lower grade. But the back half was very
                entertaining, and he remained somewhat even handed in his judgements of some of the
                main players. The chapter on the election of one of Montanas Senators is an eye
                opening coverage of naked political corruption. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Belisarius: Thunder at Dawn</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Eric Flint and David
                    Drake</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Recommended to me by Nick Salafsky. An "alternate" history that imagines forces
                from the future going back in time to the Byzantine Empire of Justinian I. One force
                seeks to build in empire based in India to re-direct the course of history, another
                force enlists general Belisarius in a plot to counter the Indians. The author's try
                to imagine how the two sides would adapt to the sudden introduction of such
                technology as stirrups and gun powder. That might have made for a thought provoking
                work, but Belisarius' diplomatic / espionage journey to India veers way off into
                James Bond style action adventure. And since the authors' style resembles nothing so
                much as a Hollywood screen play, it is perhaps inevitable that they imbue Belisarius
                with a thoroughly modern outlook. But, to their credit, the book provides many
                interesting details about the external trappings and customs of the Byzantine Empire
                and ancient Ethiopia and India.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Snobbery</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Joseph Epstein</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An reflection on the types of snobs, the effects (pros and cons) of snobbery and
                its impact on culture. Mr. Epstein is a delightful stylist. My favorite touch in
                this book was on the back cover: blurbs from Henry James, Proust (and one other
                writer- I dont red:member which at the moment). These writers are, of course, long
                dead so Mr. Epstein provided his own blurbs in the voices of writers that he holds
                in high regard. All the while enjoying the snobbish pleasure of having his book
                recommended by some of the greatest writers of the past 150 years!</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Cannon Blasts: Civil War Artillery in the Eastern
                    Armies</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> L. VanLoan
                    Naisawald</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A comparison of the artillery branches of the Army of the Potomac and the Army
                of Northern Virginia written by a former US Army artillery officer. His basic
                premise is that despite the impact on moral of massed artillery, the overall
                effectiveness of Civil War artillery was quite low. Yet he recognizes the commitment
                and bravery of those who served in the artillery.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">War of the Copper Kings</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Carl B.
                    Glasscock</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Given to me by Stacy's cousin Tommy Michael Kalaris. In terms of style, this
                would be a 1 or a 2. If the writing of the Romantic period can seem overwrought, it
                has nothing on the muck-raking style of journalism of the early 20th century. Yet
                the story of the founding of Montana and the development of the mining industry in
                Butte is very interesting.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">War at Sea</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> James P.
                    Delgado</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/10/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An overview of the development of naval technology as revealed through maritime
                archaeology. A useful companion to the works of Capt. Alfred Thayer Mahan - while
                Mahan focused on the development of naval strategy and tactics, Mr. Delgado presents
                the development of the tools of the trade. While the writing is about on par with
                a typical text book, it does provide a wealth of pictures, drawings and diagrams,
                and the quality of the paper, print and binding is much higher than most hard-back
                books produced now days.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Life on the Mississippi</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Mark Twain</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/28/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A digitally scanned and OCRed (optical character recognition) Fairly poor copy,
                especially on pages with footnotes. I have had this in my Nook "app" for a number of
                years and finally got around to finishing it. Provides a fascinating view of Mr.
                Twain's life growing up and then serving as a steamboat pilot on the Mississippi.
                Then moves onto a nostalgic tour covering the length of the rive late in life. The
                reminiscing on his early life is pretty good; the moralizing that comes with his
                observations on his late trip is sometimes too much. I'm sorry I didn't book mark
                it, but there was one bit of unintentional irony when he talks about the 19th
                century being the most "progressive" in history. Mr. Twain had no inkling of present
                day "progressives" who brand him as a racist miscreant and who would love to consign
                    <d:emphasis role="underline">Huckleberry Finn</d:emphasis> to the ash heap of
                history. This raises a couple of points for consideration. When he serves as our
                observer into a way of life long past, his writing is wonderful. When he steps onto
                his soapbox to moralize, he writing is dated and laughably out of date. So too, I
                suppose, will our own efforts be judged by future generations.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The British Are Coming The War for America,
                    Lexington to Princeton, 1775-1777</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Rick Atkinson</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/2/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Nick Salafsky lent me this book. An excellent military history of the first
                years of the Revolutionary War. He does a good job of also covering the British
                perspective. An excellent writer, he weaves in a tremendous level of detail from
                primary sources yet never seems to bog down. Here is my favorite: Captain George
                Harris, shot in the head near the redoubt, was saved by trepanning, the boring of a
                hole in the skull to relieve the pressure from bleeding. Doctors positioned a mirror
                so as to give me a sight of my own brain, he later wrote a cousin. It may
                convince you and the rest of the world that I have such a thing.  So typically
                British! The British had huge advantages in training and tactics and command of the
                sea where and when they chose. The Americans had the advantage of huge distances, a
                large population and genuine outrage at heavy handed British responses to event in
                America. Two more volumes to follow!</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Scarlet Letter</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Nathaniel
                    Hawthorne</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/11/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Anna had to read this for 12th grade English, so I read it as well. Didnt love
                Hawthornes decision to tell the story in the third person; the best parts of the
                novel are when the characters interact in dialog.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Crime and Punishment</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Fyodor
                    Dostoevsky</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/25/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>My third time reading this book. Read it the first time in the summer of 1990
                after I returned from my exchange program in Leningrad. If you would have asked me
                then if I would have ever read the book again, I would have said know. While I found
                the story compelling enough to finish, my feeling at the time was that I had spent
                too much time in Raskolnikovs head and that was not a pleasant place to be. A
                number of years ago, I picked up a recorded version at the library and listened to
                it during my daily commute. This time, I read it at the same time as Anna, who had
                to read it for her English class. Just like with The Scarlet Letter, I read it so
                that we could discuss the book at dinner. This time, the translation was done by
                Pevear and Volokhonsky. This time around, I found the novel much more interesting.
                Dont know if this is because the translation is better, or because I have a deeper
                understanding of Orthodox Christianity and can see how deeply this influenced the
                story, or because I was just slow to appreciate the some of the underlying themes.
                This time, I was also able to recognize some of the reoccurring symbols in the book
                - such as the color yellow and the contrast between the hot oppressive air of St.
                Petersburg contrasted by images of fresh air. I wasnt keeping a book journal in
                1990, so I didnt grade the book then. Dont red:member if I recorded the time I
                listened to the recording. But upon a third reading, I can confidently say that this
                is worthy of a five as I am quite likely to read it again. Also, while published
                only 16 years after The Scarlett Letter, Crime and Punishment seems far closer to
                our current world view. In some ways, Dostoevsky was eerily prescient about the
                negative consequences of some of the emerging radical theories of socialism,
                nihilism and individualism.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Fall and Rise: The Story of
                9/11</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Mitchell Zuckoff</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/31/19</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Mom gave this to me for Christmas. Mr. Zuckoff weaves personal narratives
                following the structure of the events of that day. Some of the accounts were
                familiar to me from the various 9/11 retrospectives on TV over the years; most were
                not. I highly recommend this to Thomas (who was too young to red:member the events)
                and Anna (who was two days from being born on 9/11).</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="bookOfTheYear">
            <d:title>Book of the Year</d:title>
            <d:para>Probably <d:emphasis role="underline">Crime and Punishment</d:emphasis>. I find
                that I frequently think about Thucydides and his insights on politics and conflict,
                but not sure that I would actually read the book again. In terms of style and the
                simple pleasures of reading, Joseph Epstein is top notch.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:chapter>
</d:book>
