<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<d:book xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <d:info>
        <d:title>Paul's Book Log</d:title>
        <d:subtitle>2020 - </d:subtitle>
        <d:abstract>
            <d:para>These are the criteria by which I grade a book. A grade of <d:emphasis
                    role="bold">1</d:emphasis> usually means that I have made a definite decision
                not to finish a book. Of course, there are some books that I start and set aside.
                But I only enter the book if I have finished it or determined it is not worth
                finishing.</d:para>
            <d:formalpara>
                <d:title>Grading Scale</d:title>
                <d:para>
                    <d:simplelist>
                        <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">1</d:emphasis> - Don't bother</d:member>
                        <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">2</d:emphasis> - Generally a waste of
                            time</d:member>
                        <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">3</d:emphasis> - OK</d:member>
                        <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">4</d:emphasis> - Recommend the book to
                            others</d:member>
                        <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">5</d:emphasis> - Plan to read the book
                            again</d:member>
                    </d:simplelist>
                </d:para>
            </d:formalpara>
        </d:abstract>
    </d:info>
    <d:chapter>
        <d:title>2020</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Bach: Music in the Castle of
                Heaven</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>John Eliot
                    Gardiner</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/6/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>1</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Have had this for a few years now; got half way through and now I’ve decided to
                give up. Mr. Gardiner is a noted conductor of Bach’s choral works and I own a couple
                of albums that he has conducted. But in spite of his enthusiasm, he does not
                overcome the fundamental problem of writing about another art form. For each
                cantata, he writes much more than you get from the liner notes, but does not provide
                enough to allow you to follow along as you listen to the cantata. It would have been
                much better if he had done a series of lectures on a smaller selection of cantatas.
                As a biographer of Bach, he provides a great deal of insight on how he composed his
                works, but shows little understanding of the culture / world view in which Bach
                operated. Mr. Gardiner is very much a man of the modern secular world and projects
                his values onto Bach more than truly trying to understand Bach. My recommendation -
                buy Mr. Gardiner’s albums, but skip this book.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Day Will Pass Away</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Ivan Chistyakov</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/12/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>The subtitle, which sums up this book nicely, is: 'The Diary of a Gulag Prison
                Guard 1935-1936. As you might expect, this is not an uplifting book. Mr. Chistyakov
                was drafted into a position as a junior officer supervision prison guards building
                railroads in the Soviet Far East. A native of Moscow, Mr. Chistyakov was less than
                thrilled with his new surroundings, and most of his diary is spent complaining about
                his lot, thinking of ways to get out of his position and complaining about his
                superiors. If the prisoners were at the very bottom rung of Gulag society, the
                guards were barely one step above them (indeed, many guards were former prisoners.)
                And depending on their skills and work tasking, sometimes the prisoners had some
                leverage over their guards. While Mr. Chistyakov remained a loyal Soviet, he was
                very critical of the Gulag. Mr. Chistyakov's diary ends before we learn of his fate;
                apparently he was arrested himself at some point. All that is known is that he was
                killed at the front in 1941 fighting the Germans.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Be Strong and of Good
                Courage</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Dennis Ross and David
                    Makovsky</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/13/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Thomas gave this book to me for Christmas; he attended a lecture my Mr. Ross at
                Tufts University and bought the book afterwards. These days, the phrase "Peace in
                the Middle East" is synonymous with "a hopeless task." Nobody has tilted at this
                windmill harder than Mr. Ross, and I say that not in disparagement but to illustrate
                the depth of his background in this subject. In summary, the authors believe that
                the only hope for peace is for the creation of separate states and that given the
                continued bad faith and judgement of Palestinian leadership, the only way for this
                to occur is for Israel to impose the boundaries themselves. But before presenting
                his recommendations, they examine the careers of four Israeli prime ministers
                (Ben-Gurion, Begin, Rabin, and Sharon. Each of these prime ministers had to make a
                decision that balanced Israel's need for security while advancing the possibility of
                achieving peace - most famously by Begin and Sadat at Camp David. This book is well
                written, well reasoned and gives honest attention to viewpoints that differ from the
                authors'. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Aviator</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Eugene
                    Vodolazkin</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/2/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Stacy gave this to me for Christmas. Beautifully written. The plot is totally
                unexpected; I won't spoil it here because it is so fun to see how the novel unfolds.
                Written in the form of journal entries, which works surprisingly well. In a sense,
                this is a modern version of <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">Crime and Punishment</emphasis>.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Intelligent Investor</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Benjamin Graham</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/7/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Revised edition. I started this several years ago, and finally got around to
                finishing it. Central premise is to explore the difference between investment and
                speculation and to offer guidance to those who wish to invest intelligently rather
                than simply gamble with their money. Asks the reader to evaluate their interest in
                the process of understanding investments and to assess their goals. If nothing else,
                this helped me to recognize that I am curious about how money can be put to
                effective use, but my level of interest does not rise above simple curiosity. Which,
                I suppose, is why I am a software engineer and not a financial analyst.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">President McKinley: Architect of the American
                    Century</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Robert W. Merry</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/16/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A well written and well balanced biography. President McKinley, was a man of
                even temperament, quiet confidence and low key charisma. He had the bad luck not
                only of being assassinated but of being followed in office by the hyper-energetic
                and highly charismatic Teddy Roosevelt. Despite being overlooked for many years, he
                may rank as one of the most effective presidents in terms of using his executive
                powers in coordination with his party's operations in the legislature. I find it
                interesting that Mr. Merry, who also wrote A Country of Vast Designs about President
                Polk, has chosen to write about two presidents who are relatively unknown despite a
                tremendous amount of success in office. Both served during periods of tremendous
                expansion of American power (and geography) and both seem to be ethereally regarded
                as accidental by-standers to these monumental events. But Mr. Merry make a
                compelling case that they actually were shaping events through a quiet brand of
                leadership in coordination with effective behind-the-scenes political operations.
                Mr. Merry does not seem to advance any particular ideology in these two biographies.
                He balances praise with criticism and presents his subjects' point of view as well
                as those of their respective opponents. In particular, I was struck by two
                observations by Mr. Merry. Pres.. Polk was an opponent of tariffs, and one of his
                first actions was to pass legislation to greatly reduce them. The apparent result
                was a great increase in government revenue - despite lower taxes, economic expansion
                produce greater government revenue. So great, that the US paid the costs of military
                action in the Mexican War without incurring debt. Pres. McKinley was a great
                believer in tariffs, and one of his earliest actions was to raise tariffs. The
                apparent result was a great increase in government revenue, this time due to higher
                taxes and increasing economic activity. So great an increase as to finance the
                Spanish-American War (as well as the subsequent fighting against insurgents in the
                Philippines) with the addition of a short-term tax on beer and other consumer items.
                Mr. Merry does not make this comparison - indeed he seems little interested in
                economic details - but it shows that he does not appear to apply modern political
                outlooks to his historical analysis. For a present day Republican would be greatly
                in favor of the Democratic Polk's policy of lowering taxes while a present day
                Democrat would much prefer the Republican McKinley's approach of raising
                taxes.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Solovyov and Larionov</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis> Eugene
                    Vodolazkin</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/22/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A very interesting novel. Solovyov is a graduate student in history whose thesis
                is on General Larionov. On one level, the novel seems to be a very satirical take on
                Russian academia. Even given the difficulties of translation (for instance, in
                Russian, the novel apparently included hundreds of footnotes, but the translator
                opted to include them in the text), the novel is amusing. Then there are the details
                of Solovyov's upbringing in a remote railway town and his romantic interests. These
                descriptions begin with the same sense of ironic detachment, but gradually these
                topics take on greater depth. And finally, there is the life of General Larionov,
                who commanded the White army's last stand against the Bolsheviks in the Crimea, yet
                who somehow escaped execution and died a natural death of old age in the Soviet
                Union. Whenever Solovyov's research turns up new details on the general, the story
                jumps back in time. The general remains a rather two dimensional character in the
                novel and much of his concern seems to be trying to understand the boundary between
                life and death and to understand his relationships with those who have died before
                him and those who still live. The novel concludes in a rather dramatic fashion in
                which a number of seemingly innocuous details described earlier in the novel are
                linked in the General's confrontation with the Bolshevik forces as they occupy
                Yalta. I plan to read this novel again someday, if for no other reason than to see
                how many more details tie to the conclusion. But also, Mr. Vodolazkin seems to be
                attempting a larger examination on the process of recording and understanding
                history versus living and understanding life in the first place.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">American Sniper</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Chris Kyle, Scott McEwen
                    and Jim DeFelice</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/23/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Audio Book, I checked this out before driving up to Boston to pick Thomas up
                from Tufts University due to the school closure as a result of the coronovirus
                outbreak. The autobiography of Chris Kyle, a Nay SEAL who completed 4 combat tours
                in Iraq. He served as a sniper and is credited with more confirmed kills than any
                sniper in American history. Mr. Kyle seemed to be one of those individuals who are
                drawn to the experience of combat. Not in the somewhat theatrical style of say,
                General Patton, but in the manner of someone who takes pride in doing a very
                difficult job and doing it very well. Mr. Kyle was not of a philosophical or
                intellectual inclination, and his story is told with great enthusiasm. What I think
                is the best touch with this book was the fact that they included, in the first
                person, the perspective of his wife as she dealt with the challenges of being
                married to a SEAL in a time of war. In a sad bit of irony (not dealt with in this
                book), Mr. Kyle was murdered by a fellow veteran a number of years after the war.
            </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Introduction to Christianity, 2nd
                    Edition</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Joseph Cardinal
                    Ratzinger</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/29/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I've been slowly working on this for a few years now. It is amusing that this is
                entitled as an "Introduction" as this is written at a far higher level than that
                which most people would consider introductory. I believe that it is intended as an
                introduction for graduate level students of philosophy and theology and probably
                professors in these fields who do not have a Christian background. The structure is
                straight forward, but the writing is often dense. So, I plowed through some sections
                with glazed eyes, yet found other sections to be very engaging and thought
                provoking. Fortunately, the concluding paragraph give a very clear summary of the
                book. I quote the conclusion in the next paragraph.</d:para>
            <d:para>"The goal of the Christian is not private bliss but the whole. He believes in
                Christ, and for that reason he believes in the future of the world, not just in his
                own future. He knows that this future is more than he himself can create. He knows
                that there is a meaning he is quite incapable of destroying. Is he therefore to sit
                quietly with his hands in his lap? On the contrary; because he knows there is such a
                thing as meaning, he can and must cheerfully and intrepidly do the work of history,
                even though from his little segment of it he will have the feeling that it is a
                labor of Sisyphus and that the stone of human destiny is rolled anew, generation
                after generation, up the hill only to roll down again once more and nullify all
                previous efforts. Whoever believes knows that things move “ forward ”, not in a
                circle. Whoever believes knows that history is not like Penelope’s tapestry, which
                was always being woven anew only to be undone again. Even the Christian may be
                assailed by the nightmares, induced by the fear of fruitlessness, out of which the
                pre - Christian world created these moving images of the anxiety that all human
                activity is vain. But his nightmare is pierced by the saving, transforming voice of
                reality: “ Be of good cheer, I have overcome the world ” ( Jn 16: 33 ). The new
                world, with the description of which, in the image of the final Jerusalem, the Bible
                ends, is no Utopia but certainty, which we advance to meet in faith. A salvation of
                the world does exist — that is the confidence that supports the Christian and that
                still makes it rewarding even today to be a Christian"</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Imitation of Christ</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Thomas A' Kempis</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/4/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A free version of this from Amazon Kindle. This is not a book to read straight
                through, but rather a collection of contemplations by a monk. Perhaps because of the
                translation, the language is archaic. While this sometimes works to "elevate" the
                text, in this case, it often made it hard to retain focus on some passages.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Personal Recollections of Joan of
                Arc</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Mark Twain</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/12/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Finished this on Easter Day, 2020, in the year of the coronovirus pandemic. I
                can't remember where I first heard about this book; certainly almost no-one today
                would think that Mark Twain would have written a favorable portrayal of Joan of Arc.
                When I was young, I had read A Connecticut Yankee in King Arthur's Court, which
                displayed Twain's biting satire, confidence in modern progress in comparison to
                medieval ignorance and superstition. So I turned to the internet to get the reaction
                of others to this book. Susan Harris, a professor states: "By the time Twain is
                writing <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="italic"
                    >Recollections</emphasis>, he’s not a believer. He is anti-Catholic, and he
                doesn’t like the French. So he writes a book about a French-Catholic-martyr?
                Ostensibly, it doesn’t make a lot of sense." Most modern opinions cited on
                Wikipedia, unless they are from profession Catholics, either share this befuddlement
                or our downright dismissive. Yet this is what Mark Twain had to say: "I like
                    <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="italic">Joan of
                    Arc</emphasis> best of all my books; and it is the best; I know it perfectly
                well. And besides, it furnished me seven times the pleasure afforded me by any of
                the others; twelve years of preparation, and two years of writing. The others needed
                no preparation and got none." A newspaper review (cited by his daughter) at the time
                of publication sums up this work with: "His language has undergone a startling
                change. Not flippancy, but pathos, meets us on every page; the sardonic mocking
                spirit has been conquered by the fair Maid of Orleans, and where aforetime we met
                laughter, we now meet tears." Personally, I loved this book. There are some
                drawbacks. The ongoing interactions between Noel and the Paladin is annoying and
                distracting - I times I would skip over sections relating between the two. But as a
                reflection on the life of Joan and her impact upon French history, this is a
                masterful work of historical fiction.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Rule of Four</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Ian Caldwell and Dustin
                    Thomason</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/16/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A work of historical detective work. Interesting and a quick read. I gave this
                to Anna for Christmas and read it after she finished.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Meetings With Remarkable
                Manuscripts</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Christopher De
                    Hamel</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/29/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An examination of twelve illuminated manuscripts from the Middle Ages. The book
                is beautifully illustrated, and Mr. De Hamel acts as an enthusiastic tour
                guide.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">March 1917 The Red Wheel Node III Book
                    1</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Aleksandr
                    Solzhenitsyn</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/3/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Covers a period of four days in March 1917 in which Petrograd descended into
                chaos following rebellion by Russian troops. On one hand, this is a very convincing
                portrayal of the state of chaos. On the other hand, the characters from the earlier
                novels in the Red Wheel cycle barely make an appearance. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Dreadnaught: Britain, Germany, and the Coming of
                    the Great War</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Robert K. Massie</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/4/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>When it comes to book titles, usually I complain about inane sub-titles. In this
                case, the sub-title actually tells you the theme of the book. Silly me for thinking
                this would be a naval history. The actual H.M.S. Dreadnaught does not make its first
                appearance until page 461, and then the ship gets a whole chapter describing its
                construction and technical innovations. And, since the name of the ship is used to
                describe all of the battleships built by Britain from 1904 until WWI, there are
                additional mentions of "dreadnaughts" in the remaining 447 pages of the book. And
                there is a second volume - Castles of Steel - to follow. But I digress. Mr. Massie
                provides a detailed examination of the political, economic and military relations
                between Germany and Great Britain between the unification of Germany until the
                outbreak of WWI. Since Britain was historically antagonistic with France, and
                periodically with Russia, it was by no means inevitable that Britain would have
                sided with France and Russia in the decade before WWI. An implied thesis for why
                this was so is Kaiser Wilhelm II's insistence on building a powerful fleet. In the
                end, I can't help but think that Germany and Great Britain, as the two most powerful
                nations in Europe, badly played their hands. Bismark's sole policy following the
                unification of Germany was to prevent a combination of more than two powers (the
                powers of his time being Britain, France, Austria and Russia) uniting against
                Germany. Wilhelm II's blind adherence to an alliance with Austria alienated Russia.
                His insistence on a powerful navy alienated Great Britain. Great Britain, under Lord
                Salisbury, was content to avoid involvement in continental squabbles while
                maintaining superiority at sea. The Liberal cabinet that came to power in 1906
                managed to improve ties with France, in part to prevent further friction from
                competing colonial endeavors. This certainly served Great Britain's interests. But
                the involvement of the British Army staff in coordinating potential operations was
                naive. The French, weaker than Germany, had every interest in drawing Britain into
                an alliance. Britain, aside from assuring a hostile power did not appear in Belgium
                and the Netherlands, had no inherent interest in supporting the French army against
                the Germans. In the end, the weak powers dragged the strong into global
                conflict.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Blindness</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Jose Saramago</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/17/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Anna read this last summer as part of her summer reading for English. It details
                the total breakdown of social order caused by a pandemic of sudden blindness. In the
                part of the book set when the characters are forced into quarantine, the story is
                like a very condensed version of the Gulag Archipelago. Aside from the narrative of
                social chaos, the interactions of the characters allow Mr. Saramago to reflect on
                physical blindness vs. moral blindness. Perhaps the most interesting feature of this
                story is that it is filled with colloquialisms. The most annoying feature of this
                novel is the rendering of dialog. Extended dialog tends to run in single paragraphs
                with no delineation of the speaker and often no punctuation between
                statements.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Journey By Moonlight</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Antal Szerb</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/19/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>David Bentley Hart once published a long list of books that he recommended and
                this was one of them. I was not really impressed. On one hand, the main character's
                journey to Italy in the mid 1930's is fairly interesting. Despite the fine writing,
                I really did not like any of the characters. Nor did I relate to their emotional
                turmoil In a way it reminds me of Death in Venice. Both books struck me as having an
                overblown, morbid fixation on death. Not death as it relates to the human condition,
                but with an individual's fixation on their own death. Mr. Szerb might argue, as does
                one of his characters, that modern civilization has distracted us to such a degree
                that we simply forget about death. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Why Intelligence Fails</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Robert Jervis</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/20/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An examination of two "intelligence failures - the failure to predict the
                Iranian Revolution in 1979 and the mistaken belief that Iraq had weapons of mass
                destruction prior to the second Gulf War. Mr. Jervis does have a number of
                recommendations for improving the process of analysis of intelligence; in particular
                by adopting more rigorous methodologies from social science and academia. (To which
                the cynic will reply - but of course he would recommend that because that is his
                background!) But Mr. Jervis is a very thoughtful and balanced critic. He does not
                argue that the Intelligence Community (IC) should be able to predict the future. And
                in the case of Iraqi WMD, he argues that based on what they know, the IC wasn't out
                of line to predict that Iraq had them - indeed the Intel agencies of all the
                countries involved and the media all believed the same thing at the time. His
                criticism is that the IC should have noted that the actual degree of uncertainty
                with its intel and should have considered ways in which it could have challenged its
                assumptions. Mr. Jervis also points out the intelligence is not policy, and those
                who make policy don't always want better intelligence. Elected officials (and even
                bureaucrats) tend to have pre-conceived notions of what they want based upon their
                political leanings / world view, and better intelligence that runs counter to their
                belief will not be welcome. Indeed, he suggests that policy makers like using the
                IC's mistakes so that politicians can use the IC as a scapegoat. Stylistically, this
                is a dry and academic treatment of the subject, but Mr. Jervis offers a model of
                clear, rational evaluation of evidence. He takes examples of failures from each
                administration from Roosevelt thru George W. Bush (except for maybe Truman) and from
                other nations as well. Nor does he adopt polemical language to make his points. And
                there is the occasional humor: "We are not happy with the apocryphal story of a
                British Foreign Office official who proudly said on his retirement that throughout
                his career he had said there would be no European war and was wrong only
                twice"!</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Greece: Biography of a Modern
                Nation</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Roderick Beaton</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/25/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A fairly balanced history of Greece since its independence from the Ottomans.
                The idea that Greece needs a biography instead of a history is somewhat of a conceit
                of the author; based upon his history, if Greece were a person, it would be a person
                suffering from manic-depression or split personality. I in no way intend this as a
                criticism of Greece or the Greeks, but to poke fun at the author's pretensions. But
                Mr. Beaton does a commendable job of detailing the challenges that the Greeks have
                had in creating an independent, stable, prosperous country. He describes the long
                standing tensions between tradition and modernity, between east and west, between
                religious and ethic identity, between democracy and dictatorship. A useful study
                that probably shed some light on what much of the Balkans have in store as they deal
                with the history of oppression by the Ottoman's and the Soviets.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Castles of Steel</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Robert K. Massie</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/6/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>After 30 years of English &amp; German royal and parliamentary politics with
                some naval development thrown in on the side in Dreadnaught, the payoff comes with
                the history of the war at sea in WWI. Which, as far as battleships go, pretty comes
                down to the Battle of Jutland. I am already familiar with that battle, and Mr.
                Massie does a fine job of describing the action and evaluating the performance of
                the participating admirals and ships (as he does with all the engagements in this
                book.) He gives a great deal of Adm. Jellico, who is usually criticised for
                excessive criticism. But his handling of the British Grand Fleet ensured a
                devastating blockade of Germany, and his tactics at Jutland ensured the German High
                Seas Fleet would not win. Mr. Massie also gives a lot of attention to Churchill's
                performance running the Admiralty, the Gallipoli campaign and the evolution of
                German submarine warfare. A few observations about naval warfare in WWI. Just like
                with the armies on land, technology had evolved to allow the projection of
                tremendous fire power over very long distances. Strategically, communication
                technology allowed the fleet to stay in close contact and coordination with
                headquarters. But tactically, the newness of wireless communication combined with no
                technology to improve navigation considering the high speeds of modern ships meant
                that both the British and the Germans often missed out on great success (the Germans
                at the Battle of the Falklands and the British at Jutland). And, one can't help but
                conclude that the world lost its collective mind in August 1914. The stunning amount
                of casualties inflicted in pursuit of such paltry goals. Also, interesting to
                reflect on the naval competition between Britain and Germany in light of the current
                tensions between the U.S. and China.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Anna Karennina</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Leo Tolstoy</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/19/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Pevear &amp; Volokhonsky translation, which is highly commended online. This
                book had an insert indicating that it was an Oprah Winfrey book club recommendation
                - kudos to Oprah for this recommendation, although I wonder how many people bought
                the book only to discover this edition is 817 pages long! This book has sat in my
                collection for some time now as I had developed somewhat of a negative view of
                Tolstoy. Not exactly sure why, but some of the short stories of his had struck me as
                overly moralistic and perhaps self-righteous. But I was deeply impressed with this
                novel. First of all, the plot summary that I was familiar with was that this was the
                story the "fall" of a high society women who leaves her husband. While that is
                technically true, and while Anna Karennina's emotional struggle is the main driver
                of the story, you could make the argument that she is not the main character in this
                novel. I would argue that Konstantin Levin is actually the main character, and that
                the novel might more accurately been titled "Love and Marriage" (cue the Frank
                Sinatra song …) Tolstoy offers in depth examination of love, marriage and faith and
                the various ways these played out in upper crust Russian society in the 1870's. The
                novel is brilliantly written and I truly enjoyed it. I didn't rank it as a 5 because
                I doubt I'd read the whole thing again, although I might return to the final
                section.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Way West</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>A.B. Guthrie,
                    Jr.</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/21/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A novel about a wagon train making the trip from Missouri to Oregon. By the
                author of The Big Sky, a novel about mountain men. I really enjoyed The Big Sky, but
                this one, not so much. This book was either from Grandpa Krush's collection, or
                maybe Grandpa Rodine's; but since there is a sticker from a bookstore in Boston, I
                assume Grandpa Krush's.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Jenkins' Ear</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Odell &amp; Willard
                    Shepard</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/27/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I inherited this book from Grandpa Rodine. Since there is no cover jacket, I
                assumed it was a history of the "War of Jenkins' Ear" (more generally referred to as
                the War of Austrian Succession." Instead, this is a work of historical fiction, set
                at the start of the Seven Years War with characters relating their experience in the
                War of Jenkins Ear. The stories are very well done. The plot device that drives the
                telling of the stories is far less interesting (and far too wordy.) The authors
                clearly enjoyed the process of getting "inside" their characters. But in the end,
                the plot is not convincing, the dialog is too wordy and whole effect falls
                short.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Seven Ages of
                Washington</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Owen Wister</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/28/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A printed sheet was inserted inside the front cover of this book. It states, "In
                furtherance of the Nation Wide Bicentennial Celebration of the Birth of George
                Washington and as a Prize for Excellence in the Bicentennial Poster Contest
                Conducted Among the Pupils in the Schools of Phelps County, Nebraska, This Book is
                Publicly Presented this 18th day of August, 1932, at the Holdrege Auditorium to Paul
                Rodine through the courtesy of The Holdrege Rotary Club, The Holdrege Womans Club,
                The Holdrege American Legion Auxiliary, The Business and Professional Womans Club of
                Holdrege, The Phelps County Junior Fair." Mr. Wister was invited to give a
                presentation at the University of Pennsylvania about George Washington, and this
                book is an expansion on his talk. He main emphasis it to review Washington's life
                and character through his own words from speeches and letters. His goal was to
                "de-mythologize" Washington in order to illustrate the "real" Washington is more
                impressive than the myth. Dated in style and content.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Life of Andrew Jackson: Complete in One
                    Volume</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Marquis James</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/10/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Inherited from the library of my grandfather - Thaddeus Krush. Originally
                published in 1938, the style is dated. For instance, when referring to the American
                people, he often says "we," where today historians would strive to view their
                subject with an outsiders perspective. And in 2020, could you imagine anyone writing
                the following sentence: "General Jackson was an ideal slave-owner." p349 - and
                surviving the Twitter storm that would follow? But for all the stylistic challenges,
                the book is well researched and won a Pulitzer Prize. Mr. James provides ample
                footnotes and includes frequent quotations from letters and speeches of Jackson, his
                friends and his foes.</d:para>
            <d:para>Mr. Marquis portrays Jackson as the paragon of the Scots-Irish "Border
                Chieftain". Proud and honest to a fault, devoted to his family and friends and
                implacable to his foes. His central political tenet was the preservation of the
                United States and service to the common people (as Jackson understood the needs of
                the people.) Mr. James view Jackson mostly as a conservative"The contest of 1824 …
                witnessed the opening of the schisms that were to wreck the Republican Party and
                remould it, Andrew Jackson's violent moderation superseding the mild radicalism of
                Thomas Jefferson …"p364. "The gradual alteration from border conservative to
                national liberal is noteworthy …" p721 , but one whose views adjusted to his
                perception of what was best for the union. </d:para>
            <d:para>I would probably rate Jackson as the most interesting person in the first half
                of the 1800's, and this book does a good job of capturing the drive and energy of
                one who never sought popularity yet became the most popular American of his era. And
                Mr. James does a very good job of balancing this with the details of his personal
                life. Mr. James clearly views slavery as a great wrong and he notes the hypocrisy in
                the southern attempts to soften the image of slavery by referring to it as the
                "peculiar institution" and to the slaves as "servants." But he does not belabor the
                details of Jackson's brief venture as a slave trader, and he treats Jackson's
                benevolent handling of his slaves as a positive indication of the quality of
                Jackson's character. The chattering classes of today, in their correct (but
                self-righteous) condemnation of the bitter fruit that slavery has born in our
                country, would brand him a simple bigot and consign him to oblivion. The same holds
                true for Mr. James' handling of Jackson's relations with Native Americans. Indeed,
                perhaps the greatest shortcoming of this book is the complete ignoring of the Trail
                of Tears. </d:para>
            <d:para>Two weeks ago, a mob attempted to pull down the statue of Jackson in front of
                the White House. In part, this is what makes Jackson so interesting. He did not
                create the society in which he lived and he was not one to question the pros and
                cons of the social order that he inherited. For that, he deserves no credit and
                clearly falls short of the standard of a "great" man. Yet, if Jackson had joined
                Burr in a successful attempt to create an independent nation along the Mississippi,
                or not defeated the British at New Orleans and prevented them from returning
                Louisiana to Spain or not held the Union together during the South Carolina
                nullification crisis, doesn't it seem probable that slavery would have endured much
                longer in a long running civil war between different sections of are now the U.S.?
                And his personal popularity was key in pulling the process of selecting Presidential
                candidate from the hands of state Congressional delegations and thus to bolstered
                American democratic traditions. And as determined a military foe of the Native
                American as Jackson was, during the campaign against the Creeks, he adopted an
                orphaned Creek boy when no Creek woman would do so and raised him as his own child.
            </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Pale Rider: The Spanish Flu of 1918 and How it
                    Changed the World</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Laura Spinney</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/12/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Thomas read this for a history course this summer; I read it given the current
                COVID-19 pandemic. First off, let's dispense with the review of Ms. Spinney's
                writing style. The book's sub-title with its hackneyed "how it changed the world"
                sets a bad first impression. Given the scope the subject, Ms. Spinney is upfront
                about organizing her book more as a collection of narratives rather that a strict
                chronological layout. I am fine with that approach, but there are times when the
                structure of her paragraphs simply do not make sense. For instance, there is one
                paragraph that begins with a sentence describing the impact of the "Spanish Flu" on
                pregnant women. The next sentence states that many people bled from the nose and
                mouth and the rest of the sentence deals with the experience of soldiers on troop
                transports. There is a section in one chapter that focuses on the flu in Chile that
                concludes with a single paragraph on the Shanshi province in China. Then the chapter
                breaks to a new section examining the flu in Shanshi. Why the orphan paragraph in
                the previous section? She is prone to run-on sentence and sentences in which two
                clauses don't really belong together. She sometimes uses words out of context -
                Chilean Lieutenant Dagoberto Godoy is an "ace pilot" because he flew a plane over
                the Andes (his Wikipedia bio indicates that he never served in time of war, and thus
                never shot down the requisite 5 enemy planes to be classified as an "ace".) And
                there is the sentence in which she states that "By 1918 [Poland] had been entirely
                erase from the map..." The Polish partition was complete in 1795- certainly "by
                1918" but her syntax would imply the partition had only been recently completed. I
                hold the editor and the fact-checkers from her publish (Public Affairs, New York)
                most responsible for allowing so many annoying little errors.</d:para>
            <d:para>Issues of stye aside, Ms. Spinney's coverage of the scientific efforts to
                understand that the flu is top notch. Her coverage of the public policy actions
                taken to try to manage impact of the pandemic are also well done. It is clear from
                her writing that she is not a fan of "traditional" societies, institutions and
                social structures, but she is fair in pointing out where the "traditionalists"
                played a helpful role. And while he sympathies clearly lie with the "scientific"
                mindset, she is honest about the short comings of those who try to practice the
                "scientific method" as well. What I found most interesting in her account is how
                slowly "human nature" changes and indeed how slowly scientific knowledge advances.
                In 1918-19, it was not known that the flu was caused by a virus (or even that such a
                thing a virus existed). Those socialites that best weathered the flu were those that
                practiced the time-honored practices of social distancing and quarantine. Today, we
                know much more about the virus that causes COVID-19, but we still have a very
                limited knowledge of the exact mechanics of how it spreads. Yet the most effective
                response still seems to be social distancing and quarantine of those deemed to be at
                high-risk. But in 1918 as in 2020, the interactions between politicians, bureaucrats
                and scientist seems to have improved very little.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">An Army at Dawn</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Rick Atkinson</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/15/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Stacy's brother Tim gave Thomas Rick Atkinson's three volume history of the US
                Army in Europe during WWII. This is the first volume covering operations in North
                Africa. Most history's of WWII give scant coverage to this period of the war. Mr.
                Atkinson is an outstanding writer who weaves the viewpoints of many of the
                participants into his narrative. It is very easy to criticize the initial
                performance of the U.S. Army in combat and this book amply proves the wisdom of the
                adage "the more you sweat in training, the less you bleed in combat." But this book
                also illustrates just how quickly the Americans learned how to fight.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Victory Machine: The Making &amp; Unmaking of
                    the Warriors Dynasty</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Ethan Strauss</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/18/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Bought this for Anna recently as she has been a fan of Steph Curry and the
                Golden State Warriors. This is not a well written book. It is rambling,
                dis-organized and offers very little insight on what made the Warriors so good.
                Mostly it is a rehashing of Kevin Durant's tenure with the Warriors and Mr. Strauss'
                long running feud with Mr. Durant. Mr. Strauss portrays Mr. Durant as an insecure
                super-star, yet Mr. Strauss comes across as equally insecure. Indeed, Mr. Strauss
                inserts himself into the book far too often. If the book were intended to portray
                life as a reporter covering a great team, that would have been fine. Another
                instance where good editorial guidance could have greatly improved the book. Mr.
                Strauss presents some interesting views, but it in the end it is not a compelling
                treatment of its subject.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Land of the Firebird: The Beauty of Old
                    Russia</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Suzanne Massie</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/26/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An art history of pre-revolutionary Russia. Although Ms. Massie has great
                enthusiasm for the subject, this book still reads somewhat like a textbook.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Collected Tales of Nikolai
                Gogol</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Nikolai Gogol</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/2/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Selections from the various collections of short stories by Gogol, translated by
                Pevear &amp; Volokhonsky. The first half of the collection are stories set in the
                Ukraine and the second half are set in St. Petersburg. I preferred the one set in
                the Ukraine. As an American, I would describe him as the Russian equivalent of
                Washington Irving. A light hearted critic of the foibles of the self-important, the
                ability to describe the details of the daily lives and settings of his subject and
                the willingness to weave the supernatural to make a memorable impression.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Envy</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Joseph Epstein</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/4/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A relatively brief treatment of one of the seven deadly sins; written as part of
                a collection covering all seven. Each chapter is, in effect, an essay on an aspect
                of envy. And, as usual, Mr. Epstein brings his tremendous learning to bear upon the
                subject and writes with style, charm and wit. I laughed out loud about five or six
                times while reading this book. For instance, he writes a chapter dealing with the
                envy the old hold for youth - he titled the chapter: "The Young, God Damn Them." Or
                this example of understated irony: "The rich want to be beautiful or wish themselves
                wise; and the wise, if they really are wise, know that the wisdom begins with the
                acknowledgement that one knows nothing, so, really, what the hell good is that."
                Looking at these two examples, I realize that they do not do Mr. Epstein justice.
                The chapter title, removed from the context of the book, make him seem like an angry
                crank. And the quote could imply that he has no respect for wisdom. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Native Son</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Richard Wright</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/10/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Reminded me a bit of "Crime and Punishment", where the author portrays the inner
                struggle of a young man who has committed murder. But while the structure of the
                novels are similar, the "outlook" of the novels differ greatly. Mr. Wright is just
                as effective as Dostoevsky in taking the reader inside the head of one consumed by
                the commission of murder and attempts to avoid capture in the aftermath.
                Unfortunately, once the story moves into the court house, Native Son devolves into a
                series of long speeches about the deplorable social conditions faced by African
                Americans. These ruminations are worth reading, but would have been better as an
                essay. The end effect is similar to Sinclair's "The Jungle," where a gripping story
                devolves into a political tract. Mr. Wright was a member of the Communist Party for
                a while, and this seems apparent in the final section of the novel. But, not knowing
                much of his biography, and just inferring from what I read in "Native Son", his
                Communism is unrecognisable when contrasted to that of the Bolsheviks. It seems most
                concerned with support for organized labor and for racial equality. And while
                American communism never achieved lasting influence and International communism has
                ignominiously crumbled, in hindsight it must be said that on the issue of racial
                equality the American communists were correct. It is a shame that the loathing the
                average American bore the communists probably served to discredit racial equality
                once it was espoused by the communists. Yet in this instance, the communists deserve
                some credit, while the Democratic Party bears the shame of enabling "Jim Crow" and
                the Republican Party (in the 20th century) that of generally ignoring the issue
                altogether. Issues of artistic style aside, this remains a compelling
                novel.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Silk Roads: A New History of the
                    World</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Peter Frankopan</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/13/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I bought this book for Thomas due to his great interest in his high school World
                History course. Mr. Frankopan rightly notes the traditional historical emphasis on
                the rise and triumph of the West. This book puts the spotlight on the history and
                influence (religious, cultural and economic) of south and central Asia. Until his
                coverage reaches the 20th century, I felt he was reasonably balanced and did a great
                job of covering event that are unfamiliar to most in the West. For all his
                enthusiasm for his subject, there are some flaws in his outlook. Mr. Frankopan seems
                to feel that in order to boost the profile of the Silk Road region, he must
                denigrate the West. For instance, if the Mongols destroyed certain cities to
                intimidate those they will encounter later, he notes that for their historical
                reputation for savagery, they were pragmatically asserting their authority over the
                regions they were conquering (and, in total, preserving the great wealth they were
                ruling). He does not give the Crusaders, or the British or the Americans any such
                benefit of the doubt. Indeed, if America had followed the conventions of the
                Mongols, we would have dropped nuclear bombs on Baghdad, Tehran and Kabul in the
                aftermath of 9/11. And he states: "The great iron, then, that although Europe
                experienced a glorious Golden age, … it was forged by violence." True, but how does
                that differ from the Persian Empire, or Alexander and the Hellenic empire, or the
                Roman Empire, or the Byzantines, or the Islamic caliphates, or the Mongol and
                Ottoman Empires - each of which established it hegemony over central Asia by
                force?</d:para>
            <d:para>This leads us to the 20th and 21st Centuries, which receive as much coverage as
                all of the ages past. He criticizes the European powers from asserting their
                economic and political interests. By implication, this is a bad thing, even though,
                based on the evidence presented in his history, they were no worse than those who
                proceeded them. In the end, he is product of post-WWII western education that
                believes in human rights, the rule of law, democracy and intellectual development,
                as practiced in the West. When the West fails to live up to his ideals, he is quick
                to criticize. And that would be a fine approach to take, if you also held the
                Soviets, the Chinese and the Indians to the same standard. He accurately notes the
                wide ranging attempts by the Soviets to reshape the region to its own purposes, yet
                this is done without censure. And he treats American involvement in the Middle East
                as tragic. Certainly, it has been so for the Middle East. But unlike the British,
                the US (to date) has bankrupted itself in defense of a colonial empire. The US has
                failed to remake the Middle East in the image idealized by the West, yet the US has
                enough population and natural resource on its own to fall as far as the British did
                in the 20th Century. Mr. Frankopan believes the center of the world sits in Central
                Asia, which makes him largely blind to North and South America and Africa (even
                Egypt generally gets short shrift.) </d:para>
            <d:para>There are a couple of minor nitpicks I have with regards to his coverage of the
                Crusades. He criticized the eventual focus of the Crusades on the capture of Egypt
                due to a simply desire for plunder and wealth. That is certainly partially true, but
                from a strategic point of view, whoever controls Egypt controls Jerusalem. It is no
                accident that Salahdin, who captured Jerusalem from the Crusade state had first
                established his rule over Egypt. (And note, that even today, the US provides
                enormous amounts of aid to Egypt in order to preserve peace between Egypt and
                Israel.)</d:para>
            <d:para>Aside from my substantial criticisms, this is still a worthwhile book. Mr.
                Frankopan writes well, and in his enthusiasm does remind us that there is much to
                learn from outside our own culture.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Nicomachean Ethics</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Aristotle</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/16/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This is a tough book to read straight through; it is really better suited as the
                basis for a course in ethics. The first challenge is in the specialized language.
                For instance, Aristotle’s prime concern in this book is how to live to achieve
                happiness. In modern usage, happiness is a feeling - think of the yellow smiley face
                figure. But for Aristotle, happiness is not a feeling, but the achievement of the
                highest possible goodness. Good is another word that differs greatly from
                Aristotle’s meaning and common usage today.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Science and the Good</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>John D. Hunter and Paul
                    Nedelisky</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/20/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An interesting overview of the attempt by some scientist to assert a scientific
                theory of morality. In some sense this is understandable given the endless conflict
                and controversy that continue in spite of the best efforts of philosophers and
                theologians to develop a universal standard of morality. But the authors point out
                that over 200 years of scientific efforts have done no better. Worse, some
                scientists, in order to make their hypothesises fit their facts, seem to have
                concluded that there is no such thing as morality at all. The authors are not at all
                anti-scientific, and certainly aren't in the least pro-religion. Rather, they are
                two left-of-center academicians who recognize that an attempt to explain away
                morality allows anyone to justify their actions, good or bad.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Republic</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Plato</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/1/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An electronic book from Amazon.com. The formatting was absolute trash. Instead
                of electronic text, the book consisted of electronic images of scanned pages. The
                images didn't even fit 100% within the viewer, and the type was painfully small. And
                I suspect that there are some pages missing. Despite this, The Republic may be
                Plato's most famous work. It is written as a dialogue between Socrates and his
                friends, and begins with some of his colleagues asserting that the unjust are
                happier than the just. The rest of the book is an examination of justice, happiness
                and the nature of the city state that would promote justice. It is best to think of
                this as a "thought experiment" rather than a handbook for a political platform.
                Because many of his ideas, taken simply at face value, sound more like the republic
                of Florence under Savoronella, or the Bolshevik Soviet Union or Nazi Germany.
                Indeed, Plato's (or Socrates, I'm not sure if these are truly Socrates' views)
                suggestions point to the modern obsession of developing the right social structure
                to ensure human flourishing. But if, instead, you read it a framework for
                questioning human learning and behavior in the pursuit of betterment, it is still
                useful even if some of the prescriptions have been dis-proven by later history. All
                in all, I prefer Aristotle's "lecture" style of writing and his emphasis on
                achieving the "mean" between an excess and a dearth of a virtue to Plato's dialogues
                and emphasis on the eternal forms. Too many times, Socrates' companions are little
                more than straw-men, or worse, sycophants who simply agree with everything he
                proposes.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">On the Nature of Things</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Lucretius</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/10/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An extended poem describing the tenets of Epicureanism. Key points are that all
                matter is ultimately composed of tiny objects (he tends to call germs, but what we
                would call atoms) and empty spaces; that this matter is eternal and of infinite
                number, that everything composed of these basic building blocks is not eternal, that
                everything is explained by the interaction of these objects and the forces which
                cause them to move. Epicurus said that there were gods, but that they were not
                involved in the natural order; Lucretius seems more inclined to the view that gods
                don't exist. (Although he does dedicate the poem to Venus - the may simply be a
                manner of style.) The reading is tough sledding; perhaps his Latin poetry was
                eloquent. This translation certainly is not although it does seem dated. As a work
                of science, like most "scientific" works from the classical era, it contains many
                errors of interpretation of how nature works. But as a work of history of scientific
                thought, it is a useful illustration of how the ancients reasoned. If their
                conclusions were often wrong, the process of observation and rational argument
                clearly anticipate modern scientific methods.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Aristotle for Everybody</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Mortimer J.
                    Adler</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/16/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I had this book when I was young, but never read more than the first chapter. It
                is a shame that it has taken me so long to return to this book. An excellent
                overview on the wide range of concepts evaluated and explained by Aristotle. The
                style of this book is somewhat dry and pedantic, like a text book, but not bad. Its
                great strength is in the clear explanation of what Aristotle taught and how it
                applies even today. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Experience of God: Being, Consciousness,
                    Bliss</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>David Bentley
                    Hart</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/22/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Dr. Hart presents an argument for the existence of God by refuting atheist
                attempts to limit all knowledge to that which can be physically verified in the
                framework of the scientific method. More importantly, he reformulates the common
                arguments for the existence of God as traditionally espoused by the world's great
                religions (as well as the Greek philosophers such as Plato and Aristotle.) In
                summary, the very fact that the universe exists (which science cannot explain
                because it can only deal in the realm of what already exists) is the primary
                argument. Science can deal with an endless chain of causes and effects, but there
                must be an "uncreated" and "unchanging" being outside of any cause and effect for
                anything to exist at all. The fact that we all have and recognize consciousness is
                his next proof; he argues against any attempts to explain consciousness as a result
                of any purely material cause. Incidentally, he includes a very strong critique on
                the idea of "artificial intelligence" and the analogy of the brain (and
                intelligence) as some sort of advanced "computer" algorithm. Finally, the sense of
                bliss, for instance in human kind's pursuit of the good, the true and the beautiful.
                "God is thus experienced as that bliss in which our natures have their consummation
                because that bliss is already, in God, the perfect consummation of divine unity of
                being and consciousness: infinite being knows itself in infinite consciousness and
                therefore infinitely rejoices." This is not a work for the casual reader. True to
                his style, there are many long sentences and arcane words. But his arguments are
                clear, thorough and easy to follow.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Rise and Fall of Great
                Powers</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Paul Kennedy</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>9/22/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This book came from Stacy's father's collection; her brother Tom recommended
                that I read it. The reason I hadn't planned on reading this book, indeed the reason
                I have taken so long to actually getting around to reading it is that I had
                developed a prejudice against the book in my time as a Midshipman. The book was
                published in 1987, when I was a Plebe. This was during the very heart of the Reagan
                era defense build up of conventional military forces to contest the Soviets. The
                Reagan era also saw many heated debates between those who contended that America was
                on the decline due to Vietnam and economic competition with Japan and those who
                argued for the expansion of American military power and an aggressive policy to
                counter Soviet influence. Needless to say, the more popular view at the Naval
                Academy was in support of an active, "muscular" American involvement in world
                affairs. When Mr. Kennedy's book was published, I remember that it was lauded by
                those were on the other side of the argument. As I was young, and didn't enjoy the
                idea that the United States could be a declining power, I was inherently disposed to
                avoid the book. A further prejudice against the book was a result of Mr. Kennedy's
                very bad luck to have published it just two years before the fall of the Berlin Wall
                and the collapse of the Soviet military threat. He joined the very long list of
                experts who failed to foresee this prospect.</d:para>
            <d:para>Having finally read his book, this serves as a very useful reminder to question
                your prejudices. The central premise of the book is to examine the how various
                nations rose to great power in the periods from 1500 - 1987 and then fell from
                power. It gives very great weight to the economic component of power, and if it has
                a central argument, it is that it is very expensive to maintain military forces
                strong enough to project power, and it is even more expensive to maintain a strong
                military presence far from a nation's border. Mr. Kennedy does not discount the role
                that diplomatic and military skill and technical innovation play in creating a
                powerful nation. He simply asks the obvious question of how a nations economy can
                support its ambitions. For instance, in discussing Germany during World War I, he
                offers an explanation for the food shortages in Germany that I have not encountered
                before. The most common explanation was that the British naval blockade was so
                effective. But given the large landmass of Germany and the Austria-Hungarian empire,
                this never seemed to be a convincing argument. Much more convincing is Mr. Kennedy's
                argument that the sheer number of men pulled into the military (and the armament
                factories) resulted in a critical shortage of manpower left to support agriculture. </d:para>
            <d:para>There is nothing anti-American (or anti- any particular nation) in his
                arguments, and he made no predictions that Japan, or the Soviets, or the Chinese
                would inevitably supplant the US as a global power. Indeed, he is very balanced in
                evaluating the relative strengths and weaknesses of the large powers at the end of
                the 20th century. He clearly recognized the great strain the Cold War had placed
                upon the Soviet economy, but like nearly everyone else, he had no idea how quickly
                the Soviet Union would collapse. Rather than arguing that Japan would surpass the
                US, he anticipates many of the problems that would hinder Japan since the 1990's.
                And he noted the rise of the Chinese economy since the death of Mao, and gave some
                thought to the impact of sustained growth yet did not anticipate just how far China
                would advance. And he did not foresee (but who did?) the economic revolution of
                computer technology. But his central examination of the relationship of economic
                development (and decline) with political, diplomatic and military power seems to me
                to be quite sound.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Day of Battle</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Rick Atkinson</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/4/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>The second of Mr. Atkinson's three-volume history of the U.S. Army in Europe in
                WWII. This volume covers the invasion of Sicily and the Italian campaign through the
                capture of Rome on June 5, 1944. As always, Mr. Atkinson delivers a compelling
                narrative. He does an excellent job weaving first hand accounts into the flow of
                events. He follows some individuals throughout the course of the campaign, and
                weaves in other individual voices to highlight particular events. He does not offer
                bold judgements of those in command, but he does evaluate controversies from all
                sides; noting the generally accepted verdicts while presenting the case of those
                being judged. In this volume, General Patton's slapping of two hospitalized soldiers
                and General Mark Clark's attacks along the Rapido River and the break out from Anzio
                are clearly the subjects that have received the most criticism over the years. Mr.
                Atkinson presents all the available facts, the reactions of those who participated
                in the events, the reactions of other officers and later historians and an
                occasional pointed comment of his own. But in the end, he leaves the reader to their
                own judgement.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Style: The Art of Writing
                Well</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>F.L. Lucas</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/6/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Highly recommended by Joseph Epstein. A common sense evaluation of how to write
                with good style. Certainly a highly subjective goal, but Mr. Lucas' suggestions seem
                to me to be on the right track. In summary: be honest, be concise, end sentences
                with strong words and paragraphs with strong sentences, pay attention to metre and
                don't be afraid of "poetic" devices such as simile and metaphor. In style, this book
                comes across as a lecture by a professor of long tenure. It is dated in the sense
                that many of his examples are in French or Greek. Perhaps, as a result of frequent
                trips to the endnotes for the translations, this makes his chapters seem longer than
                they need to be. If Mr. Epstein was a student of Mr. Lucas in developing his own
                style, then I would say that the student has surpassed the master.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Confidence Man</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Herman Melville</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/7/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Melville's journey to sea with the whale ship Pequod is unforgeable; his journey
                down the Mississippi on the steamer Fidele is long-winded and confusing.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Charterhouse of Parma</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Stendhal</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/08/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>1</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This book was recommended in the Wall Street Journal Review section some years
                ago. I downloaded the electronic book from Amazon, read about 120 pages and then set
                it aside. I came back to it today and realized that I could not realized that I
                could not recall any details of what I earlier read. A few pages more and I recalled
                that I do not care for wordy style or the lives of the noblemen and women portrayed
                in the novel.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Abelard and Heloise: The Letters and Other
                    Writings</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>William Levitan,
                    translator</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/9/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Anna is reading this in her English class. When I was ordering the electronic
                version of the book from Amazon, I was amused by one review in which the reader was
                disappointed that there was very little romance in the letters, but a great deal of
                instruction on how to run a monastery! The modern idea of a love letter is based on
                the Greek version of love Eros. While Peter and Heloise do acknowledge their
                "erotic" love, the letters are really more centered on the Greek version of love
                Agape. These are letters between two very intelligent and highly educated people, so
                the letters read generally read more like academic treatises than personal letters.
                But they do offer a very personal insight into life in medieval life and philosophy.
            </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Thomas Aquinas: A Portrait</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Denys Turner</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/23/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An introduction to the theology of Thomas Aquinas. Mr. Turner's style is rather
                dense, which is ironic since he frequently notes that St. Thomas' style was plain
                and direct. I prefer G.K. Chesterton's book in terms of biography and I prefer Peter
                Kreeft's A Shorter Summa as an introduction to his theology. But this book is
                worthwhile if you want more than a cursory introduction.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Storm of Steel</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Ernst Junger</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/27/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Capt. Junger's memoirs of his service in the German army in WWI. He survived
                four years of combat in the trenches and was wounded 7 times. Here is his account of
                the battlefield: "The Modern battlefield is like a huge, resting piece of machinery.
                Countless hidden eyes, ears, and arms are idly watching for some poor soul to arrive
                alone at any minute. Then as a fiery overture, a single red flare rises high above
                from some hole in the earth. A thousand guns roar at the same time. At a stroke, the
                work of annihilation begins, driven by countless levers and its crushing gears.
                Battlefield commands increase like sparks and flashes through a tight electrical
                network. This initiates and spurs on increased destruction. From the rear areas, a
                steady stream of new people and material are set in motion, and thrown into the
                surge of annihilation. Everyone feels compelled to reach the focal point of the
                deadly new events. It is as if a whirlpool seizes them from afar, and a mysterious
                will yanks them in with a relentless precision."</d:para>
            <d:para>One interesting note about Junger. After serving in combat for four years and
                winning the highest medals awarded by the German army, he never rose above the rank
                of Captain nor served in a higher capacity than that of company commander.
                Tocqueville, in Democracy in America, expresses the opinion that in war, democracies
                are at a disadvantage a the start of the war but have the advantage in an extended
                conflict (book 2, chapter 24). He suggests this is the case because in a democracy,
                military service is generally undesirable and those who are ambitious take their
                talents to other fields. In contrast, in an aristocracy, the officer class comes
                from the nobility and tends to attract the best of that class. Junger was not from
                the aristocracy and enlisted at the start of the war. The German army was quick to
                promote promising enlisted men to the rank of 2nd Lieutenant, which is what happened
                with Junger after his first stint in the trenches in 1914. From that point forward,
                he was promoted twice in a period of about 4 years. In the modern American army, all
                junior officers can expect to be promoted with the exact same rapidity. Yet he was
                one of the finest soldiers in the German army with extensive experience in combat.
                He does note quite frequently that officers of longer tenure (and often with noble
                titles) were promoted ahead of him. So perhaps Tocqueville's suggestion has some
                merit, at least in this case. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Democracy in America</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Alexis de
                    Tocqueville</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/30/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>When you write a book as astute and well regarded as this, a book to which
                academics still turn more than a century later, you may be so lucky as Tocqueville
                and be rewarded with an introduction by Joseph Epstein. Mr. Epstein begins his
                introduction with this: "The older one gets, the more it becomes clear that it is a
                great mistake not to have been brilliant when very young. Difficult to arrange, I
                realize, but what a splendid saving of time it is to come into one's intelligence
                early!" This is a long work, undertaken by the author not so much to study the
                United States as to understand the impact of the dying of European aristocracy and
                the rise of individual freedom, political liberty and democratic government. He
                travelled in the United States and offers brilliant insight in to the strengths and
                weaknesses of the young nation. And he offers commentary on what he thinks this
                means for the future of democratic government. I found myself highlighting far more
                passages than I can include here for future consideration. But as a warning, I found
                that this book is best taken in short, regular doses. His writing focuses on the
                abstractions he forms from the experiences of his study and his travels. His style
                is direct and he has the gift of creating a very vivid abstraction. Equally often,
                too much abstraction without supporting detail makes it hard to hold interest.
            </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Apology</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Plato</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>10/31/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Not sure this really counts as a book, but since it was sold as such by Amazon I
                will count it. This is Plato's account of Socrates’s defense during his trial for
                atheism and corruption of youth. This should be required reading for all high school
                students.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Favorite Poems of Henry Wadsworth
                    Longfellow</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Henry Wadsworth
                    Longfellow</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/4/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Inherited this from either Grandpa Rodine or Nanny. I'm not a huge poetry fan,
                so it took a while to get through his longer poems, such as "Song of Hiawatha." Long
                though this poem was, it was still an interesting retelling of Native American
                folklore. "Evangeline" was another long poem, but I did not care for it's soap opera
                twists and turns of fate.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Guns at Last Light</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Rick Atkinson</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/7/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>The third and final volume of his "Liberation Trilogy" covering the American
                Army in Europe from D-Day until the German surrender. Fine writing, as usual. Two
                nits to pick with this volume, both very minor. First, I'm not sure why he devoted
                so much coverage to the Yalta Conference, most of the other conferences of the
                allies were passed over more succinctly. Second, he does not mention that when
                Roosevelt died in Warm Springs, Georgia, he was in the company of his mistress, not
                his wife. Normally, I would commend him for bypassing salacious details not germane
                to his story. But he had not afforded the same courtesy with regards to speculation
                or gossip about Eisenhower and Patton. Aside for those minor point, he is very
                balanced in his assessments of the performance of the American and British generals
                (and the French and Germans, too.) Alas, General Simpson, the commander of the US
                Ninth Army gets very little attention, although he has one of the best quotes:
                "Never send an infantryman where you can send an artillery shell." Most people will
                not care about this, but my father's father served in the 102nd Division in the 9th
                Army. The 102nd Division gets a brief mention in the book for it's discovery of a
                German massacre of prisoners at Gardelegen; this is something my grandfather would
                have witnessed personally because he was an Army doctor.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Fire Upon the Earth</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Norman F.
                    Langford</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/9/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I think I inherited this one from Nanny. Could be sub-titles "A History of
                Christianity for Young Protestants." Like many books that cover a very long period
                of history, this focuses much more on recent events than early events.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">What is History</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Edward Hallet
                    Carr</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/15/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Inherited this from Nanny, it is inscribed 'Thaddeus P Krush 5/63.' Although I'm
                not sure my grandfather actually read the book because the binding was very tight
                and the book did not feel "broken in." Thomas was assigned this book his freshman
                year at Tufts. This is a thought-provoking, but uneven book; it is a series of
                lectures given by Mr. Carr. The first chapter is best, but they get progressively
                weaker. On the positive side, he commends historians to have an "imaginative
                understanding for the minds of the people with whom he is dealing, for the thought
                behind their acts." He notes that history is not just the assembly of all possible
                facts on a subject, but involves which facts are relevant. He is suspicious of
                historians making moral judgements on their subject. On a more problematic note, he
                argues that history be treated as a "science" along the lines of the "social
                sciences." He correctly notes that the social sciences differ from the physical
                sciences in that they cannot separate the "observer" from the "observed." But his
                disdain for providing definitions as being "pedantic" leads him into trouble. He
                doesn't clearly delineate what he means by "science", rather using analogy to other
                branches of learning that in modern usage are known as sciences (e.g. physics,
                botany). Like those who utilize the modern "scientific method," he attempts to limit
                philosophy, theology and morality from the evaluation of historical evidence. This
                would be fine, except that he then takes on the subject of "progress" in history. He
                notes the problems with what is known as the "Whig" interpretation of history in
                which things are always getting better. He notes that this was a self-serving
                viewpoint for historians of the British empire at the peak of its power.
                Never-the-less, he argues that the "progress" of history has been for the best
                because it was the result of interactions that lead us to where we are today - it is
                best because it is. In his chapter on causation, this is really where he runs into
                problems with his refusal to clearly define terms. His idea of causation, in
                Aristotelian terms, is merely of the "efficient" causes - every event is the result
                of a constant interplay of cause and effect. His belief in "progress" is now
                problematic, because that is a value judgement implying "final" causes. He correctly
                notes that the Judeo-Christian world view of man's progress towards perfection in
                God is the source of this view of history. He throws out the theological and
                philosophical basis for this view - the "final" cause and maintains a belief that
                "efficient" causes have an inherent direction. And he seems to really mus-understand
                the idea of "chance", or "accident" in his preferred usage. He seems to mean
                "chance" to be an occurrence that has no cause - more on line of the term "miracle."
                But, to take an example from my field of software engineering. The computer operates
                at the level of 1's and 0's - known as bits. Sometime bits flip unintentionally and
                change data. There is always a cause for this flip (electro-magnetic interference)
                but when it happens and how it affects the data is for all practical purposes
                unforeseeable. His final chapter, where he tries to provide some rough
                generalizations on what the future hold, is the weakest. As a side note, he had one
                very interesting comment on the Russian Revolution. He asserts that the Bolsheviks
                were very conscious of how the French Revolution played out and were worried about a
                "Napoleon" taking power. When Lenin died, mos Bolsheviks viewed Trotsky as the
                likely candidate as the Soviet Napoleon given his military role in the civil war.
                And thus, they over-looked Stalin.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Philosophy 101 by Socrates</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Peter Kreeft</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/17/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I wasn't planning on including this again; I had read the book already in 2010.
                But I noticed that I had included no comments in the 2010 entry and I remembered
                that I was waiting to comment on this book until after reading Plato's Apology. So,
                it has only taken me 10 years to getting around to it! I mentioned that I thought
                all high school students should have to read the Apology; this book is an excellent
                companion. Rather than a linear examination of the text, Dr. Kreeft offers a number
                of claims about "what is philosophy" and illustrates these claims from the words of
                Socrates. Dr. Kreeft's strongest claim is that we are all philosophers and that we
                each have the responsibility of self-examination.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Dandelion Wine</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Ray Bradbury</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/21/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A beautifully written fictionalized account of childhood during the summer of
                1928 in Waukegan, Illinois. When I was young, I read a great deal of Mr. Bradbury's
                stories and his novel Fahrenheit 451 in high school English. He has a vivid
                imagination that strikes off in often startling directions. In this case, an
                idealized picture of childhood is intermixed with reflections on the role of
                technology in life and on death. Interestingly, this book deal almost solely with
                the viewpoints of the young and the very old. When the adults / parents are involved
                in the story, they are generally dealing with some crisis.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Socratic Logic</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Dr. Peter Kreeft</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/22/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Found this book when looking for books about Aristotle after reading <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Aristotle for
                    Everybody</emphasis>. Thought this might be useful for Thomas when he takes his
                course in Logic at Tufts. This is an examination of the rules of logic as developed
                by the ancient Greeks; Socrates gets pride of place in the title for the development
                of the 'Socratic Method' of inquiry. But much of the formal structure of logic was
                developed by Aristotle. This method of logic is "broader" than the boolean logic I
                use as a software engineer; and its use of Aristotelian causes is broader than the
                understanding of causes in the scientific method. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Loyal Son</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Daniel Epstein</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/25/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Mom gave this to me for Christmas last year. Based on the title, I thought this
                would be a biography of William Franklin; but in this case the sub-title is
                illuminating: "The War in Ben Franklin's House." In summary, it is an examination of
                the relationship between Benjamin (the "patriot") and William (the "loyalist"). Not
                bad. I don't much care for the author's style. The book could have used better
                editing as he is often careless with dates.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">No Place to Hide</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>David Bradley</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>11/29/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Inherited this book from Grandpa Rodine. Dr. Bradley was a doctor tasked with
                monitoring radiation levels during the first two atomic test explosions on Bikini
                Atoll in 1946. This book is his journal of the operation and was intended to educate
                the American public on the dangers of radiation sickness inherent in the use of
                atomic weapons. Having grown up at the end of the Cold War era, none of the details
                on radiation were new to me. But Dr. Bradley offers an interesting insider's view on
                how the tests were conducted. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Tragic Mountains: The Hmong, the Americans and the
                    Secret Wars for Laos, 1942-1992</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Jane
                    Hamilton-Merritt</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/1/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>We inherited this from Stacy's father. The book is inscribed: "July 4th, 1993.
                George: I don't think I shall ever forget this 'neck of the woods' either. Allen L.
                Pope." Mr. Pope is mentioned in a footnote in the book and he was a prisoner in
                Indonesia when the Kalaris' lived there (I'm pretty sure there is an article in our
                files describing his release.) I started reading this book about 10 or 12 years ago
                knowing that Stacy's father worked in Laos in the early 1960's. The book is very
                interesting, but I paused my reading as the events approached the U.S. withdrawal
                from south east Asia in the early 1970's. I knew things did not work out well for
                the Hmong and that the "rest of the story" was going to be sad. Having finished the
                book at last, I can attest that indeed the Hmong were abandoned to a terrible fate.
                I can only imagine that Stacy's father found this to be a difficult book to read
                given his personal connection to the events in question. I must commend Ms.
                Hamilton-Merrit for the sheer volume of first-hand research that went into this
                book.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Black Death</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Rosemary Horrox, translator
                    and editor.</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/5/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Anna's college English professor, who is actually a history professor, assigned
                readings from this book. This is a collection of primary accounts of the bubonic
                plague epidemic in Europe in the late 1340's. It wasn't on his original course
                syllabus, but he threw it in given its relevance to our own COVID epidemic. Like any
                collection of primary accounts, the reader suffers from the lack of narrative flow.
                Even so, this was a fascinating book. As much as human knowledge has advanced in 700
                years, we have still been taken by surprise with COVID and we still struggle to
                understand the causes, effects and long term impact. If many in the 1300's would
                ascribe the plague to the will of God, they were still aware that there were
                physical causes and thus hope for a treatment. Today, we have a much better
                understanding of how diseases spread, yet many ascribe political causes to the
                spread COVID and there is still much we don't know about how COVID spreads and why
                some are affected more than others.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Othello</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>William
                    Shakespeare</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/9/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Such beautiful language used for such an ugly story.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Discourse on Free Will</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Desiderius Erasmus and
                    Martin Luther</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/22/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Not many people today remember Erasmus, who was one of the most learned men of
                his day. I'm sure that many (non-Lutherans) today would not even remember Martin
                Luther unless they dimly recollect from a wold history course that he was one of the
                prime movers of the Protestant Reformation. Early in their careers, both were
                greatly concerned with corrupt practices in the Church. When he finally split from
                the Church, Luther hoped that Erasmus would follow. But Erasmus did not, and in his
                letter "On the Freedom of the Will", he stated that his primary objection to
                Luther's views was that Luther rejected human "free will." Erasmus defined free will
                as "a power of the human will by which a man can apply himself to the things which
                lead to eternal salvation, or turn away from them." And in making his case that
                humans indeed possess free will, he recognized that Luther would only accept
                evidence from the Bible. So he limits his arguments, although he does point out
                Luther's inconsistency in rejecting arguments by the "Church Fathers" because they
                are only men and thus sinners, yet his followers accept Luther's authority on how to
                interpret scripture. In style, Erasmus is humble and gentle, yet very logical. In
                response, Luther is quite bombastic and critical. He rejects Erasmus' definition of
                free will, yet does not provide a clear definition himself. Luther flatly rejects
                the possibility that humans have free will, and asserts that if they do any good, it
                is because God has given them the "gift' or grace to do so. Because Erasmus'
                arguments do not address his own definition of free will, he rejects them and does
                not bother to offer much evidence. If this were a formal debate, such as on in which
                a high school debate team participates, Erasmus wins hands down. If we use Erasmus'
                definition of free will, the fact that Luther thinks it is necessary to try to
                convince Erasmus of his point of view proves that he and Erasmus have some measure
                of personal choice in the matter. This is the closest statement from Luther that I
                could find that explains his definition of free will: "The supreme concern of free
                will is to exercise itself in moral righteousness, or the works of that law by which
                its blindness and impotency derive their assistance." This tells us not what free
                will is, but what it does. I think Luther is confusing God's "final" causes with the
                "formal" and "efficient" causes that dominate our day to day life. Luther seems to
                think that God, in having a final end in mind, must therefore control all of the
                efficient causes that in the end will reach that final goal. But in the court of
                public opinion in the 1500's, Luther's much more emotional approach to the question
                clearly had a major impact. In today's age, Erasmus' arguments would carry the day
                in the halls of academia, but Luther's would carry the day out on the political
                campaign trail. My ultimate critique of Luther, based solely on this exchange, is
                that he was too caught up in his own ego. Pascal had a brilliant insight when he
                noted that the "heart has reasons that reason knows not." In his letter, Erasmus
                attempts to align the "love" of the heart with a rational evaluation of evidence.
                Luther is all heart; accepting that God loves man, he rejects nearly all rational
                thought as "sophistry." Personally, I find Erasmus much more convincing.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Last Lion: Visions of Glory,
                    1874-1932</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>William
                    Manchester</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/26/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I think we inherited this book from Stacy's father. It is the first volume of a
                three-volume biography of Winston Churchill. Mr. Manchester writes very well, this
                is as engrossing as American Caesar. He presents Churchill in all his glory and in
                all his short-comings. Mr. Manchester clearly regards him as the greatest Englishman
                of the 20th Century, but his biography does not fall into simple hagiography.
                Churchill is convincingly portrayed as the single most insightful strategist in
                either the Allied or Central Power camp, yet he is something of a Cassandra as he is
                unable to convince others of his views. He takes the blame for the debacle at the
                Dardanelles, yet it was Kitchener and Gen. Ian Hamilton who botched the job. He
                enacted a number of benefits aimed at the working class and the poor, yet he earned
                the undying enmity of organized labor by refusing to be bullied by strikers. His
                energy was unmatched in government, yet he was periodically afflicted with
                depression. In all, Mr. Manchester is commendably balanced. When he covers a subject
                that has aroused controversy, such as the Dardanelles campaign, he gives Churchill's
                views as well as the views of others who criticized Churchill. And just like Robert
                Massie in Castles of Steel, he make a compelling argument Churchill was 100% correct
                in proposing the operation and that the reason it failed was solely due to Army
                incompetence. For instance, Kitchener waffled for months before committing troops,
                Hamilton chose to land at the tip of the peninsula instead of its base (as suggested
                by the Navy) and compounded his mistake with an unorganized and dilatory landing
                operation that allowed the Turks to seize the high ground overlooking the landing
                zones. Nor does Mr. Manchester shy from the portrayal of the upper-class (in the
                English sense of class, not the American) ignorance/indifference/prejudice against
                the lower classes and colonial people. Mr. Manchester does not excuse this, but he
                does place his views in the context of Churchill's upbringing and the society in
                which he lived. And, when Churchill's views evolved, he portrays that as well. I
                found only two small short-comings with the book. First, Mr. Manchester very briefly
                delves into Churchill's "psychology," including an outdated examination that links
                Churchill's "body type" with his personality. But to his credit, he moves past this
                very quickly and in no way attempts to play the role of Churchill's "therapist." The
                second shortcoming is that he goes perhaps a bit too far in giving a portrayal of
                Victorian and Edwardian society in England. Interesting, but doesn't always add much
                to the story.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Navy Football: Return to
                Glory</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>T.C. Cameron</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/27/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Christmas gift from Stacy. Apparently Mr. Cameron is a reporter for the
                Annapolis Capital-Gazette. This explains the good and bad of this book. The book is
                a history of Navy football focusing on the years between 1950 and the present (book
                was published in 2017). He interviewed many of the featured players and coaches; his
                quotes from these interviews are the highlight of this book. His style is spare but
                sometimes he is confusing by trying to be too brief. The book ends up feeling like a
                collection of newspaper articles without much narrative flow. There are occasional
                odd paragraph breaks. And his editor earns a failing grade as there are a number of
                words / names that are miss-spelled.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Discourse on Method and Meditations on First
                    Philosophy</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Rene Descartes</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>12/31/20</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Translated by Donald Cress. This could actually count as two book, I suppose.
                The Discourse on Method describes Decartes' approach for approaching the development
                of knowledge. In a way, it a precursor of the modern scientific method. Meditations
                on Philosophy is more a development of why a human's ability to think is the
                'essence' of their existence as a person, why the mind is distinct from the body and
                how this knowledge confirms the existence of God. His famous phrase: "I think
                therefore I am" appears in the Discourse, but is fully developed in the Meditations.
                Personally, I think he is more influenced by Plato and his concept of "ideal forms",
                but I think he takes this too far in his distinguishing a person's mind and body. I
                also think that he would be shocked at the lengths to which some later philosophers
                and scientists have taken this insight. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="bookOfTheYear">
            <d:title>Book of the Year</d:title>
            <d:para>Three candidates this year; <d:emphasis role="underline">The
                    Aviator</d:emphasis> and <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">Envy</emphasis> based upon initial grades and <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Nicomachean
                    Ethics</emphasis> based upon the influence it has exerted on my further reading
                interests. I have finished more books this year than in any single year since I have
                started keeping a record of what I read. There are a few reasons for this. First,
                Thomas and Anna are both in college now, so I have much more free time that is not
                devoted to their activities. Second, the COVID pandemic has prevented any travel,
                and greatly reduced the frequency of social interaction outside of the home. And
                finally, my government agency's decision to split the workforce into two teams and
                have only one team come in to the office on any given week has also provided more
                free time. In a way, this makes it harder for a book to stand out as the best. In
                another way, since I used my extra time to read a number of books that have been
                gathering dust on our bookshelves, there were a lot more mediocre books. </d:para>
            <d:para>So, after due consideration, Envy will take the blue ribbon. Mr. Epstein
                reviewed F.L. Lucas's <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">Style</emphasis> this year in First Things magazine. After
                reading his review, I considered purchasing Mr. Lucas' book for Thomas and Anna to
                aid in their own writing at college. But after reading Style, I instead opted to
                print out Mr. Epstein's review and place it inside a copy of Envy for both Thomas
                and Anna. Mr. Epstein, the student, has far surpassed his master, Mr. Lucas. Second
                place goes to <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline"
                    >Nicomachean Ethics</emphasis> and third to <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">The
                Aviator</emphasis>.</d:para>
            <d:para>One additional note, my reading this year was heavily influenced by the readings
                in Anna's freshman English class at Notre Dame. Her teacher is providing a
                fire-house introduction to Western thought. In the fall semester, she was required
                to read The Science of the Good, Aristotle's <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Nicomachean Ethics</emphasis>, Plato's
                    <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Republic</emphasis>, Lucretius
                    <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">On the Nature
                    of Things</emphasis>, St. Augustine's <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Confessions</emphasis>,
                    <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">The
                    Rule</emphasis> of St. Benedict, selections from the Koran, David Bentley Hart's
                    <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">The Experience
                    of God</emphasis>, Thomas a'Kempis' <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">The Imitation of
                    Christ</emphasis>, <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">The Letters of Abelard &amp; Heloise</emphasis>, selections
                from St. Thomas Aquinas' <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">Summa Theologica,</emphasis> and writings by St. Francis of
                Assisi, St. Clare and St. Theresa of Avila. Her reading list for the second semester
                will be: Shakespeare's <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">Othello</emphasis>, Rene Descartes' <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Discourse on
                    Method</emphasis>, Diderot's <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">D'Alembert's Dream</emphasis>, Erasmus and Martin Luther's
                    <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Discourse on
                    Free Will</emphasis>, Pascal's <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">Pensees</emphasis>, Rousseau's <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Reveries of the Solitary
                    Walker</emphasis>, Hobbes' <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">Leviathan</emphasis>, Goethe's <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Sorrows of Young
                    Werther</emphasis>, Shelley's <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">Frankenstein</emphasis>, Freud's <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">The Future of an
                    Illusion</emphasis>, Marx's <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">Communist Manifesto</emphasis>, Nietzsche's <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Twilight of the
                    Idols</emphasis>, John Stuart Mill's <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">On Liberty,
                    Utilitarianism and Other Essays</emphasis> and Sartre’s <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">No Exit and Three Other
                    Plays</emphasis>. In addition to a broad exposure to Western thought, theology
                and philosophy, there is a common thread of examining the alleged conflict between
                science and religion. This has motivated me to read these works as well, both to
                fill gaps in my own education and allow Anna and I to be able to discuss the
                readings. This had certainly made for some fun dinner table conversations!</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:chapter>
    <d:chapter>
        <d:title>2021</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Know Your Enemies: Modern
                Battle</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Lt. Col. Paul W.
                    Thompson</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/17/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>On the cover of this book is written in ink: "Med. Det. 405th. Do not remove
                from room." Apparently my Grandfather (Thaddeus Paul Krush) failed to read that
                instruction! Published by the Army Orientation Courser. This is a collection of
                accounts of German army actions in Poland, France, Yugoslavia, and Greece intended
                to familiarize Army officers with what to expect when fighting the Germans. Since it
                was published early in the war (1942) the source of its information came from German
                publication supplemented by accounts in the European press. Thus, the details are
                lacking in certainty. Stylistically, it is rather dry, as one would expect from Army
                training material. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Leviathan</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Thomas Hobbes</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/25/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>This was a long, painful book to read. Much of this is due to style; in essence,
                this is a text book on political science in the language and style of the
                mid-1600's. When reading Shakespeare, the effort required to stick with sometimes
                obscure text is worthwhile because otherwise the poetic language would be lost in
                translating it to current English. This book, which seeks to make an intellectual
                argument, would be greatly improved by a "translation" to current usage.
                Difficulties with style aside, this book remains famous for Hobbes' argument for the
                basis of government in a "social contract" of the people. Hobbes argues that this is
                due to man's fear of death and the chaos of the state of nature in which every
                person pursues their own benefit. The positive insight of his social contract is the
                idea that government is ultimately derived from the people. In a more current
                reformulation, that "government exists for the people, not the people for the
                government." The downside to his social contract theory is his assertion that once a
                people has a given form of government, then they are duty bound to maintain that
                government no matter what. Moving past the social contract theory, he spends a great
                deal of time on the role of Christianity in government. He notes that there is a
                difference between civil law and Church law, but notes that while Church law is
                universal in scope, it can only be enforced by civil authority. And since civil
                authority derives from the people of the commonwealth, it is up to the ruler of the
                commonwealth to enforce, not the Church. But this involves the reader in the
                arguments of the Protestants against the Catholics. In fact, he spends a great deal
                of ink refuting a work by St. Robert Bellarmine. He also take a dim view of the
                ancient Greek philosophers. He thinks that the Greeks corrupted Jewish and Christian
                faith with the idea of demons and spirits and that they argue endlessly about
                universal forms and essences. While Hobbes uses the Bible for texts to back his
                arguments, his point of view is that human nature can be explained without recourse
                to the idea of the "highest good." Personally, I think his antipathy to Aristotle in
                particular is due to his favor with the Catholic Scholastics. For his style of
                argument could be said to follow closely to Aristotle - he takes great care in
                defining his terms, stating his arguments and supporting them with examples from
                history and the Scriptures. Yet it must be said that he falls short of Aristotle and
                Aquinas in that he is generally content to dismiss those with whom he disagrees
                rather than to honestly engage with them. Then again, that would have made this a
                much longer book! One final personal observation - I personally like the use of the
                term "common-wealth" to refer to a government as it emphasizes the goal of the
                common good. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Rameau's Nephew &amp; D'Alembert's Dream
                </d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Denis Diderot</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/28/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Actually two separate works in a single volume. These two books are French
                Enlightenment critiques of morality, religion and science. As an expression of a
                materialist philosophy of nature, these offer little improvement on Lucretius' On
                the Nature of Things. The science is more up-to-date (but still primitive by current
                standards) and yet the argument against the existence of God because we have a
                better understanding of how the physical laws of nature work is still not
                convincing. And while providing a witty critique of the mores of late ancient-regime
                French culture, it does not offer an alternative that can replace Judeo-Christian
                morality or Greek / Roman ethics. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Reveries of the Solitary
                Walker</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Jean-Jaques
                    Rousseau</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/30/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I do not understand why anyone would see that this book is fit for publishing,
                nor to assign for reading. If this were the only work by which to judge him, I
                believe that he would have long since been forgotten. These reflections were written
                late in his life, and in all honesty, they seem to be the reflections of someone
                suffering from self-delusion and even paranoia. One reflection has an interesting
                discussion on truth, another on his interest in botany. And throughout, he seems to
                hold a sort of proto-romantic view of the benefits of being close to nature and the
                problems with society and commercial interests. But I would say that close to 90% of
                this work relates to his struggle with his persecutions, which seem to have existed
                largely in his own imagination.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Strange Death of Adolf
                Hitler</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Anonymous</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>1/31/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>1</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Inherited from Nanny; the book is stamped with "Green Bird Circulating Library,
                Sewickley, Pa." This is a really strange book - published in 1939, it is a story of
                a "body double" for Adolf Hitler. Hitler winds up being poisoned in 1938 and his
                body double is installed as Hitler. The plot is outlandish, but the point of the
                book seems to be a presentation of the inner workings of the Nazi party. Couldn't
                finish the book; too far fetched, and really, who wants to spend time with Hitler,
                Goring and Goebels, even if in caricature?</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Hellenika</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Xenophon</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/2/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A Christmas present from Stacy and the kids. Another volume in the Landmark
                series of classical history. Xenophon was a student of Socrates, a contemporary of
                Plato and a soldier who commanded the "10,000" Greek mercenaries in a retreat from
                modern day Iraq to the shores of the Black Sea in present day Turkey. This work
                picks up where Thucydides left off in the Peloponnesian War, and continues thru the
                period when Thebes ended Sparta's days as a great military power. On one hand, it is
                easy to see how the Greek city states wore themselves out in two generations of
                ceaseless warfare and set the stage for their conquest by Philip of Macedon. On the
                other hand, they gained two generations worth of military expertise which Alexander
                was able to turn loose upon the Persian Empire. His stye is easier to read than
                Thucydides, but his pro-Spartan sympathies shade his accounts. And true to the
                Landmark tradition, this book is a treasure trove of maps, footnotes and appendices
                to allow the modern reader to make sense of the details.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Sorrows of Young
                Werther</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Johann Wolfgang von
                    Goethe</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/7/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>The story of a young man who shoots himself after falling in love with a woman
                engaged (and then married) to another. While technically not a part of the
                "Romantic" period of art and literature, this novel suffers from the overwrought
                nature of that period. Perhaps this book is more appealing to the young, but I
                cannot recommend it. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Astoria</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Peter Stark</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/11/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A brief history of John Jacob Astor's attempt to create a trading post on the
                Columbia River in present day Oregon. Mr. Stark is a journalist, and stylistically
                this reads more like an extended magazine article than a history.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The New Organon</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Francis Bacon</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/11/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Francis Bacon concluded that philosophy of Aristotle in particular, and the
                Greeks in general, based as they are upon the principles of logic and deduction,
                were no longer of use for advancing human knowledge. So, in this work, he outlines
                an approach for using inductive reasoning in the pursuit of scientific knowledge. He
                recognized that the risk of using an inductive approach would be to get lost in an
                endless accumulation of facts, so he proposed a framework for guiding induction.
                This work is clearly a milestone in the development of the scientific method, but it
                is not without its flaws. With the passage of time, it turns out that deduction is
                still useful, even in science. And, after stating his purpose, it is rather
                difficult to follow the framework he proposes for developing induction as he
                proposes a long list of "aphorisms" to guide the quest for knowledge. And he is not
                particularly good about defining his terms - in fact, he seems somewhat hostile to
                the idea of spending much time in "philology." So I recommend the first two sections
                of this book, but skip the rest.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Campaigns of Alexander</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Arrian</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/13/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Another volume in the Landmark Series of
                ancient history; a gift for Christmas. Arrian's coverage of the reign of Alexander
                is very interesting. As always, the quality of the book is top notch.</para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Communist Manifesto</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Karl Mark and Friedrich
                    Engels</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/13/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Another selection from Anna's English reading list this semester. Marx and
                Engles are surely rolling in their graves at the fact that Amazon is profiting from
                the sale of this short work; although I must say that I am proud to have found a
                version that was free ;) They do have a strong critique of the impact of the
                industrial revolution on the lives of the working class. But their "10 point plan"
                for resolving the problem has been pretty convincingly proven wrong by the Soviet
                Union and even "Communist" China. I think their problem is that they think too much
                in generalizations and offer no insight into individual responses to individual
                conditions. And even from the very beginning, the fathers of communism show a talent
                for labelling different versions of socialism that need to be rooted out along with
                the industrialists and capitalists. Considering that I graduated from college in the
                waning days of the Soviet Union, it is somewhat surprising that I have never had
                occasion to read this work until now. But having finally read it, I can say that I
                did not miss much.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Let Us Dream</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Pope Francis and Austen
                    Ivereigh</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/24/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Stylistically, this book is somewhat of a mess. There is an overall structure
                that is clear, but each individual section often feels like ideas are just thrown
                together. In reading the afterwards, Dr. Ivereigh states that the book started with
                a period of questions and answers and then he developed some themes as pointed out
                by Pope Francis. I think a strictly Q&amp;A format would have been more effective.
                The book is not universal in scoped; the target audience seems to be only the
                developed Western countries. The Pope, as the head of the universal Church, clearly
                articulates the final causes to which our response to the COVID-19 pandemic should
                aim. His suggestions as to the means to the final end are simplistic (dare I say
                naive) and contradictory. Pope Francis possess great charm and charisma, but in this
                book his concern for the souls of the believers and the well being of the
                marginalized are diminished by concrete suggestions of dubious value.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">On Liberty, Utilitarianism and Other
                    Essays</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>John Stuart Mill</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>2/25/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>In the matter of style, Mr. Mill is too verbose. But that is largely due to the
                stylistic difference between the mid-1800's and today. "On Liberty" is an exposition
                of what today we would call "Classical Liberalism," and some of its tenets seem
                amenable to modern day Libertarians. "Utilitarianism" is a defense of the idea that
                moral goodness shroud be determined by the "greatest happiness" principal where what
                is good is that which produces happiness for the greatest number of people. His idea
                of happiness seems to drift from that of Socrates/Plato/Aristotle, but not so far as
                the modern conception of happiness with "feeling good" or self-esteem. Personally, I
                found "Considerations on Representative Government" to be the most thought
                provoking. Finally, his calls for equal rights for women in "The Subjugation of
                Women" have largely been vindicated. Although, I must add that he address only in
                passing the danger to a women that they bear the cost in time, money and emotional
                energy for the raising of children. Mr. Mill does not seem to consider the
                possibility that women will be abandoned by their husbands (or, in the modern case
                by their romantic partners) and left to raise the children alone.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Twilight of the Idols &amp;
                    Anti-Christ</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Friedrich
                    Nietzsche</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/4/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Two books in one volume. My first encounter with Nietzsche was in college in my
                Western Culture class where we were assigned selections from his Birth of Tragedy. I
                found his writing to dense and hard to read, and I never bothered to read the entire
                book. These two books have the advantage of being much easier to read. Instead of
                long academic discussions, he seems to have come to favor collections of short
                fragments. But he gave up any attempts at reason or logic and issues a steady stream
                of invective and ad hominem attacks in place of arguments. So, in illustration,
                let's turn the tables on Prof. Nietzsche. "He is obsessed with sickness and
                associates this with Western morality in general and Christianity in particular. The
                psychologist will say that the loss of his father at an early age made him angry at
                God, the ultimate father figure. He tried to be the obedient son and pursued
                theological studies, but when he contracted syphilis in a visit to a brothel, he
                found the guilt too much to bear. Instead of reforming himself, he turned on
                Christianity as the cause of his guilt and remorse. His horror at his own sickness
                lead him to label Christianity as a religion of sickness. His insignificance and
                lack of success after a promising start to his academic career made him envious and
                obsessed with a will to power, a power he would never possess himself. His acid pen
                was a cry for attention from those he envied but would never pay him heed." If I
                were to carry this exercise on for 100 pages and throw in frequent proclamations of
                how smart I am for being the first to ever think such bold thoughts, then you will
                have a sense of his style. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Future of an Illusion</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Sigmund Freud</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/11/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>2</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Freud's argument that religion is an illusion based upon human "wish"
                fulfillment. He also argues that scientific knowledge makes religion obsolete and
                that it will soon pass away. This is ironic, for he provides no actual evidence for
                his assertions. Freud was a genius in the development of psychoanalysis to treat
                mental illness, but many of his ideas have not stood the test of time. This book, in
                which he moves into areas not amenable to the scientific method, can only convert
                those whose inclination is already to un-belief. Freud says that those who do not
                agree are clinging to an illusion. Those who believe know that in this subject,
                Freud is the delusional one making claims in the name of science that science cannot
                support.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Remade for Happiness</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Fulton J. Sheen</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/12/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Having read Nicomachean Ethics last year, for Lent this year I picked out two
                books exploring the Christian concept of happiness. Archbishop Sheen lays out the
                Christian view that happiness lies in discovering and living with the transcendent
                love of God. This book is written for the "popular" audience, and so he relies much
                more on argument by analogy than on theological arguments from reason. Not bad, but
                better suited to young adults or those new to Catholicism.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">On the Good Life</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Marcus Tullius
                    Cicero</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/22/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A selection of Cicero's writings that pertain to the definition of a "Good"
                life. Cicero was a student of Greek philosophy, and in these selections he applies
                his learning to life in Rome. I don't find his attempts at dialogue to be as
                effective as Plato's in illuminating philosophical points. But they do offer
                interesting insights into Roman culture. This was one of Thomas' books from his
                "Western Political Thought " course, and it fit in nicely with my Lenten reading
                focusing on what is "happiness."</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Discourses Addressed to Mixed
                    Congregations</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Cardinal St. John Henry
                    Newman</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/23/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Anna was assigned selections of this book in her English class. This is a
                collection of essays by Cardinal Newman outlining the Catholic faith and its
                applicability to the citizens of Great Britain. He offers persuasive arguments in
                favor of Catholic tradition, but his style - like many educated Englishmen of the
                mid-1800's - can be dense.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Finding True Happiness</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Fr. Robert
                    Spitzer</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>3/26/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Picked this up for Lenten reading following this year's theme of "eudaimonia" or
                "happiness." This is not a classic in the literary sense, but the book does bear
                another reading. It is part textbook, part self-help guide and part personal
                testimony. Where Cardinal Sheen's book on the same topic can be likened to a
                pre-game speech by a coach to a team, this is more like a plan for running the
                team's whole season from pre-season workouts, through practices and onto game
                strategy. There are three more volumes that build upon this book. The question is,
                do I re-read this with an eye to some of the practical recommendations or do I
                finish the entire series first?</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Leadership and Command in the American Civil
                    War</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Steven E. Woodworth,
                    editor</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/6/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A collection of essays rather than an actual book on the topic. In general, the
                essayists focus on a particular general, generally in light of an experience in
                which their performance was criticized or found wanting. One of the six was a junior
                officer in the Army early in his career, but the point of view of all the articles
                is more that of an academic. For instance, the first essay is on Joseph Johnson and
                his relationship with Jefferson Davis. The author high lights the various ways in
                which Johnson was an ineffective general and he ascribes most of this to his
                personal insecurity and hostility to superiors. Certainly true points. But he covers
                only briefly the military aspects of his poor performance. He mentions his penchant
                for strategic withdrawls to perserve the fighting strength of his armies and notes
                his consistent failure to actually reconnointer and plan his withdrawls ahead of
                time. This resulted in many instances where he was forced to destroy scarce
                resources that could have been saved with planning. In noting these failures, the
                essay then examines his hesitency to take responsibility for actions that might harm
                his reputation, but does not examine his relationships with his subordinates or the
                composition or capabilities of his staff. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Reflections on the Psalms</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>C.S. Lewis</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/6/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>My second go around with this fine book. As much a reflection of how Christians
                read and understand the Old Testament as it is a guide to making sense of the Psalms
                themselves. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Gallifumry</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Joseph Epstein</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/6/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A collection of recent essays by Mr. Epstein. A number of these I have already
                encountered in either the Wall Street Journal or First Things. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Notes From Underground</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Fyodor
                    Dostoyevsky</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/11/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An ugly, unsympathetic narrator. The translator notes indicate that this work is
                a satiric takedown of Russian nihilist thought. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Lincoln's Lieutenants: The High Command of the
                    Army of the Potomac</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Stephen Sears</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>4/25/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>The title is obviously a nod to Douglas Southal Freeman's "Lee's Lieutenants,"
                and the topic is in many ways similar to Bruce Catton's trilogy of books on the Army
                of the Potomac, with more of a focus on the high command than on the common soldier.
                I have not yet read Mr. Freeman's work, but Mr. Sears is nearly as good a narrative
                writer as Mr. Catton. As a study of the Union high command, Mr. Sears choses to
                re-tell the history of the Army of the Potomac and to include relevant discussions
                on the key generals throughout. This is in contrast to Thomas Buell's approach in
                "The Warrior Generals" where he chose 3 pairs of generals to compare and contrast.
                Mr. Sears is more in tune with the political nature of the job of a Union general
                (particularly in the Army nearest to Washington, DC) than is Mr. Buell. But he
                somewhat shares Mr. Catton's view that the generals should have been left to be
                generals, and the politicians left to be politicians. But I think this view is
                somewhat mis-placed. Setting aside von Clauswitz's statement that war is an
                extenstion of politics, a civil war by its very nature involves a political failure
                on a grand scale that no citizen - general or politician or priviate soldier or
                private citizen - can avoid becoming entangled. By 1864, Grant, Sherman and Lincoln
                best understood this; far more so than Jefferson Davis, Robert E. Lee, George Meade
                or George Thomas. The "old regulars" of the Army of the Potomac, epitomized by
                George McClellan but also included Meade and John Gibbon never seemed to grasp that
                the capture of Richmond would be largely inconsequential in the final outcome of the
                war. So I can't give this book great credit for originality or for an in depth
                insight into understanding how the high command of the Army of the Potomac was
                ultimately able to prevail over the Army of Northern Virginia. But I can recommend
                it as a well-researched and well-written treatment of its subject. What I would
                really like to see would be a work, following the mold of Plato's Republic,
                structured around an imaginary conversation between Grant and Lee in which they
                explore the topic of what it takes to be an ideal general.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Right Ho, Jeeves</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>P.G. Wodehouse</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>5/15/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An audio book checked out from the library. Light-hearted comedy, but very funny
                in an understated way. The actor who reads the book really enhances the effect. The
                language is witty and stylish, and the actor renders the dialog with cadences and
                inflections that really enhance the effect.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Ambition: The Secret
                Passion</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Joseph Epstein</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/1/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>One of Mr. Epstein's earlier works; I would bet that the subtitle to this book
                was not his idea! It is an extended essay on the nature of ambition with examples of
                those whose lives have illustrated the benefites and drawbacks.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Stalin: Waiting for Hitler,
                1929-1941</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Stephen Kotkin</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/12/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>The second volume of a planned 3 volume history of Joseph Stalin. This volume
                begins with Stalin having consolidated his control of the Communist party, (and thus
                the Soviet Union) and ends on the literal eve of the German invansion of Russia. It
                covers such momentus periods as the forced collectivization of farms (and the
                corresponding mass starvation), the Great Terror and the opening stages of World War
                II. Mr. Kotkin's style is to open a chapter focusing on a particular period by first
                setting the stage, then providing a large number of short scenes covering events,
                and then end with a summary tieing the events to the larger picture. His stated
                focus is to study how Stalin acquired, maintained and utilized "power" and this
                informs what is covered. For instance, while the mass starvation in the Ukraine and
                Khazakstan was a horrific episode in Russian history, it gets relatively short shift
                in this book after Mr. Kotkin examines why and how Stalin came to his decision to
                force collectivization. In contrast, his relationship/competition with Hitler gets a
                much more nuanced and thorough treatment. Indeed, in a way this volume is a joint
                biography of Stalin and Hitler. One interesting perspective Mr. Kotkin brings to
                light is that for a time after the fall of France, it seemed entirely plausible that
                Stalin and Hitler would unite to knock Britain out of the war (while each
                recognizing that they were almost certainly destined to face each other in combat
                eventually.) While this book is not for the faint-hearted, I recommend it as the
                best treatment of the prelude to World War II that I have read. (And I recall that
                his first volume offered the best account of the lead up to World War I that I have
                read, even though it was not the central focus of the book.) </d:para>
            <d:para>One other note; I finished the first volume a number of years ago but it has
                taken a number of years for me to work up the enthusiasm for spending more time in
                the company of Stalin. I actually saw an inteview with Prof. Kotkin recently in
                which the reviewer actually asked him how he dealt with spending so much time trying
                to get inside the head of someone most regard as a monster. Prof. Kotkin doesn't shy
                from moral judgements, but feels it is important to understand what drove him. But
                other than understanding how evil works in this world, it is hard gather much
                positve, enlightening knowledge from Stalin's life. And so, I find it helpful to let
                a few years pass between volumes. This reminds me, in a way, of my experience of
                Sozhenitsyn's Gulag Archipeligo. It was a gripping, ground-up view of life under
                Stalin but it took me ten years to finish all three volumes. After spending a time
                deeply immersed in the book, the weight of so much misery would soon require a
                break.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Other Worlds: Peasants, Pilgrims, Spirits,
                    Saints</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Teffi</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>6/21/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>I can't remember where I heard about this collection of short stories - probably
                in the Wall Street Journal. Teffi was a Russian writer who grew up in
                pre-revolutionary Russia and eventually emigrated to France. He stories draw heavily
                on her experiences in spending summers at her family's country estate. They provide
                an interesting view of the social and spiritual lives of those who lived in the
                Russian countryside. Not as good, in my opinion, as the tales of Gogol but still
                interesting. I passed this book along to Stephen Brumbaugh.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">John Adams: Volume 1
                1735-1784</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Paige Smith</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/3/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Inherited either from Grandpa Rodine or Grandpa Krush (through Nanny). It is
                appropriate that I finished this just before Independence Day; few played a larger
                role in the decision by the colonies to declare their independence from Great
                Britain. Mr. Smith writes in a rather informal style and clearly has great respect
                for his subject. But that does not mean that he shies away from the faults of John
                Adams. Mr. Smith also includes rather long passages from primary sources, which
                sometime interrupts narrative flow but allows John and Abigail Adams to speak for
                themselves. The book was published by the Book of the Month Club, and although it is
                a hardback, it is not of very good quality.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Politics</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Aristotle</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/4/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Apparently Politics (as well as Nicomachean Ethics) are a sort of collection of
                lecture notes and not completed essays. The lack of narrative flow makes for dry
                reading, but the emphasis on terms and the structure of arguments are clear enough.
                Aristotle's analysis of politics is centered on the Greek city-states of antquity
                (hence the tie between the Greek word for city: polis and the term politics.) As in
                his Ethics, his central focus on on the ultimate "good" of the citizen and of the
                city. Unlike most modern political writers, he doesn't advocate for a particular
                form of government, although he does argue that some forms are better than others.
                And his emphasis on the rule of law in preference to the will of the ruler and a
                corresponding emphasis on moderate constitutions that balance competing interests
                within a city can be seen to have influenced the United States Constitution. It is
                interesting that John Adams so clearly adheres to the principles of a balanced,
                moderate govennment of virtuous citizens.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">After Virtue</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Alasdair
                    MacIntyre</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/10/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>From Anna's humanities seminar reading list; in a way a key to understanding the
                relationship amoung the large number of works she was asked to read. Mr. MacIntyre
                argues that the rejection of Aristotle's teaching on what is virtuous and what
                constitues the "good life", beginning at the Reformation, gathering force in the
                Enlightenment and reaching fruition in modernity has produced a modern culture with
                a view of virtue that is irrational and unsustainable. After arguing that moder
                attempt to re-create / re-define virtues and morality has failed, he then proposes
                that returning to a morality based upon Arititolean principals (defining virtues,
                defining what constitutes a "good" life, understanding means to achieve this end) is
                not only possible, but the most rational option. One key definition for Mr.
                MacIntyre is that of "practices." His definiton is rather wordy, but perhaps can be
                summed up as an activity that can be mastered, that offers some practical, external
                good and, at the same time, allows the "practicer" to achieve some internal "good."
                For example, playing basketball is a practice. If a basketball player practices and
                becomes good because he wants to become a professional and earn a lot of money and
                fame, then the player has achieved the "external" goods of the practice. But if
                another player practieces just as hard and becomes skilled solely for the love of
                the activity (indeed, if they would still play even if they never earned any money
                or if no one ever watched them play) then they would have achieved the "internal"
                goods of the practice. Having defined "practice", here is his summation of views:
                "My account of the virtues proceeds through three stages: a frist which concerns
                virtues as qualities necessary to achieve the goods internal to practices; a second
                which considers them as qualities contributing to the good of a whole life; and
                third which relates them to the pursuit of a good for human beens the conception of
                which can only be elaborated and possessed within an ongoing social tradition." Or,
                perhaps more simply, the qualities a person needs to first learn to achieve the
                "internal goods" in their chosen activities; the ordering of these to the pursuit of
                the "good life", and the ordering of an individual's good life to contribute to a
                "good society." I am not going to lie, this is not an easy book to read, and it will
                definitely help to have read Plato's <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">Republic</emphasis> and Aristotle's <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">Nicomachean
                    Ethics</emphasis> and <emphasis xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    role="underline">Politics</emphasis> first. But his critiques of modern trends
                in philosophy and socialogy and moral relativism seem even more obvious 40 years
                after he published this work.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">No Easy Day</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Mark Owen &amp; Kevin
                    Maurer</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/21/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Recorded book checked out from the library. An account of the career of a Navy
                SEAL and his participation in the raid that killed Osama bin Laden. I have quite a
                number of books by or about Navy SEALs over the years, and this one is pretty
                typical of the genre. However, his account of the raid is quite good. The actor who
                read the book sounded very similar to the actor who read <emphasis
                    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" role="underline">American
                    Sniper</emphasis>. Not sure if it is the same guy, but it was somewhat annoying
                to hear the same style of speaking.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Making Sense of the
                Troubles</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>David McKittrick &amp;
                    David McVea</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/2/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An exremelty well balanced account of the polical and military history of
                Northern Ireland. This is one of the most even-handed assessment of a political
                topic that I can remember reading; each party in the events (the Protestants and
                Catholics in the North, the British government and the Irish government) are
                criticised in both a positive and a negative manner as events dictate. While
                presenting the attrocities commited in their full gory detail, the authors do not
                exagerate their moral judgements. As a somewhat disintersted observer, who remembers
                some of the events from press coverage "back in the day," I find much to reflect
                upon. First, our society viw "democracy" as an entirely positive form of government,
                yet the creation of the government of Northern Ireland following Irish independence
                is a cautionary tale of how a democratic majority can be tyrannical. (Which would
                not surprise Plato, Aristotle or Thucydides.) In preserving absolute control over
                the political process, the Unionist ultimately were doomed to suffer loss of
                control. In rejecting the peaceful approach of the early "civil rights" movement,
                the IRA only delayed the eventual integration of Catholics into a Nothern Ireland
                governement. The Irish Republic and the IRA seemed to think that if the British
                left, the North would magically integrate with the South. The Irish Repbulic seemed
                to have realized much earlier that there could be no solution that was not also
                accceptable to the Unionists, but the IRA stubbornly clung to the idea that the
                British could be terrorised into compliance with their wishes. (Again, from a safe
                distance from events, how could the IRA think that a few bombs, no matter how
                spectacular in effect, could intimidate a nation who withstood the unrestrained
                blitz of German bombing just a generation before?) And the British governent had
                little sympathy with the Unionists, yet their inept military operations only
                achieved further rancor of the Irish and Catholics. It is indeed a tragedy to
                consider that if the British Army and the IRA did not react so badly in the early
                1970s, a political solution could have developed much sooner and with many fewer
                deaths. Finally, in further confirmation that Britain and America are two countries
                divided by a common language, consider this statement: "Some like Hutchinson had
                served life sentences, spending a dozen years or more behind bars." Given that
                Hutchinson was referred to as an ex-prisoner who supported the budding peace
                process, it is clear that a "life" sentence in Britain means something different
                than in America.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Panzer Killers</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Daniel P. Bolger</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/3/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An audio book that I checked out from the libray. This is part biography and
                part history of General Maurice Rose and the Third Armored Division in Northern
                Europe during WWII. This is just an outstanding book. Daniel Bolger is a retired
                Lietutenant General who now teaches history at NC State University. Although this is
                a very well researched book, it is not a dry, scholarly examination of the role that
                Gen. Rose and the 3rd Armored Div. played in defeating the Germans. Gen. Bolger
                writes as if he is delivering a lecture to a class of West Point cadets or junior
                officers in the Army. The prose is lively, and as the 3rd Armored Div. fights across
                France, Belgium and Germany, he weaves in asides that deal with Gen. Rose's
                upbrining, career and family as well as US Army doctrine, strategy and culture. He
                is unstintin is his praise and criticism of those involved in the events. He
                excoriates US 1st Army general Courtney Hodges; in the onc instance where Gen.
                Bolger agrees with one of Gen. Hodges actions, he goes on to note that this was a
                case that reminded him of a broken clock that tells time correctly twice a day. He
                is also no fan of Gen. Omar Bradley and often questions Gen. Eisenhower's strategic
                and tactical decisions. As a writer who was a professional soldier before becoming a
                historian, he is able to </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">A Jaques Barzun Reader</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Jacques Barzun</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/8/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>A collection of essays and other short writings by Jacques Barzon, who describes
                himself as a cultural historian. These writings are a mix of historical studies,
                criticism of art, music and literature and commentary on contemporary culture
                (which, given his long career, extends from the 1930s to the earl 2000s).</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Empire of the Summer
                Moon</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>S. C. Gywnne</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/16/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Here is the ridiculously long subtitle: "Quanah Parker and the Rise and Fall of
                the Comanches, the Most Powerful Indian Tribe in American History." 19th Century
                America produced a number of extraordinary "self made" me - Abraham Lincoln, Ulysses
                S. Grant, Andrew Jackson, Sam Houston, etc. Quanah Parker ranks with these
                luminaries even if no one today knows his name. Mr. Gwynne is a journalist, and this
                history / biography is written like a collection of magazine articles. He suffers
                from the occasional tendency of journalists to exagerate and occasionaly shows a
                lack of understanding of salient points (as in an off-hand comment equating Baptists
                with Calvinists.) Yet he is remarkably balanced in his treatment of the conflict
                between the Comanches, their neighboring tribes, Mexico, Texas and the United
                States. He seeks to understand his subject on their own terms, covering both the
                positive and negative aspects.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Skin in the Game: Hidden Asymetries in Daily
                    Life</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Nassim Nicholas
                    Taleb</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/10/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Mr. Taleb offers a useful heuristic for judging the worth of expert advice; it
                is worthless if the one giving advice does not have "skin in the game", or in other
                words, if they do not share in the risk of unexpected consequences of their advice.
                Mr. Taleb descibes himself as a libertarian in national politics, a Repulican in
                state politics, a Democrat in local politics and a Socalist at the family level. He
                earned a fortune as a trader on Wall Street before turning his interest to the
                mathematics dealing with risk and uncertainty. His strengths are a keen intellectual
                curiosity and the willingness to call a spade a spade. I think many of his
                criticisms of modern bureauacracies is spot on, but I also think, that like many
                libertarians, he takes morality of granted. And make no mistake, he is very blunt in
                offering his moral viewpoint. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">That All Shall Be Saved</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>David Bentley
                    Hart</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/19/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>4</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>David Bentley Hart offers a series of reflections on whether the concept of
                "universalism," the belief that all humans will be saved by God. The popular view of
                Hell is perhaps best given by Dante's inferno as a land of eternal torment suffered
                by sinners; their punishment reflecting the nature of their sin. In contrast, the
                usual argument in favor of universalism is that it is unjust for a crime of finite
                impact to be punished by infinite pain / suffering / alienation. The traditional
                view, or at least the view that I understand from the Catholic Church, is that the
                eternal nature of Hell is not the result of God's desire to punish, but a conscious
                choice of those too proud to accept the loving forgiveness of God. Perhaps the best
                illustraion of this view that I have encountered is provided by C.S. Lewis' The
                Great Divorce, where residents of Hell are free to travel to heaven, but where those
                posessing excessinve pride choose not to do so. Instead of eternal hell-fire, these
                residents of Hell simply grow smaller and more distant; the implication being that
                they would eventually fade to nothingness. But Dr. Hart rejects this concept.
                Probably influence by Plato and certainly influenced by such Orthodox theologians as
                ???, he argues that no truly rational being can freely reject what is best for
                themselves. And the sins that we seemingly freely choose are done so out of
                ignorance and that when finally healed by God's love even the most reprobate would
                understand where they went wrong. I can see that Mr. Nassim Taleb would reject
                universalism on the grounds that each person should have "skin in the game" and
                accept that their actions may result in damnation. But Dr. Hart does not argue that
                Hell does not exist; indeed he suggests that it is the process by which humans are
                "purged" of their sins and restored to full rational capacity. As an Orthodox
                theologian, he does not call this Purgatory, but that is the implication. The one
                big weakness of this book, in my opinion is that Mr. Hart does give a clear
                definition of hell right from the start. His use of the term is always qualified by
                linking hell with great suffering  of unlimited duration. But by the end of the
                book, it becomes clear what he means. And, treating his argument as a hypothesis
                rather than as a proven fact, I would say that his argument may well be - is even
                likely - to be correct.  </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">Only the Brave: July 1944 - The Epic Battle for Guam</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Don Keith</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>8/27/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>3</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>An audio book from the library's website. I picked this up because Uncle Jim,
                who served in the Sea Bees during World War II, participated in the invasion of
                Guam. The book is well researched and includes primary sources from the perspectives
                of the US, the Japanese and the Chamorro partipants in the events. His writing style
                is rather weak, at least compared to Danial Bolger or Rick Atkinson; he isn't helped
                by the rather dull "performance" of the actor reading his book. </d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:chapter>
    <d:appendix>
        <d:title>Template</d:title>
        <d:simplesect label="review">
            <d:title><d:emphasis role="underline">The Cat in the Hat Comes
                Back</d:emphasis></d:title>
            <d:simplelist>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Author: </d:emphasis>Dr. Seuss</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Date: </d:emphasis>7/10/21</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Grade: </d:emphasis>5</d:member>
                <d:member><d:emphasis role="italic">Comments: </d:emphasis></d:member>
            </d:simplelist>
            <d:para>Somebody, SOMEBODY has to you see. Then she picked out two somebodies. Sally and
                me.</d:para>
        </d:simplesect>
    </d:appendix>
</d:book>
