<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <info>
        <title > Paint, Oil and Chemical Review</title>
        <subtitle>Vol. 34</subtitle>
        <author>
            <personname>Trade Review Company</personname>
        </author>
        <pubdate>Dec. 1, 1902</pubdate>
        <othercredit class="other" otherclass="transcriber">
            <personname>
                <firstname>Paul</firstname>
                <othername>S.</othername>
                <surname>Krush</surname>
            </personname>
            <address>
                <city>Bethesda</city>
                <state>Maryland</state>
            </address>
            <email>pskrush@verizon.net</email>
            <contrib>Document electronically transcribed by</contrib>
        </othercredit>
        
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>Charles Finley Nevin</keyword>
            <keyword>Theodore H. Nevin</keyword>
            <keyword>Elizabeth Grafton Nevin</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Transcriber's Notes</title>
        <para> This was copied from the digital edition of the book.  The original book was 
               scanned and published by Google Books.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Issue Front Page</title>
        <subtitle>PAINT, OIL AND DRUG REVIEW.</subtitle>
        <para>Published every Wednesday.</para>
        <para>In the interest of the PAINT, OIL AND DRUG TRADE.  The largest circulation in the PAINT and OIL trade.
        </para>
        <para>D. VAN NESS PERSON, Publisher, 84 and 86 La Salle St., Chicago, Ill.</para>
        <para>CHICAGO, SEPTEMBER 17, 1902</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Death of Charles F. Nevin</title>
        <para>page 470 </para>
        <para>Charles Finley Nevin, of Pittsburgh, Pa., died September 9,
            after a lingering illness of nearly two years’ duration. Mr. Nevin was president of the
            T. H. Nevin Co., paint manufacturers of Pittsburgh, and was widely known as treasurer of
            the Paint Grinders’ Association of the United States, in which organization he was
            prominent. His death, though not unexpected, has made a profound impression in trade
            circles where he was best known and highly honored. In November, 1900, Mr. Nevin
            suffered a severe attack of pneu-</para>
        <para>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="./images/charlesFinleyNevinObitImage.jpg" 
                    contentwidth="4in" align="center" format="JPG"></imagedata></imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </para>
        <para>monia, which developed into consumption, from which he was unable to recover. Charles
            F. Nevin was born in Sewickley, Pa., on May 19, 1848. He was a son of Theodore H. Nevin,
            and with his father he organized the T. H. Nevin Company, pioneer —paint and white lead
            company, of which he has been president since 1870. He succeeded his father as inspector
            on the prison board of the Western Pennsylvania penitentiary, which office he has held
            ever since. In Sewickley, where his whole life has been spent he has been prominent in
            the church, social and political lines. For the past three terms he has been president
            of Sewickley borough council, holding that oﬂice at the time of his death, and he also
            served two previous terms with that body, in the eighties. Mr. Nevin is survived by a
            wife -formerly Miss Elizabeth Grafton - and two children, Theodore Hugh, a senior at
            Yale University, and Elizabeth, a young school girl, and a brother and sister, Franklin
            Taylor Nevin, Esq., of the Allegheny county bar, and Mrs. John B. Booth, of
            Sewickley.</para>
        
    </section>

    <acknowledgements>
        <para>Google Books</para>
        <para> This is a digital copy of a book that was preserved for generations on library
            shelves before it was carefully scanned by Google as part of a project to make the
            world's books discoverable online. See the back of the book for detailed
            information.</para>
        <para>
            
            <link 
                xlink:href="https%3A%2F%2Fplay.google.com%2Fstore%2Fbooks%2Fdetails%3Fid%3De-A1AQAAMAAJ%26rdid%3Dbook-e-A1AQAAMAAJ%26rdot%3D1"></link>         
        </para>
    </acknowledgements>
    
</article>
