<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <info>
        <title/>
        <author>
            <orgname/>
            <address><city/>
<street/>
<postcode/>
<country/></address>
            <email/>
        </author>
    </info>
    <sect1>
        <title>My Memories</title>
        <para>I was born in 1967 in Omaha, Nebraska. Elizabeth Nevin Conneely was 77 years old and
            lived on Samson's Harbor Farm in Mechanicsvillle, Maryland. Before I record my personal
            memories, I will provide a bit of background, although I will save more of her
            biographical details for later. In 1967, Gram lived by herself in the farmhouse and the
            Nolans and the Plowdens also lived on the Farm. William Nolan, who had managed the
            farming for Gram since the late 1930's , died in 1967. York Plowden was hit by a car and
            killed in 1968, although the Plowdens may no longer have been working on the farm by
            then. Gram's oldest child, John Gundry Jennings lived in Huntington, WV and Nanny and my
            parents lived in Omaha, Nebraska.</para>
        <para>The following events obiously occurred long before my first memories, but I have
            scanned my childhood photo album and have my Mom's notes to guide me. I was born on
            November 24th and baptized in the Catholic church in December. Gram travelled to Omaha
            in March 1968 and I met Gram for the first time. I'm not sure what brought Gram to
            Omaha, but while she was there, I was baptized for the second time, this time in the
            Presbyterian Church. Gram was a Presbyterian, and either didn't know about my Catholic
            baptism, or didn't care and wanted the job done according to her standards. I will have
            to ask my parents. My first visit to the farm was in September, 1968 and my first
            Christmas on the farm was in 1970.</para>
        <figure floatstyle="right" pgwide="0" >
            <?dbfo float-type="right"?>
            <title>Omaha, March 1968</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="right" width="1in" fileref="gram-1.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>            
        </figure>

        <para>The first visit to Samson's Harbor that I actually remember was probably in the summer
            of 1972, and I really can't say that I have any specific memories of Gram. What I do
            remember is Dad and Aunt Kathy putting rows of well-rings into the beach to prevent
            erosion and a visit to the Leonardtown Volunteer Fire Department's Summer Carnival.
            Perhaps it is from this visit that I remember sitting in the front seat of Gram's Ford
            as she drove down the driveway. I remember keeping an eye on the driveway looking for
            box turtles, and Gram singing a song describing the features of the the farm that we
            were passing. "Here we go past Gant's Lot, Gant's Lot, Gant's Lot …" </para>
        <para>We moved from Omaha to Maryland in August 1973. I believe that Gram had some health
            care that promted Nanny and Dad to move east to be closer to Gram. Nanny found a job at
            Johns Hopkins Medical Campus in Baltimore, and Dad was hired as an art teacher at Thomas
            Stone High School in Waldorf, Maryland. We lived on the Farm from August until December
            while Mom and Dad looked for a house to buy. Considering I spent more than three months
            in daily contact with Gram, I actually have very few memories of her.  Like many people
            who lived through the Depression, she didn't throw much away. When she was finished with
            a small tub of margarine, she would wash it out and save it for later use.  One warm
            day, probably shortly after we moved in, I noticed stink bugs climbing on the screen
            door on the front porch. I was fascinated by these ugly insects that gave off an
            unpleasant odor when you poked them. Gram noticed my interest in the bugs. I asked her
            if I could have a jar to collect the stink bugs and she brought out a stack of margarine
            tubs. </para>
        <para>Gram was 8? years old at this time</para>
    </sect1>
</article>
