<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <info>
        <title>Memories of Gram</title>
        <author>
            <personname>Paul Krush</personname>
            <email>pskrush@verizon.net</email>
        </author>
    </info>
        <chapter>
        <title>Childhood</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="50%" depth="50%" align="center" format="JPG"
                    fileref="./images/childhood/gram-and-theodore-1896.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
                <para>Elizabeth and Theodore Nevin, 1896</para>
            </caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <para>Elizabeth Grafton Nevin is my great-grandmother, my father's mother's mother. Because
            her mother and daughter were also named Elizabeth, and because I knew her as such, from
            this point forward I will refer to her as Gram. Even if it is a bit strange to refer to
            a child as Gram! Gram was born to Charles Finley Nevin and Elizabeth Anne (nee Grafton)
            Nevin. Gram's mother, Elizabeth Anne Nevin was called "Dammuddy". Gram's daughter was
            also named Elizabeth Anne and always went by her middle name.  She was called "Nanny" by
            her grandchildren and as her grandchild I will continue to do so. And for good measure,
            Nanny's second daughter is named Elizabeth. I will refer to her as Aunt Betty. And any
            references to Mom and Dad with the use of capital letters, will refer to my parents -
            Christopher and Sandy Krush. Hopefully that will be as clear for you, the reader as it
            is for me, the writer.</para>
        <sidebar floatstyle="right">
            <?dbfo float-type="right"?>
            <?dbfo sidebar-width="1.5in"?>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="1in" format="JPG"
                        fileref="./images/childhood/gram-1889.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                    <para>With Mother, 1889</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </sidebar>
        
        <para>Gram was born on May 3rd, 1889 in Sewickely, Pennsylvania. According to the record of
            births in Charles Finley Nevin's Bible, Gram was the third child. The first-born, Ester
            Grafton Nevin, was born in 1875 and died in childhood. Theodore Hugh Nevin, Jr. was born
            in 1878. So there is an eleven year gap between the birth of Theodore and Gram. As Nanny
            told the story,  Charles and Dammuddy were planning a trip to Europe when Dammuddy
            became pregnant with Gram. Nanny said that Dammuddy resented the fact that the trip had
            to be cancelled. I suppose this resentment was perhaps the beginning of the strained
            relationsip between Gram and her mother. </para>
            <sidebar floatstyle="left">
                <?dbfo float-type="left"?>
                <?dbfo sidebar-width="1.5in"?>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="1in" format="JPG"
                            fileref="./images/childhood/gram-11may1890.jpg"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>With Father, 1890</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </sidebar>
            <para>Whatever ups and downs Gram had with her mother, in Sewickely she was surrounded
            by a very large extended family. The five sons of John Nevin settled in the area around
            Pittsburg starting in the 1840s and many of them ended up in Sewickely. A search on the
            FindAGrave website reveals that there are 59 graves in Sewickely Cemetery bearing the
            last name of Nevin. And that does not count the women, who in Gram's era nearly
            universally took the name of their husbands. Gram inherited a strong sense of pride in
            her family and an interest in her family's history. Although very few of the Nevin's
            achieved a level of promenance as to be recognized outside the neighborhood of
            Pittsburg, the Nevins were still proud of their standing in their community.  On her
            mother's side, the Graftons had also achieved a measure of accomplishment in
            Pennsylvania politics. Charles Finley Nevin was a president of the xxx Bank and of the
            XXX White Lead company, so in addition to the moral support of a large extended family,
            Gram was raised in material comfort.</para>
    </chapter>

        <chapter>
            <title>My Memories</title>
            
                <para>I was born in 1967 in Omaha, Nebraska. Elizabeth Nevin Conneely was 77 years old and
                lived on Samson's Harbor Farm in Mechanicsvillle, Maryland. Before I record my personal
                memories, I will provide a bit of background, although I will save more of her
                biographical details for later. In 1967, Gram lived by herself in the farmhouse and the
                Nolans and the Plowdens also lived on the Farm. William Nolan, who had managed the
                farming for Gram since the late 1930's , died in 1967. York Plowden was hit by a car and
                killed in 1968, although the Plowdens may no longer have been working on the farm by
                then. Gram's oldest child, John Gundry Jennings lived in Huntington, WV and Nanny and my
                parents lived in Omaha, Nebraska.</para>
                <sidebar floatstyle="right" >
                    <?dbfo float-type="right"?>
                    <?dbfo sidebar-width="2.5in"?>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="2in"  format="JPG" fileref="gram-1.jpg"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <caption>
                            <para>Omaha, March 1968</para>
                        </caption>
                    </mediaobject>            
                </sidebar>
                <para>The following events obiously occurred long before my first memories, but I have
                    scanned my childhood photo album and have my Mom's notes to guide me. I was born on
                    November 24th and baptized in the Catholic church in December. Gram travelled to Omaha
                    in March 1968 and I met Gram for the first time. I'm not sure what brought Gram to
                    Omaha, but while she was there, I was baptized for the second time, this time in the
                    Presbyterian Church. Gram was a Presbyterian, and either didn't know about my Catholic
                    baptism, or didn't care and wanted the job done according to her standards. I will have
                    to ask my parents. My first visit to the farm was in September, 1968 and my first
                    Christmas on the farm was in 1970.</para>
                
                
                <para>The first visit to Samson's Harbor that I actually remember was probably in the summer
                    of 1972, and I really can't say that I have any specific memories of Gram. What I do
                    remember is Dad and Aunt Kathy putting rows of well-rings into the beach to prevent
                    erosion and a visit to the Leonardtown Volunteer Fire Department's Summer Carnival.
                    Perhaps it is from this visit that I remember sitting in the front seat of Gram's Ford
                    as she drove down the driveway. I remember keeping an eye on the driveway looking for
                    box turtles, and Gram singing a song describing the features of the the farm that we
                    were passing. "Here we go past Gant's Lot, Gant's Lot, Gant's Lot …" </para>
                <para>We moved from Omaha to Maryland in August 1973. I believe that Gram had some health
                    care that promted Nanny and Dad to move east to be closer to Gram. Nanny found a job at
                    Johns Hopkins Medical Campus in Baltimore, and Dad was hired as an art teacher at Thomas
                    Stone High School in Waldorf, Maryland. We lived on the Farm from August until December
                    while Mom and Dad looked for a house to buy. Considering I spent more than three months
                    in daily contact with Gram, I actually have very few memories of her.  Like many people
                    who lived through the Depression, she didn't throw much away. When she was finished with
                    a small tub of margarine, she would wash it out and save it for later use.  One warm
                    day, probably shortly after we moved in, I noticed stink bugs climbing on the screen
                    door on the front porch. I was fascinated by these ugly insects that gave off an
                    unpleasant odor when you poked them. Gram noticed my interest in the bugs. I asked her
                    if I could have a jar to collect the stink bugs and she brought out a stack of margarine
                    tubs. </para>
                <para>Gram was 8? years old at this time</para>
            
        </chapter>
</book>
