<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <info>
        <title>Journal: 1874-???</title>
        <author>
            <personname>Charles Finly Nevin</personname>
            <address>              
                <city>Sewickley</city>
                <state>Pennsylvania</state>            
            </address>
        </author>
        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>1</revnumber>
                <date>2021-04-12</date>
                <authorinitials>PSK</authorinitials>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>
    </info>
    <chapter>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata scale="75" align="left" fileref="./images/cfn001.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        <para>Diary and scrapbook of Charles Finley Nevin. In the posession of Christopher and
            Sandra Krush.</para>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Journal</title>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata scale="75" align="center" fileref="./images/cfn005.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        <para> C.F. Nevin. Jan 15th, 1874</para>
        <para>Died. BROWN - On January 29, ALICE, daughter of Henry &amp; Ellen Brown of Mt. Blaine,
            Washington county. Funeral from Center Church to-day at 2 P.M.</para>
        <?dbfo-need height="6in" ?>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata scale="75" align="center" fileref="./images/cfn006.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        <para> One dan?? at Transylvanna La Pleuilirs Lunding. Say he rushed 20 bales cotton ??? 13
            Aelu lard. Says he can only get 10c but at le???ding bales about 500 # ???</para>
        <para>Pittsburgh, Penn. Jan. 15th 1874. Cor 3rd &amp; Market. T.H. Nevin Co.</para>
        <?dbfo-need height="6in" ?>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata scale="75" align="center" fileref="./images/cfn007.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Left Margin:</emphasis> Feb. 24th a daughter 1875. Essie Grafton
            Nevin.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Right Margin:</emphasis>  Theo. H Nevin Jr. Apr. 24 1878 9 ¾ #
            Elizabeth May 3rd, 1889 8 ½ </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Clipping:</emphasis>  Mr. Wilford H. Nevin, of Pittsburgh, since
            the marriage of his boon companion, is sad and lonely, dining in seclusion, with
            Dyspepsia and Despair as chief cook and waiter.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Clipping:</emphasis> St. Louis &amp; New Orleans Packet Company. For Memphis, Vicksburgh &amp; New Orleans.
            J. ??? A. SCUDDER.  A.J. Carter, Master. Leaves Monday 12th, at 5 p.m. For freight of
            passage apply on board of company's wharfboat of Market st. JNO. W. CARROLL, Gen. Supt.,
            CHAS. SCUDDER, Gen. Fgt. Agt.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Clipping:</emphasis> MARRIED. NEVIN - GRAFTON - On Thursday evening January 22, 1874 at the residence of
            the bride's parents, by the Rev. J.B. Bittinger, D.D., </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Clipping:</emphasis> SEWICKLEY WEDDING. A very pleasant occasion was that of the wedding of Mr. Charles F.
            Nevin to Miss LIzzie Grafton, all of Sewickley, on Thursday evening last. The ceremony
            took place at the residence of the bride's father, Mr. Grafton, and a large number of
            invited guests were there to witness the rite and congratulate the handsome couple on
            their prospect for a long life of wedded happiness. The ceremony was performed by Dr.
            J.B. Bittinger, of the FIrst Presbyterian church of Sewickley. The usual joyful
            festivities followed, and with extorted admiration for the splendid display of presents,
            and the demolition of the good things provided, the evening sped away till "train time"
            summoned away the party and the guests from the city, and the suburban neighbors hied
            them home through a sea of mud, to talk over the event of the Sewickley season. Mr.
            Nevin and his bride started on a tour souithward, whither the kind wishes of all their
            friends follow them.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Clipping:</emphasis> RANKIN - MURPHY - On Tuesday, February 17, 1874, at St. Stephen Episcopal church,
            Sewickley, Pa. by Rev. George W. Easter. JAMES H. RANKIN, of Pittsburgh, and KATE F.,
            daughter of George W. Murphy, Esq. of Haysville.</para>
        <?dbfo-need height="6in" ?>
        <formalpara>
            <title>
            1874 C.F. Nevin. Jan 15th.</title>
        <para>Only one week more and then a new life. All ready. Letters from Alex. Nevin and
            Walter. Hope A will get home. Cold.  "zero" Invitations all out, will be a good many
            present.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para>Present from Mr. and Mrs. Poole Chicago a little early they are in N.Y. - the ??? pan
            all met Tuesday (13th) Good time.</para>
        <para>Died. BROWN - On January 29, ALICE, daughter of Henry &amp; Ellen Brown of Mt. Blaine,
            Washington county. Funeral from Center Church to-day at 2 P.M.</para>
        <?dbfo-need height="6in" ?>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata scale="75" align="center" fileref="./images/cfn008.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>           
        </para>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Monday Jan. 19th '74</title>
        <para>Damp out. Mr. Poole and ??? arrived on Saturday from N.Y. and will ??? over for the
            wedding. Went to church in the AM. Jack was down home half day spent the evening with
            Lizzie "Good resolutions" Only think just a few more days of single Life the beginning
            of a new Life.  Alice was sick yesterday, better this AM.</para></formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Tuesday Jan 20th 1874</title>
        <para>Cloudy and Damp. Spent last evening with Lizzie  the last we will spend together as
            engaged people. Take tea with Ada this evening. Called on Dr. Saturday eve to engage ???
            seemed pleased with ??? on hand some presents to day and in particular from Ada and ???
            ??? figures. ??? is a beautiful present Ice Pitchers and Gobblets.</para></formalpara>
        
        <?dbfo-need height="6in" ?>
        <para>
            <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata scale="75" align="left" fileref="./images/cfn009a.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
        </para>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Wednesday Jan 21st</title>
            <para>Wet day. ??? will clear up by to morrow. Spent last evening at
            Uncle Daniels (??? tea) Rec'd, Fathers &amp; Mother's present - it is a beautiful one.
            Large case of Silver ???ule set. Home, read several letters, "regretts" Mr &amp; Mrs.
            Peebles ??? by up. Lidie gave a very handsome chair &amp; picture. Mau??? &amp; Frank a
            ??? ??? sing. Have a rehearsal to night.</para></formalpara>
        <para>
            <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata scale="75" align="center" fileref="./images/cfn009a.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
        </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Clipping:</emphasis> WHAT'S THAT.  Another wedding is on the tapis for this evening, the nuptial vows being
            taken by Miss Marge Rankin, daughter of Mr. James H. Rankin, and Mr. Robert D. Miller,
            both members of the oldest families in the Sewickely valley. The ceremony is to be
            elaborately celebrated in the Sewickley presbyterian church, which today has assumed a
            decidedly festive appearance for the occasion, the pulpit being fairly lost in a sweet
            maze of great palms, of ferns clinging about the profuse white chrysanthemums. A large
            party from the city will be in attendance, for both the young people are very popular
            here as well in their own town, and have a large circle of relatives. Miss Rankin is a
            niece of Dr. D.N. Rankin, of Lincoln avenue, and of the late A.J. Rankin, of this city.
            THrough her mother, who died some years ago, she is related to the Von Bonnhorst family.
            Mr. Miller is a grandson of the late Rober S. Davis and a nephew of Mrs. L.H. WIllard,
            of this city. Miss Rankin is a pretty girl and quite young, scarcely having finished her
            school days. Her bridal robe is a fairy like construction of white silk and billows of
            chiffon, with orange blossoms in her veil, and a magnificent pendant of pearls and
            diamonds, an imported jewel the gift of Mr. Miller. Miss Caroline Nevin Rankin, a sister
            of the bride-elect, is to be maid of honor, preceded by two pretty little flower girls,
            little Miss Nevin, daughter of Mr. Charles Nevin and little Miss Gormly, daughter of Mr.
            George Gormly.  The maid of honor has a beautiful gown, a Paris affair, it is told. It
            is fashioned of a lovely net, something quite new here, and has a sort of scintillation
            of moonlight green through the meshes, draped over white silk. Her bouquet of
            chrysanthemums is to be tied with long streamers of light green ribbon. The flower girls
            are to wear pretty frocks of white mull and to carry chrysanthemums. Mr. Walter Miller,
            brother of the bridegroom-elect, will serve as best man, and the ushers are to be Mr.
            Swift Miller, Mr. Macon, Mr. Will Chochran, Mr. Robert Nevin, Mr. Harry Atwood and Mr.
            Will Osburn. No reception follows the church service, the young couple leaving at once
            for the honeymoon trip, upon the termination of which they will reside on Harry avenue,
            Sewickley.</para>
        <para>
            <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata scale="75" align="right" fileref="./images/cfn009c.jpg"/>
                    </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
        </para>
        
        <?dbfo-need height="6in" ?>
    </chapter>
</book>
