<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <info>
        <title>Memories of Sampson's Harbor Farm</title>
        <author>
            <personname>Paul Krush</personname>
            <address>
                <city>Bethesda</city>
                <state>Maryland</state>
                <email/>
            </address>
        </author>
    </info>
    <part>
        <title>Sampson's Harbor Farm</title>
        <chapter>
            <title>Our Trip</title>
            <para>Thomas and Anna – let's take a trip. I have a pleasant destination in mind; let's
                go to the Farm. To be precise, let's go to Samson's Harbor Farm on the banks of the
                Patuxent River. As you know, Samson's Harbor Farm is located in Saint Mary’s County
                in southern Maryland, midway between the towns of Mechanicsville and Hollywood. The
                Farm fronts the Patuxent River and Cole Creek for about one and a half miles and
                contains a large tidal pond and several small marshes. It covers about 450 acres
                with about 75 acres of fields. There are about 2 acres of yard for three houses and
                the remaining area are mostly woods with some marshy bottomland. The woods are
                composed of a mixture of hardwood and pine trees, although the hardwoods
                predominate. The driveway from Sandgates Road to the main house covers a distance of
                about a mile and three-quarters. The Farm is oriented towards the river, reflecting
                its origins in colonial times when nearly all transportation in the Tidewater region
                was by water. If we were making this trip around the time of the Civil War, we would
                start with a steamer from Washington to Point Lookout or Solomon's Island. We would
                then transfer to another steamer to take us up the Patuxent. Although the thought of
                such a trip sounds fun, it must have taken at least two days to accomplish. Instead,
                we will make the drive, as we have always done, in about 90 minutes.</para>
            <para> We leave our house in Bethesda, drive through the neighborhoods of DC, along the
                Potomac River and past the monuments. We continue down the highways leading south
                and east from Washington. The cityscape transitions to a suburban mixture of homes
                and strip malls as we pass through Prince George's and into Charles County. Entering
                St. Mary's county, the landscape is increasingly rural. We may even pass an Amish
                buggy traveling on the shoulder of the road. At long last, we turn off of the
                highway onto Sandgates Road. We descend two small hills and turn onto the fifth
                driveway on the right. You both understand that a good part of why a visit to the
                Farm is so special is the anticipation that builds as the journey draws you nearer
                and nearer. The moment we turn off of Road and onto the driveway is the point where
                anticipation ends and we enjoy our entry into a new landscape.</para>
            <para>Our turn off of the macadam pavement of Sandgates Road onto the gravel driveway
                begins the second, and far more interesting, part of our journey. Perhaps you take
                notice of the tall signpost upon which hangs a small sign displaying “Samson's
                Harbor Farm”. In a way, this is like the lamp post in "The Lion, The Witch, and The
                Wardrobe." It marks the transition from our modern world of hustle and bustle to
                another world, a place set apart. From this point forward, you can ride in the car
                without a seatbelt, you can roll down the windows and turn off the air conditioner
                and you can even sit on your father’s lap and steer the car. This is where the two
                of you in your excitement, would begin (to sing to the tune of “She'll Be Coming
                'Round the Mountain”):
            </para>
            <blockquote>
                <para>There are no cars behind us on the road,</para>
                <para>There are no cars behind us on the road,</para>
                <para>There are no cars behind us, no cars behinds us,</para>
                <para>There are no cars behind us on the road!</para>
            </blockquote>
            
            

        </chapter>
    </part>
</book>
