<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <info>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>Charles Finley Nevin</keyword>
            <keyword>Theodore H. Nevin</keyword>
        </keywordset>
        <title>National Painters Magazine</title>
        <subtitle>Volume 41</subtitle>
        <author>
            <personname>Trade Review Company</personname>
        </author>
        <pubdate>Dec. 1, 1902</pubdate>
        <othercredit class="other" otherclass="transcriber">
            <personname>
                <firstname>Paul</firstname>
                <othername>S.</othername>
                <surname>Krush</surname>
            </personname>
            <address>
                <city>Bethesda</city>
                <state>Maryland</state>
            </address>
            <email>pskrush@verizon.net</email>
            <contrib>Document electronically transcribed by</contrib>
        </othercredit>
    </info>
    
    <chapter>
        <title>THE PAINTERS MAGAZINE</title>
        <subtitle>Front Page</subtitle>
        <para>and PAINT &amp; WALLPAPER DEALER</para>
        <para>MAY 1914</para>
        <para>Copyright, 1914, by The Painters Magazine.</para>
        <para>VOL. XLI.   NUMBER 5.</para>
        <para>OUR FORTIETH ANNIVERSARY NUMBER</para>
    
    <section>
        <title>Transcriber's Notes</title>
        <para> This was copied from the digital edition of the book.  The original book was 
               scanned and published by Google Books.</para>
    </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
    
        <title>PAINT, OIL AND DRUG REVIEW, CHICAGO, SEPTEMBER 17, 1902</title>
        <para>Published every Wednesday.</para>
        <para>In the interest of the PAINT, OIL AND DRUG TRADE.  The largest circulation in the PAINT and OIL trade.
        </para>
        <para>D. VAN NESS PERSON, Publisher, 84 and 86 La Salle St., Chicago, Ill.</para>
  
    <section>
        <title>White Lead Manufacture</title>
        <subtitle>A Historical Sketch of its Development in the United States Since 1874.</subtitle>
        <para>By G. W. Thompson, Chemist of the National Lead Company.</para>
        <para>pages 326 - 330</para>
        <para>PULSIFER in his "Notes for a History Lead," states that the annual production white lead in the United 
            States during decade ending 1880 averaged about 55,000 tons per year. Taking this as the production in 
            the year 1874, we find according to the government reports that the production in 1884 was 65,000 tons;
            in 1894, 76,343 tons; in 1904, 126,336 tons. It is probable that the production in 1913 was in the neighborhood
            of 140,000 tons.</para>
        <para>Considering these figures, the particularly striking feature is that the annual production of white lead increased 
            nearly 70 per cent. during the ten years ending 1904.  This rapid increase in production may be variously explained,
            but it is probably mostly due to the campaign for the purity of white lead, which was started in the 8o's and which 
            was carried forward persistently by white lead manufacturers from that time on.</para>
        <para>In the 70's when this history starts, some few manufacturers of white lead still added other pigments to their product,
            selling it as white lead, sometimes with distinguishing marks, at a reduced price. During the time that this practice existed,
            it became necessary to designate by adjectives the degree of purity of product. Those manufacturers, that marketed only the 
            pure product found it necessary to designate their product by some distinguishing adjective. This was done first by describing
            it as "pure," but as some so-called pure white lead was occasionally found to be adulterated, the adverb of "strictly" was added. 
            Some went even further than this. It can readily be appreciated that such a condition of deception could not last long, and it 
            was finally agreed by all manufacturers of white lead that no adulteration should be practiced by them. They were manufacturers 
            of dry white lead, however, and some of this dry white lead was sold to paint grinders, mixed by them with other pigments and 
            labelled "strictly pure white lead." Sometimes this label was placed on packages containing no white lead. The low standard of 
            public morals which allowed the practice of selling, under the name of white lead, materials which were not white lead, or only 
            partly white lead, could not but hinder the legitimate growth of the white lead industry. The campaign for pure white lead was 
            inaugurated and it is safe to assume that the phenomenal growth referred to above was largely due to the confidence to which 
            the public was finally restored. It is probable also that the increased production of white lead was partially due to the fact 
            that white lead, no longer being adulterated to the same degree, was consumed in place of the substitutes. This however was probably
            a small factor as compared with the big factor of restored confidence and popularity. </para>
        <para>The plants manufacturing white lead in 1874 were as follows:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Salem White Lead Company, organized in the 50's by Francis Brown. (There was, prior to this, a Salem Lead 
                        Manufacturing Company which commenced operations in 1824, manufacturing white lead by something like the chamber process,
                        changing later to the Dutch process. This company gave up business in 1835) </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Boston Lead Company which began manufacturing in 1831. This later became the Boston-Chadwick White Lead Company,
                        absorbing the Forest River Lead Company.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Forest River Lead Company (succeeding in 1843 Francis Peabody, who commenced manufacture in 1826), at Salem Mass.,
                        this company later becoming a part of the Boston-Chadwick White Lead Company.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Union White Lead Manufacturing Company, Brooklyn N.Y., which in the '40s succeeded the Union White Lead Company 
                        established prior to 1830, first as a white lead grinder, then as a corroder.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Brooklyn White Lead Company, organized prior to 1830, manufacturing white lead by a quick process - quickly changing 
                        to the Dutch process.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>John Jewett &amp; Sons, who started manufacture at Saugerties, NY in 1838, and shortly thereafter moved to Port Richmond,
                        Staten Island.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hall Bradley &amp; Co., Brooklyn N.Y., started in the '60's, becoming later the Bradley White Lead Company.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Atlantic White Lead and Linseed Oil Company, Brooklyn, N.Y., established by Robert Colgate in the '40's </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Wetherill &amp; Brother, Philadelphia, Pa., successors to Samuel Wetherill &amp; Son, who began corroding lead in 1804.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Harrison Bros. &amp; Co., Philadelphia, Pa., who were the successors to the business started by John Harrison, sometime
                    prior to 1810.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>John T. Lewis &amp; Bros., Philadelphia, Pa., who were the successors to the business of Mordecai Lewis &amp; Co., who purchasing 
                        in 1820 the lead works of Joseph and John Richards, began the manufacture of lead products </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Maryland White Lead Company, Baltimore, Md., started in 1867.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Pennsylvania Lead Works (formerly B.A. Fahnestock &amp; Co.), Pittsburgh, Pa., started in the '40's.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Davis-Chambers White Lead Company, Pittsburgh, Pa., started in the '60's.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Beymer-Bowman &amp; Co., Pittsburgh, Pa., started in the '60's.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>B.L. Fahnestock &amp; Co., Pittsburgh, Pa., started in the '60's.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>T. H. Nevin &amp; Co., Pittsburgh, Pa., started in the '60's.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Suydam-Lawrence &amp; Co., Pittsburgh, Pa., started in the '60's.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cornell Lead Company, Buffalo, N.Y., which had absorbed the old Niagara White Lead Company,
                        organized in the '50's and the firm of Thompson &amp; Co., started in the '40's.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>J.H. Morley &amp; Co., Cleveland, Ohio the successors of the firm of Morlev &amp; Cary, started in 1862.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Anchor White Lead Company, Cincinnati, Ohio, successors to the business established by McCamdles in 1828.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Eckstein White Lead Company, Cincinnati, Ohio, successors to the business established bv Townsend Hills in 1836.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Eagle White Lead Company, Cincinnati, Ohio, started in the 40's.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>St. Louis Lead and Oil Company, St. Louis, Mo., successors of the O'Fallon White Lead Company, started in 1865.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Southern White Lead Company, St. Louis, Mo., started in 1865.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Collier White Lead and Oil Company, St. Louis, Mo. successors to Read &amp; Hoffman, started in 1837.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>DB Shipman &amp; Co., Chicago, Ill., started in the '60's.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kentucky Lead and Oil Company, Louisville, Ky., successors to the works started by Wilson Waters &amp; Co., in 1856.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>American White Lead Company, Louisville, Ky., started in the '60's</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>All of these plants, at the beginning of this period, manufactured white lead by the Dutch process. Since that time there have been
            numerous attempts to establish manufacture by other processes. The only process other than the Dutch, which has really successful is 
            that now most generally known as the Carter process, to which we will refer a later on. The improvements which have been in the 
            Dutch process involve no change in the general methods of manufacture. The methods of manufacture now in vogue which are a development 
            of those of 1874 are as follows:- </para>
        <para>To change pig lead into white lead, it is subjected to the corroding gases produced by the fermentation of refuse tan bark. Special 
            buildings, known as "corroding houses," are provided for this purpose. These corroding houses are four-sided buildings, about thirty 
            feet high and have various dimensions; they frequently have a floor space of about twenty feet by forty feet in area. On the floor 
            of this building, which floor may be of ordinary earth, a layer of spent tan bark is placed about twenty inches thick. On this is 
            placed a layer of corroding pots covering the entire floor except around the edges, where tan bark is packed. This tan bark is known
            as the "banking." In each corroding pot there is placed about a half pint of weak acetic acid (containing about two and one-half
            per cent. of glacial acetic acid) or vinegar. These pots are then filled with lead cast in the form of buckles. On top of the pots 
            a layer of boards is placed, and on these boards another layer of tan bark. Another layer of pots is placed on this second layer of
            tan bark; these pots are filled, as with the first layer, and other layers are placed on this until there are from eight to ten 
            layers of "tiers" in the stack.</para>
        <para>For the corrosion of lead to white lead, a certain amount of ventilation is necessary so that the moisture can be carried off 
            from the stack. This is done in various ways. A typical way is to provide a wooden pipe that shall run from each tier up near 
            the center of the stack to the top. On the top of this pipe is an outlet which may be opened or closed as may be desired.</para>
        <para>When the stack has been built, the tan bark commences to ferment, liberating carbonic acid and generating considerable heat. The 
            heat occasions the acetic acid to evaporate and to attack the lead buckles. In a short time these buckles are covered with a layer 
            of basic acetate of lead. The carbonic acid generated by the fermentation of the tan bark then decomposes the basic acetate of lead,
            producing white lead or basic carbonate and liberating neutral acetate of lead, which has a strong solvent action upon lead itself.
            This fermentation and corrosion of the lead continues until most of the lead is changed into white lead. At times the heat generated 
            by the fermentation of the tan bark rises quite high, sometimes exceeding 180 degrees Fahrenheit.</para>
        <para>When the fermentation of the tan bark has practically ceased and the corroding action is nearly finished, the "stack" as the whole 
            body of tiers is called, is taken down commencing at the top. When one takes down a stack, he is said to "strip" it. The corroding 
            operation takes from one hundred to one hundred and thirty days. When the stack is stripped, it is found that the metallic lead that
            was originally in the pots, has been changed into a white, porcelain-like material, which is white lead. All of the metallic lead 
            originally present has not been corroded, however. It is necessary, therefore, to remove the remaining metallic lead, and to finely
            grind the white lead in order to make it a suitable paint material. This work is done, largely, in iron machinery that is air tight,
            so that the dust formed will not escape. The corroded lead from the stacks is first passed through a screen, covered with sheet steel
            perforated with rather large holes. This screen tumbles the lead about, breaking up the white lead so that it passes through the holes
            in the steel covering, while the large pieces of metallic lead pass out as tailings, to be re-melted for further use. This coarse 
            white lead is then passed through rolls, and fine screens to remove the finer metallic lead, following which process the white lead 
            reaches the condition known as "unground carbonate" and becomes suitable for water grinding. The unground carbonate is then mixed with 
            water and ground with high-speed millstones so that every particle will pass through fine silk bolting cloth. The white lead in water,
            after grinding, is also floated a long distance, so that any coarse and unground particles may settle out. The water containing the 
            white lead is pumped into large tanks and allowed to settle. The thick mixture of white lead and water, called "pulp," which settles 
            to the bottom, is then pumped on drying pans made of copper and dried with exhaust steam, the product being the dry white lead of 
            commerce. This dry white lead is mixed with linseed oil and ground through buhr mills to produce a white lead paste, which is the 
            white lead in oil of commerce. Sometimes the white lead pulp is mixed directly with refined linseed oil in special mixers, the oil 
            combining mechanically with the white lead, producing white lead in oil of commerce, the water being eliminated.</para>
        <para>During these forty years, corroding stacks in general have become larger and more uniform in size; better control of the ventilating 
            operations have been introduced; crane handling has to some extent superseded the use of wheelbarrows and cars. The newer stack 
            buildings are constructed of reinforced concrete; the plants themselves have become larger, it not being considered to-day economical 
            to manufacture on the small scale followed in the '70's. The diversified methods of grinding, so general in the '70's, have disappeared
            and a more uniform system has been introduced. Grinding operations are conducted in closed machinery, so that the white lead, from the
            time it enters the mill to the time it is packed, is untouched by hand labor. The small grinding mills then in use are now replaced 
            by powerful high speed mills. The manufacture has become much more sanitary. The first great step in this direction was in the 
            introduction of the pulp mixing process, whereby the use of drying pans and the dry grinding of white lead was avoided. The enclosed 
            machinery referred to above also made the manufacture much more sanitary. While the pulp mixing process dispensed, to a large extent 
            with the drying of white lead on pans, what has remained of this pan drying has been made more sanitary in some cases by the 
            enclosing of the pans. Methods of dust collecting have been introduced, both for the purpose of preventing the loss of lead and also 
            to clear the atmosphere, where men are working, of particles of lead which would otherwise be breathed into the system with unhealthful
            results.</para>
        <para>Methods of merchandizing have been improved. We have already referred to the fact that in the '70s some manufacturers of white lead 
            sold some of their product more or less adulterated. Now no manufacturer of white lead sells white lead, as such, that is not pure.
            In order to cover the difference in cost of packing, in the early days white lead packages from 100 pounds down contained less than 
            100 pounds of white lead in oil. Now all white lead is sold in net weight packages, the difference in cost of packing appearing as 
            a difference in price. The use of the old wooden package has almost entirely disappeared. White lead is now almost universally packed 
            in steel containers for sizes of 100 pounds and less.</para>
        <para>In general the quality of white lead has improved. Part of this improvement has been due to the generally better quality of pig 
            lead now manufactured. All corroding lead is now carefully desilverized and otherwise purified, whereas even up to the '80's, it was 
            very difficult to obtain pig lead of the desirable degree of purity. Improvements in methods of grinding have resulted in a generally
            finer product.</para>
        <para>No one can question the fact that the largest part of the advance in the manufacture of white lead has taken place since the organization
            of the National Lead Company. Prior to its formation, every white lead factory conducted its operations with the utmost secrecy, the 
            secrets really being imperfections in methods of manufacture.  With the formation of the National Lead Company, these imperfect methods 
            became matters of common knowledge and rapid improvement resulted. There is little to-day in white lead manufacture that is secret, and 
            the general rule may be laid down, just as in old days, that where secrecy exists it covers defects rather than advantages. The chemical
            testing of white lead has advanced in great strides, so that to-day we are in a very much better position to judge of the real quality 
            of white lead than was the case in the early half of the period we are considering </para>
        <para>Attempts to develop methods of manufacture other than the Dutch process have been prolific during these forty years but with few 
            exceptions these processes have been found wanting and have fallen by the wayside. A great deal of the waste of money in attempts to 
            develop new processes of manufacture arose from the fact that imperfect knowledge existed as to what constituted a good white lead. The
            assumption was made that, because white lead had a correct chemical composition, that was all that was to be desired; the physical 
            properties were ignored. While undoubtedly, chemical composition is an important factor in quality, it is only one factor, and the
            neglect to recognize the importance of other factors has resulted in wasted effort and a great loss to investor and promoters. The 
            writer has had occasion, regretfully, to condemn many processes and thereby disappoint many inventors, because these processes did not
            recognize all of the qualities necessary for the production of a suitable product.</para>
        <para>It is a curious coincidence that the only process which has made great strides, in competition with the Dutch process, was patented 
            in 1874. On March 24, 1874, letters patent were issued to David K. Tuttle and James A. McCreary form a process of manufacture which 
            is the progenitor of the present Carter process. This patent, No. 148862, is of great historical interest. Shortly after the patent was
            issued, it was assigned to the Adams White Lead Company of "Baltimore City." The Adams Company, however, were not very successful in
            putting this process in operation, and in 1885 the patent was again assigned to the Estate of Samuel M. Shoemaker who, in his life had
            loaned money to the Adams Company to carry on the manufacture. By later assignments the right to manufacture under this patent east
            of the Mississippi River passed to David K. Tuttle, and west of the Mississippi River to the Carter White Lead Company of Omaha, the 
            successor of the Omaha White Lead Company. Manufacture under these patents was later undertaken by Harrison Bros. &amp; Co., of 
            Philadelphia, who with the Carter White Lead Co., have been the really successful manufactures of white lead in the United States by
            this process. Much of the success of this process was due to the energy and ability of the late Mr. Levi Carter, who with exceedingly
            competent associates built up a great manufacturing business in spite of great financial difficulties. The real success, however, of 
            the Carter process in competition with the Dutch process lies in the fact that the physical structure of white lead made by the Carter
            process is very similar to that made by the Dutch process. Two other processes have met with passing success; one is a precipitation 
            process developed by Dahl and financed by W.J. Matheson &amp; Co., of New York. The other process is the Rowley process, now operated
            by the Acme White Lead &amp; Color Company of Detroit. This is, in principle, similar to the Carter process except that no acetic acid
            is used in the manufacture </para>
        <para>Of the very many plants manufacturing white lead in 1874, a large proportion, when they were started, began manufacture by newly
            patented or invented processes, all of which were failures. Having entered into the business of manufacturing white lead, however, they 
            continued in it, but saw the advisability of changing to the Dutch process. It is probable that this lure - this expectation - of 
            replacing the Dutch by some simpler process - was to some extent responsible for the large number of small concerns manufacturing 
            white lead in 1874 and for some years thereafter, the corroding capacity of the country greatly exceeding the demand. The only solution
            which seemed open to corroders was a combination which would result in manufacturing in larger units and the closing up of many of the
            small plants expensive to operate. Through the many years of disaster, and through methods which would not be countenanced to-day, a
            combination resulted of many of the manufacturers which, however, fell down of its own weight after a time, and from the ruins the 
            National Lead Company was organized in 1891.</para>
        <para>The lure of new processes did not end in 1874. As we have stated above, only one of these new processes has been successful in the
            really large sense. This is the Carter process. Nevertheless, the growth of manufacture by the Dutch process, independent of the National 
            Lead Company, grew rapidly during this period, so that to-day, we have in addition to the plants operated by the National Lead Company, the 
            following plants which are producing white lead on a fairly large scale. These are the plants of the Eagle White Lead Company,
            Harrison Brothers &amp; Co., Wetherill &amp; Bro., Whittier, Fuller &amp; Co., the Camden White Lead Company, Hammar Bros., 
            Sherwin Williams &amp; Co., and the Acme White Lead and Color Company. All of these plants except those of Harrison Bros &amp; Co. and
            the Acme Company manufacture white lead by the Dutch process. The concerns that have come and gone during this period are very numerous,
            and practically all of them failed because they attempted to manufacture by processes other than the Dutch.</para>
        <para>We would like to make passing reference to a few of the men to whose efforts the growth of the white lead business during the last
            forty years is to be credited. Foremost in this list was Col. W.P. Thompson, who took hold of the old Lead Trust, wiped out the 
            questionable features in its financing and organized the National Lead Company. To his energy of character the laying of the enduring 
            foundations of the National Lead Company was largely due. Succeeding him in the '90's as president of the company Mr L.A. Cole carried 
            on its operations with the same devotion to high business principles and a conservatism and judgment unsurpassed. His death left a
            personal void in the hearts of his many friends and associates. Fletcher W. Rockwell was one of the vice-presidents of tht National 
            Lead Company and contributed much to its success. We can simply mention some of the others who have passed away such as A.S. Townsend 
            to whom some give the credit of having invented the pulp mixing system; J.H. McKelvy, of the old firm of Armstrong &amp; McKelvy;
            John Baldwin, whose manufacturing ability made the old Shipman works in Chicago a powerful factor; D.B. Shipman himself, who died
            more recently and whose benefactions are a monument to the city of his activities; A.P. Thompson of Buffalo, Colonel Richeson of St.
            Louis, Joseph L. McBirney of Chicago - all were influential factors. We must also mention the most recent death, that of Capt. J.
            Gordon Taylor of the Eagle White Lead Company, who for over twenty years had been an active worker in that company. We can but 
            conclude this personal reference by saying that there are hundreds of others to whom reference could be made, who co-operated in
            bringing the white lead business to its present high standard.</para>
        <para>In concluding this short history, in which indeed much remains that could be said, we must make a reference to this business
            as a fair example of what can be accomplished in almost any industry by an attention to the ordinary dictates of business morality.
            Its great growth came when by general agreement a campaign for purity of product was undertaken. The present stability of the business 
            rests upon its discountenancing the piratical methods of financing of twenty five years ago. Its hold upon the trade is largely due
            to its broadening recognition of community interest which sees that all honest competition is legitimate.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The Honor Role</title>
        <subtitle>A LIST OF FIRMS OR CORPORATIONS CONNECTED WITH THE PAINT AND WALL PAPER TRADES
        THAT HAVE BEEN IN EXISTENCE FOR FORTY YEARS.</subtitle>
        <para>Manufacturers and Jobbers</para>
        <para>Pennsylvania</para>
        <para>Pittsburgh</para>
        <para>page 373</para>
        <para>T.H. Nevin Company, corner Island and Preble avenue, North Side Pittsburgh; 
            paint manufacturers and white lead corroders. This business was established by Theodore H. Nevin
            and a younger brother Robert P Nevin in 1841, the style of the firm being T.H. Nevin &amp; Co.,
            for the purpose of manufacturing white lead. They were the pioneer establishment of this kind in
            Pittsburgh. The original lead works were at the corner of Grant and Western avenues, Allegheny 
            (now North Side Pittsburgh). A short time after the establishment of the concern Mitchell Finley 
            was taken into partnership. A few years later his interest was purchased by John Irwin, Jr.
            under which partnership the business continued for years. In 1873 Charles Finley Nevin was admitted
            to partnership. From 1841 to December 31, 1879, the firm was known as T.H. Nevin &amp; Co.
            From January 1, 1880 till February 3, 1882 it was T.H. Nevin &amp; Co., Limited, the partnership 
            being composed of Charles F. Nevin and Willard M. Gibbs. From February 3, 1882 until December 3, 1888
            the business was continued by the same partners under the firm name of TH Nevin &amp; Co., and
            on December 4, 1888 the business was incorporated under the laws of Pennsylvania under the present
            title. In 1891 they moved to the present plant. The present officers of the company are Dr. H.W. 
            Hechelman, president; T.H. Nevin; vice-president; F.J. Torrance, treasurer; H.R. Glbbs, general 
            manager; and L.C. Sadd, secretary. The company has a thoroughly modern electrically equipped plant 
            turning out a volume of business which would have been deemed impossible a few years ago. The 
            brand "Pioneer" was used prior to 1876, but in that year was adopted for prepared paints, and since 
            then has been registered in the United States Patent Office as applying to paints and painters' 
            materials and has been continuously in use as a fire-grade brand.</para>
       
    </section></chapter>

    <acknowledgements>
        <para>Google Books</para>
        <para> This is a digital copy of a book that was preserved for generations on library
            shelves before it was carefully scanned by Google as part of a project to make the
            world's books discoverable online. See the back of the book for detailed
            information.</para>
        <para>
            
            <link 
                xlink:href="https%3A%2F%2Fbooks.google.com%2Fbooks%3Fid%3D5abmAAAAMAAJ%26lpg%3DPA373%26ots%3Dwq8kwafdZb%26dq%3Dcharles%2520finley%2520nevin%26pg%3DPA373%23v%3Donepage%26q%3Dcharles%2520finley%2520nevin%26f%3Dfalse"></link>         
        </para>
    </acknowledgements>
    
</book>
